<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the baptized churches from the calumnies of Mr. Michael Harrison, of Potters Pury in Northampton-shire. Being an answer to his two books, intituled, Infant baptism God's ordinance. By William Russel, M.D. A lover of primitive Christianity.</title>
            <author>Russel, William, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2360A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830137</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830137</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34587</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57955)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2018:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the baptized churches from the calumnies of Mr. Michael Harrison, of Potters Pury in Northampton-shire. Being an answer to his two books, intituled, Infant baptism God's ordinance. By William Russel, M.D. A lover of primitive Christianity.</title>
                  <author>Russel, William, d. 1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes: The epistle of the author to Mr. Michael Harrison .. .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harrison, Michael, --  Minister at Potters-Pury. --  Infant baptism God's ordinance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE Baptized Churches, From the Calumnies of Mr. <hi>MICHAEL HARRISON,</hi> Of <hi>Potters-Pury</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Anſwer to his two Books, Intituled, <hi>Infant Baptiſm God's Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSEL,</hi> M.D. A Lover of Primitive Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <q>None of old were wont to be Baptized, but in a grown Age, and ſuch as deſired it. <bibl>
                     <hi>Ludovic. Viv. de Civit. Dei.</hi> lib. 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 27.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Baptizing of Children was not in uſe in <hi>Paul</hi>'s time. <bibl>
                     <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmus</hi> on the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch thing as Sprinkling uſed in Baptiſm in the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap>s time, nor many Ages after them. <bibl>Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> on <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Infants</hi> hath not been practiſed in <hi>England</hi> for about ſixty Years, <hi>Infant Rantiſm</hi> being introduced in the room thereof: Why therefore ſhould Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> revive an Abdicated Controverſie, and force his Diſcourſe upon us about a Non-entity? <q>
                  <hi>For having laid aſide the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, ye hold the Tradition, of men; making the Word of God of none effect,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Mark 7.8, 13.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author in the Year 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUr real Purpoſe and Deſign in preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſmall Epiſtle to thy View and ſerious Conſideration, is to ſatisfie all who patiently wait for the glorious appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and all who have peruſed that ſcandalous Pamphlet ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Michael Harriſon</hi> of <hi>Potters Pury:</hi> But eſpecially to the ſatisfying of all poor Souls, who may be diſſatisfyed, inhabiting in and about <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Stratford, Yardly, Gubbin, Potters Pury, Pauls-Pury,</hi> and elſewhere; and alſo to clear our ſelves from all thoſe uncharitable Reflections and ſcandalous Aſperſions which Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> hath ungratefully given forth againſt us, who are falſly called <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> Therefore ſeeing the Cauſe of God lye at ſtake, and his Holy Truth
<pb facs="tcp:34587:3"/>defamed, can do no leſs than endeavour to clear our ſelves, and Vindicate our Lord and Maſter's Cauſe, owned by Us, and held forth in Holy Writ.</p>
            <p>That we are no Diſturbers of the Publick Peace, but endeavour to live in Love, and to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, is very well known to ſome of you: And that we are not either envious or troubleſome in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, wherein we are obliged to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in Love and Virtue; which may evidently appear in our Carriage towards Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> when firſt he came into theſe parts; who more ready to Vindicate him, and to ſtop the Mouths of them that reproachfully defamed him, than we have been? But Mr. <hi>Harriſon, Ahab</hi> like, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.17. retorteth on us, as though we were the Troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he at the ſame time is ſetting up his Poſts by God's Poſts, and Contemning our Lord and Saviour's own Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Appointment, and inſtead thereof ſets up Will-worſhip and Humane Tradition, as the Common-Prayer-Book declares, they doubt not but that God favourably allows this Charitable Work of theirs, in bringing Infants to Holy Baptiſm. Do but Obſerve the Words, and how plainly they are laid down, then any Unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Man may ſee, how Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Church of which he was a Miniſter ſo many Years. But what is that, and many more of his ſayings, but to darken Counſel by Words without Knowledge, <hi>Job</hi> 38.2. But he hath Confidence enough, when he thinks to prove Infants Baptiſm to be God's Ordinance, in a Book of a Groat, whenas his Predeceſſors with
<pb facs="tcp:34587:3"/>all their Study and Pains could not do it with all their great Volumes.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> that thou mayeſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of thoſe Ignorant, or Wilful Abuſes, Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> throws upon us; and how he Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts himſelf, like Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whoſe Arguments are his Proof, and his Reflections his Arrows, which he ſhoots furiouſly at his deſpiſed Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, beyond the Rule of Chriſtianity, yea, of Civility. But that thou mayeſt know, whether Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s Heart and Tougue goes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conſider theſe following Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he aſſerts from the Pulpit and the Preſs in his Printed Book, that our Way of Baptizing over Head in Water, is not lawful, but a heinons ſin; and after this Book was print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and publiſhed, Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> confeſſed and declared in the preſence of many, he did believe and allow our way of Baptizing to be lawful, and warrantable by the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> declared in his own Houſe in <hi>Potters-Pury,</hi> in the preſence of us and many others, <hi>That God's Decree was before his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge:</hi> Herein we hope his Fallacy will plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear to the World, as it doth in many more of his Aſſertions which you may ſee, <hi>viz.</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>That God hath from all Eternity decreed a particular number of Mankind to be unavoidably dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and leaveth them without any Means of Mercy, or Hopes of Recovery:</hi> And further he adds, <hi>That Chriſt never dyed for them.</hi> But theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo Erroneous in the Eyes of moſt Chriſtian People, he would fain cover his Opinion with applauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt dyed not for all alike, contrary to his former Aſſertions.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> hath greatly defamed the Works of Mr. <hi>Henry Danvers,</hi> in his laſt Book; and ſince that ſame Book was Publiſhed, Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> hath declared publickly, that he had never ſeen any Book of Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi>'s Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; which is admirable, that he which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſo much Honeſty and Civility, ſhould abuſe a Man of ſo much Wiſdom, Larning, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, Sobriety and Holy Converſation, though now deceaſed; and yet to confeſs he knew him not, nor his Writings, all which ſhews his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt the Truth. And many more things he hath unjuſtly charged againſt us, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to burthen the Impartial Reader, nor tire your Patience with Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s Book, which is ſo full of Contradiction to his own Confeſſion at other times, and therefore we ſhall not particularize that which is ſo full of Errors, but ſhall commit the following Treatiſe to your Peruſal: So, <hi>Chriſtian Readers,</hi> Deſiring your Chriſtian Conſideration, and wiſhing God may be pleaſed to give you a Diſcerning Spirit, to diſcern between Truth and Error, and to weigh all things herein by the Word of Truth, ſo wiſhing all good Succeſs to your Holy Progreſs, and that ye may go on in Holineſs, and be Happy here, and Eternally hereafter, is the Deſire of us who are, and deſire to remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Servants to all in the Bond of the Goſpel,</hi> George Boulton, John Brittain, <hi>jun.</hi> William Wright.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is my unhappy Lot at this time to be engaged with Mr. <hi>Michael Harriſon</hi> in this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: Not ſpontaneouſly, but by the Importunity of others. The Cauſe I am engaged in is good; not only as it is <hi>Cauſa Dei,</hi> but alſo as it is in the juſt Defence of his people from thoſe invidious Calumnies he hath thrown upon them. All Men eſteem a Defenſive War lawful, becauſe it's to preſerve themſelves in their own juſt Rights. Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> hath dealt by the Baptiſts as the <hi>French</hi> King hath by the Potentates and People of <hi>Europe,</hi> entered into a War againſt them who did him no Injury, but lived in Peace and Amity with him: And therefore their oppoſing force to force, in their own Defence, and for the maintaining the Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> cannot be otherwiſe than lawful. This is our Caſe: Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> after himſelf was become a Diſſenter, could not be contented to enjoy the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:34587:5"/>of his Conſcience to Worſhip God (by the Favour of our Rulers, who have permitted him the quiet and peaceable Exerciſe of Religion) in his own way, but he muſt be diſturbing his quiet and peaceable Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; Preaching and Printing againſt them in ſuch a ſhameful and unpreſidented manner, that they were not able to be ſilent, but Neceſſitated to write in their own Defence. Whatever therefore is the Conſequence of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, we are to be excuſed, and the blame muſt lye at his Door, he being the Aggreſſor.</p>
            <p>After his firſt Book was publiſhed, Mr. <hi>Hercules Collins</hi> did write an Anſwer thereto, which was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to have ſilenced him from any further proſecution thereof, together with that addition made by that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently Learned Miniſter, Mr. <hi>Richard Claridge.</hi> But as if nothing had been done of this kind, he runs over his old Nine Arguments again, in his ſecond Book, without giving a ſolid Anſwer to any thing that thoſe Gentlemen had ſaid. And for want of Truth, Reaſon and Argument to defend his own Poſition, he ſtuffs his Book with ſcurrilous and abuſive Language, railing and reviling, ridiculing and reproaching both them and the whole Party: So that his Books can be eſteemed by ſober judicious Chriſtians, no other than ſcandalous Libels.</p>
            <p>And if this be the firſt Fruits of his Labour in print, it's adviſeable he either ſtop here, or alter his Mode of Writing, for in both theſe Tracts he hath dipt his Pen in Gall and Vinegar; yea, in the Poyſon of Aſps.</p>
            <p>That this is true, will appear, if we conſider, That he is not contented only to accuſe the Baptiſts in general (who, whatever he thinks, are no inconſiderable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) with Error, Hereſie and Blaſphemy in Points of Doctrine, but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Carriages, fearful Curſes; yea, with Murder it ſelf; and that their Imployment
<pb facs="tcp:34587:5"/>hath been to Play with Rattles, ride on Hobby-horſes, and wallow in their own Dung, with much more of this kind, which I have faithfully Collected from his two Books, and placed together at the entrance of my own, that the World may ſee what a Monſter of a Man I have to deal with in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking.</p>
            <p>If therefore I have let drop any words, which may ſavour of great Indignation againſt ſuch a procedure, I hope the Reader will make a Charitable Conſtruction of it: For as the Apoſtle ſaith in another Caſe, <hi>He hath Compelled me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus given this brief Account, both of the Occaſion, and Manner of Manageing this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, I ſhall commit it to thy ſerious and impartial Peruſal and Conſideration, Begging that the Father of Lights may aſſiſt thee therein, that (thro' his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) it may be a Means of thy Illumination in the Truths of Chriſt; and (through his Grace) of the Salvation of thy precious Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W.R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> EPISTLE <hi>of the</hi> Author <hi>to Mr.</hi> Michael Harriſon, <hi>Teacher of a</hi> Presbyterian Congregation <hi>in</hi> Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters-Pury <hi>in</hi> Northampton-ſhire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Perſon I know not, but I can with great facility diſcern your Spirit, and the Frame and Temper of your Mind, by your two Books; for it's diſcovered (almoſt) in every Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph thereof. I have endeavoured to ſhun following your Example, <hi>Quoad poteſt,</hi> with reſpect to the Nature of the thing, and (inſtead of Railing) to give you Scripture, Reaſon and Argument, for what I have ſaid. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after all (as to your ſelf) I have not loſt my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, you are beſt able to reſolve. For my own part, I have little hopes of ſuch, who ſet themſelves to oppoſe and contradict the Truths of God in ſuch a way as you have done. However, I have (according to my power) endeavoured your Conviction; being exhorted by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>In Meekneſs to inſtruct thoſe that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance, to the acknowledging of the Truth.</hi> But, Dear Sir, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that (in the Judgment of the Apoſtle) it's but a peradventure; be not therefore high minded, but fear: For, (as our Lord ſaid to <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>It's hard for thee to kick againſt the Pricks;</hi> to ſpurn againſt the Authority of Jeſus Chriſt in his Word.</p>
            <p>Sir, One Eminent Inſtance of your Wilfull Oppoſition to Truth, and the Conviction of your own Conſcience, is, that you tell us about <hi>Aenon</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 3.23. <hi>And John alſo was baptizing in Aenon, near to Salim, becauſe there was much water there; and they came and were baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now, Sir, You tell us it could not be ſuppoſed to be done by dipping, nay, almoſt impoſſible it ſhould, becauſe of the extream ſcarcity of Water, that there was not Water to dip ſuch multitudes in. That at <hi>Aenon,</hi> where <hi>John</hi> was baptizing, there was not much water. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is but <hi>Oculus</hi> an Eye, a very little Fountain, now here you ſpeak directly contrary to the very Letter of the Text: For the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, There was much water: And you ſay, There was not much water. Which muſt we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? This is a bold and daring Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>Now Mr. <hi>H. Collins,</hi> in his Anſwer to your firſt Book, ſufficiently confutes this Aſſertion of yours; not only from Scripture, but by the Authority of Learned Men, (who alſo were for Infant-ſprinkling) as the Learned <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond, Eraſmus,</hi> and that profound Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, Mr. <hi>Poole,</hi> who all teſtifie there was Pools of Water, many Waters, guſhing Streams of Water, and that the Word ſo ſignifies both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syrian</hi> Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Now if you had confeſſed your Error in your Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Book, you had heard nothing from me about it.</p>
            <p>But in your ſecond Book you perſiſt in your oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereunto, for you ſay in <hi>page</hi> 33. Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> ſaith, I have contradicted the Scripture, in ſaying there was not much Water there: Which you are pleaſed to ſay is no contradiction; for notwithſtanding the Scripture ſaith other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, yet you ſay, what I have ſaid is true. And you bring the Evidence of the Learned <hi>Piſcator</hi> (after all this) to contradict your ſelf: The words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>videntur ſignificare plures rivos,</hi> &amp;c. That the words ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie many Rivers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If there was many Rivers, (as your Author ſaith) no Man can doubt but there was much water, and that it was a fit place to dip multitudes in. And why you brought this Teſtimony, unleſs to confute your ſelf, I know not. The next Teſtimony you bring is <hi>Hierom, Aquae multae erant illic,</hi> there was much water there. But becauſe that would have directly contradicted your ſelf, you ſay, which <hi>Holybuſe</hi> Engliſhes many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And you ſay the Town had its Name from ſome Fountains of Water ſpringing there. And you further ſay, That <hi>Aenon</hi> come; from the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gnajin,</hi> a Fountain. A Man would have thought all this had beeh a full Confutation of your ſelf, and you had been hereby <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelf-condemned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:7"/>
            <p>But after all this, you ſtill oppoſe the Truth as well as your ſelf, by ſaying it ſignifies an Eye, a little Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſending forth but little water, in conformity to the Eye: There really was but little water, a Man might ſtop it with the Foot. What, can a Man ſtop many Rivers with his Foot? I hope you will bluſh at the reading of ſuch ſilly Contradictions as theſe.</p>
            <p>But yet (you ſay) there was much, that is, many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; here Conſcience began to check you, and forced another Confeſſion from you, but immediately by your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication you contradict it again: For, you ſay, there was ſeveral little Holes, like Eves, guſhing out Water. But in the next Words (you ſay) there was much water. Well, but how do you make that out? As a Bucket-full is compared with a Spoon-full. I was afraid thoſe many Rivers would have dwindled to nothing.</p>
            <p>But you confeſs, there was a Bucket full of water to fill thoſe many Rivers, and to ſupply their conſtant courſe of flowing; and ſo (you ſay) comparatively there was much, and yet really but a little water. If this be not to write againſt the Light of your own Underſtanding, and to ſtruggle with the Convictions of your own Conſcience, I know not what is. We may ſee by this, what ſhift ſome Men will make to ſupport an Error, when once they have eſpouſed it. The <hi>Greek</hi> words in that Text are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> renders, <hi>Quia aquae multae erant illic,</hi> Becauſe there was much water there; as our Tranſlators have alſo done: And the Learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> in his <hi>Critioa Sacra,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>multus, much;</hi> and in approved Authors, as <hi>Thucyd, Homer,</hi> and others, it's uſed for things that are great, large, excelling, eminent, <hi>&amp;c. Teſte Budaeo.</hi> With the ſeventy Interpreters, there is nothing more uſual than to render it thus; as <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great,</hi> Pſalm 36.6. <hi>A great deep;</hi> 1 Kings 4.29. <hi>Exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much.</hi> And it's ſo taken <hi>Luke</hi> 16.10. where it's twice rendred much.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing you have mentioned the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> give me leave alſo to ſet down the two <hi>Hebrew</hi> words that anſwer to it, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Majim rabbim: Majim</hi> ſignifies Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Fontes &amp; Flumina,</hi> Fountains and Rivers; <hi>Rab.</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies in the ſingular much, great, chief; and as <hi>Leigh</hi> ſaith, <hi>Multus magnus apponitur parvo &amp; pauco;</hi> it ſignifies much and great, oppoſed to little and few: But here it's uſed
<pb facs="tcp:34587:7"/>in the plural Number, which encreaſes its ſignification: See <hi>Robertſon</hi>'s <hi>Hebrew</hi> Dictionary, and <hi>Leigh</hi>'s <hi>Critica ſacra:</hi> And as for the other word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gnajin,</hi> an Eye, a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as it's rendred a Fountain in many other places of the Old Teſtament, ſo particularly in <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.7. it's twice ſo rendred in that one verſe; <hi>And the Angel of the Lord found her by a Fountain of Water in the Wilderneſs, by the Fountain in the way to Shur:</hi> But if in this and many other places where the ſame Word occurs, we ſhould underſtand it an Eye, inſtead of a Fountain, what ſtrange work ſhould we make in interpreting Scripture? ſuch that would not become one who eſteems himſelf a Maſter of Reaſon, and a Teacher in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, I perceive your ſpeaking of the Name of the Town, which was not at all to the purpoſe, was to lead us from the Truth of the thing, which was the Matter in Queſtion; <hi>viz.</hi> That there was much Water, as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit ſaith.</p>
            <p>Before I paſs this place, the laſt Words in <hi>John</hi> 3.23. are in <hi>Greek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and were dipped.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vaitabelu, and were dipped.</hi> For as <hi>Baptizo</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to dip, or plunge into the Water, and implieth the waſhing of their whole Bodies, even ſo the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Root <hi>Tabal</hi> (from whence is uſed this Word in the Text in the paſſive form <hi>vaitabelu</hi>) ſignifies, <hi>He dipped.</hi> The ſame that is uſed in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.14. <hi>Then went he down, and dipped himſelf ſeven times in Jordan, according to the ſaying of the Man of God.</hi> From hence you may obſerve, That when this word is rendred to waſh, it ſignifies no other waſhing than what is performed by dipping and plunging the whole body under the Water: For in <hi>ver.</hi> 10. it's ſaid by the Prophet, <hi>Go and waſh in Jordan ſeven times,</hi> and in <hi>ver.</hi> 14. according to that Command, <hi>He dipped himſelf in Jordan ſeven times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to let you ſee what Trifling you have been guilty of in both thoſe Tracts, about the Meaning of this place, Had it been Sprinkling intended, it muſt have been from <hi>Rantizo</hi> in the <hi>Greek,</hi> to ſprinkle; or from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Nazab</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> he ſprinkled; but neither of theſe are uſed in this place, but inſtead thereof its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tabal,</hi> he dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, from whence it's derived, which are as different both as to Letters and Signification, as any two Words can well be; for that Sprinkling is not Dipping, Rantizing is not Baptizing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:8"/>
            <p>Beſides, It's plain, from the reaſon given by the Holy Spirit in the Text, why <hi>John</hi> baptized in this place, <hi>i. e.</hi> becauſe there was much water. But if he had not plunged them into the water, and overwhelmed them with it, (as the word ſignifies) but only ſprinkled their Faces with a few drops thereof, this Reaſon had been without Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: For, as <hi>Cornelius a Lapide</hi> obſerves, A very little water would have ſerved to have ſprinkled thouſands: But their manner of baptizing being to dip the whole Body under water, therefore <hi>much</hi> water was neceſſary thereunto, without which the Act of baptizing could not be performed. And as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith upon the place, <hi>Aenon</hi> (in the <hi>Syrian</hi> Tongue) ſignifies guſhing ſtreams of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by reaſon whereof there was plenty of Water to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the People withall. And our Learned <hi>Critick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Matt. Poole,</hi> ſaith thus upon the place, It is from this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that both Chriſt and <hi>John</hi> baptized by dipping the Body in Water, elſe they need not have ſought places, where there had been great plenty of Waters.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more to it, for this is more than ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſatisfie any rational Man about the meaning of this place: And, Sir, If you will not acknowledge ſuch a wilfull Error as this, I ſhall deſpair of curing your infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly.</hi> I deſire you to obſerve, that the great ſtreſs you lay upon the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gnolam,</hi> Gen. 17. to prove that Covenant of Circumciſion to be the Covenant of Grace, is becauſe (you ſay) that word ſignifies eternal. Now if you your ſelf did not doubt the truth of your own Aſſertion, what makes you ſay in your ſecond Book, <hi>pag</hi> 17. The Covenant of Grace is immutable and eternal, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Gnolam</hi> doth here ſignifie a perpetual Eternity. Sir, this is according to the common Proverb, To run round like a Horſe in a Mill: For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> You prove (as you ſay) the Covenant of Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. to be eternal, becauſe <hi>Gnolam</hi> ſignifies eternal; and then you prove <hi>Gnolam</hi> to be eternal, becauſe the Covenant is eternal. I pray Sir, ſhew us the <hi>Medium</hi> if you can: And 'till you do, it's nothing to your purpoſe; and yet the main pillar of your Diſcourſe is founded upon this doubtful Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Word <hi>Gnolam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, Suppoſe (as Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> hath already told you) that this word is not limited to a perpetual Eternity, but
<pb facs="tcp:34587:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>oftentimes ſignifies a much ſhorter ſpace of Time, then all you have ſaid from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. is inſignificant.</p>
            <p>That it is ſo to be underſtood, I will give you the Opinion of divers Learned Men upon it, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica ſacra,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gnolam, Hebraeis, Non ſemper aternum eſt, ut neque Graecis</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſed ſaepe ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, atque etiam temporis ſpatium ſeculo brevius ſignificat.</hi> This word <hi>Gnolam</hi> with the <hi>Hebrews</hi> doth not always ſignifie Eternity, as neither doth <hi>Aion</hi> with the <hi>Greeks,</hi> but it often ſignifies an Age, as alſo a ſhorter ſpace of time than an Age.</p>
            <p>The Learned obſerve two things that are diligently to be noted in the uſe of this word.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That when it is affirmed of God, or other eternal things, then it deſigns an abſolute Perpetuity and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</item>
               <item>2. That when it is affirmed of things mutable in their own Nature, it deſigns only a periodical, or circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Perpetuity, according to the quality of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of this latter ſignification we have divers Examples in the Holy Scripture, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.17. ſpeaking there of the degenerate Slave, it's ſaid, <hi>Then thou ſhalt take an Awl, and thruſt through his Ear unto the Door, and he ſhall be thy Servant for ever;</hi> which can intend no longer than during his Life: And it's uſed in the ſame ſence, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.12. where <hi>Achiſh</hi> King of <hi>Gath</hi> ſaith of <hi>David, Therefore he ſhall be my ſervant for ever:</hi> As alſo in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> tells her Husband, that <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhould go to <hi>Shiloh, and there abide for ever;</hi> which is explained in <hi>ver.</hi> 28. to be as long as he liveth: And in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.14. ſpeaking of the Paſſover, <hi>Ye ſhall keep it a feaſt by an Ordinance for ever:</hi> And yet your ſelf muſt acknowledge, this <hi>Ever</hi> hath been at an end above 1600 years agoe; the Paſſover be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboliſhed by the Death of Chriſt, and in <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.16. the Sabbath is ſaid to be a perpetual Covenant, and yet you do no think your ſelf obliged to keep the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Now from hence we may fairly infer, That as thoſe things before-mentioned are not to be obſerved, becauſe they are aboliſhed by the coming of Chriſt, ſo neither is the Covenant of Circumciſion, <hi>Gen:</hi> 17. becauſe the word
<pb facs="tcp:34587:9"/>
               <hi>Gnolam,</hi> everlaſting, is added to the other as well as to that, and ſignifies no more than the time of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy, which was to continue but 'till the time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: They being temporary, and mutable, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the will of the Law-giver, 'till the Seed ſhould come to whom the Promiſe was made, and then all that ſhadowy diſpenſation was done away.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Had you been a Maſter of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue, you might have known, that this in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. cannot ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a perpetual Eternity, becauſe the Characteriſtical Note thereof is there wanting. I will deliver my ſence thereof in the Words of that Learned Rabbi, <hi>Rabbi Moſes ben Maimon,</hi> who ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gnolam non neceſſario ſignificat aeternitatem, niſi ei conjungatur</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vel</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>idque vel poſt illud ut Gnolam vagned, vel ante gnad gnolam. Mor. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bochim,</hi> Part. 2. Cap. 28. <hi>Gnolam</hi> doth not neceſſarily ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie eternal, except <hi>gnad</hi> or <hi>gned</hi> be joyned with it, and that either after it, as <hi>gnolam vagned,</hi> or before it, as <hi>gnad gnolam.</hi> And he inſtances in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.16. the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Jehovab melech gnolam vagned,</hi> The Lord is King for ever and ever. Thus you may ſee, Sir, Thoſe skilled in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> know when it ſignifies Eternal, and when not; altho' you are ignorant of it: And becauſe this is not added to it in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. it doth not prove it to ſignifie ſo, and therefore not the New-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, becauſe that is eternal and immutable. And thus (you ſee) the main pillar upon which you build your Anti-chriſtian Practice of Baby-Rantiſm, is fallen, like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Ark of God. I pray conſider it, take advice, change your Mind, and practice it no longer; for it hath no Scripture Authority for its Foundation.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, I cannot cloſe this Epiſtle, without making ſome further Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon that Argument of yours, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 44. which you have urged again in <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 26. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That all Chriſt's Diſciples ought to be baptized is not dark, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. Infants are Diſciples, therefore 'tis plain they ought to be baptized.</p>
            <p>Sir, If I ſhould deny the Minor, neither you, nor all the World are able to prove it. For Infants are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be made Diſciples by the Miniſtry of Men, which is there intended in that Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>But you tell us, the Command is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:34587:9"/>which you render (as if you did not underſtand it) in this Tautologizing Engliſh, <hi>Go, diſciple me all Nations, teaching them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, becauſe I would (if poſſible) explain this to your Underſtanding, I ſhall firſt give you the Opinion of the Learned upon this place, and then argue upon it.</p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matheteuſate,</hi> Go, and teach all Nations; or, Word for word from the <hi>Greek,</hi> Go make them Diſciples, as it is expounded <hi>John</hi> 4.1. <hi>Diſcipulate (liceat mihi ſic loqui gratia docendi) ſive, Facite mihi Diſcipulos. Vide</hi> Bullinger. <hi>Significat et docere, ut</hi> Mat. 28.19. <hi>&amp; ſimul etiam diſcipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſſe, ut</hi> Mat. 27.57. from hence you may ſee that it is not a bare ſpeaking to them that is intended, but ſuch a teaching of them by which they learned, and were made Diſciples of Chriſt by the Apoſtle's Miniſtry. And as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is rendred by our Tranſlators Diſciple, and in the plural, Diſciples, where it occurrs in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in all other places (ſo far as I have found) and particularly five times in this very Chapter, as I have ſhewed in my Epiſtle to the Inhabitants of <hi>Aſhford,</hi> &amp;c. concerning Baptiſm, why they have rendred it only Teach here in <hi>ver.</hi> 19. the Reader may eaſily gueſs. For you cannot but know, it ſignifies, as a Learned Critick hath it, <hi>Omnes eos qui doctrinam Chriſti ſectabantur,</hi> Mat. 5.1. and as the Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ita etiam uſurpatur,</hi> Mat. 12.49. Luk. 6.13. Act. 11.26. <hi>multisque alijs in locis.</hi> It is taken for a Learner, or Scholar, who ſubmitteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to another to be taught; which can no way agree with little ſucking Infants, ſo ſoon as they are born.</p>
            <p>It is diſtinguiſhed from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Teaching them: For as it's another word, ſo it hath a different reſpect and ſignification: <hi>Matheteuſate</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that the Apoſtles ſhould teach and inſtruct the Gentiles, who were Strangers and Aliens in the Faith and Doctrine of the Goſpel, that they might believe it, and become Diſciples of Chriſt: But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Teaching them, <hi>vero docere ſignificat eos, qui jam diſcipuli redditi ſunt, &amp; Magiſterio noſtro jam addicti.</hi> By which it's plain, that you have no reaſon to imagine that Infants can poſſibly be here intended <hi>(qua talis)</hi> becauſe the firſt word intends ſuch as were to be made Diſciples by their Miniſtry; and the latter reſpects their being inſtructed in
<pb facs="tcp:34587:10"/>all thoſe other Duties, this new Maſter of theirs, the Lord Jeſus required of them, after they were firſt made Diſciples and believed, and were baptized, that they might be made perfect and compleat in all the will of God.</p>
            <p>How falſe therefore and incougruous is that rendring of the Words, <hi>Matheteuſate panta ta ethne,</hi> Diſcipulize all Nations, as you have done, to ſay, Go, diſciple me all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, teaching them, when the plain meaning is, That they were firſt by their Miniſtry to be made Diſciples of Chriſt, and then to be baptized; as it follows in the Text. And not as you ſay, That when the Parents being taught, believe, they are diſcipled, and their Infants with them. For if that be the meaning of the Word <hi>Matheteuſate,</hi> that ſuch who are ſo taught as to believe, are diſcipled, their Infants not being capable to be ſo taught by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Apoſtles, as to believe, they cannot be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (in your own Underſtanding) from any meaning can be put upon theſe Words by you recited, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p>But further, here is an expreſs Command to baptize ſome Perſons. That they were Believers we affirm, becauſe it's ſaid in that Parallel Text, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16. <hi>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That any Infants can be intended by it, you muſt deny; becauſe (you ſay) there is no expreſs Command to baptize them. For, in <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 41. you put this Objection, But we have no expreſs Command in the New Teſtament to baptize Infants. Your Anſwer is, I have ſhewn there needed none. And in <hi>page</hi> 37. you bring in this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, If it be God's will Infants ſhould be baptized, why is there no Command for it, as there was for their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion. Your anſwer is, There was no need of any particular mentioning of them. And further ſay, It had been abſurd to have given a New Command for Children, and your ſaying that the general Command includes Children, and yet never tells us what it is, or where to be found, is a covering too narrow for you to eſcape this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For if there be an expreſs Command in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. given by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, to baptize fome Perſons or other, and there be no expreſs Command (by your own Confeſſion) in the New Teſtament to baptize Infants, then Infants are not at all intended in this great Commiſſion. And I pray Sir, tell me how it is then an
<pb facs="tcp:34587:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ordinance of God, if it be no where commanded by him in his Word? For baptiſm is a part of inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: And you ought to ſhew the Inſtitution, or elſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear practiſing it any more.</p>
            <p>I will now ſhew you what Grounds we have from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for baptizing penitent Believers, that are adult Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, able to give an account of their Faith. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi> is an Author you ſo much eſteem, I ſhall give you his Arguments from Scripture for proof thereof in his Book, called <hi>The ſecond Diſputation of Right to Sacraments,</hi> p. 149, 150. in theſe words upon this very Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <q>This is not like ſome occaſional mention of Baptiſm, but it is the very Commiſſion it ſelf of Chriſt to his Diſciples, for Preaching and Baptizing, and purpoſely expreſſeth their ſeveral works, in their ſeveral Places and Orders.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>firſt</hi> Task is to make Diſciples, which are by <hi>Mark</hi> called Believers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Work is to baptize them, whereto is annex'd the promiſe of their Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The <hi>Third</hi> Work is to teach them all other things, which are after to be learned in the School of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>To contemn this Order, is to contemn all Rules of Order, for where can we expect to find it if not here? I profeſs my Conſcience is fully ſatisfied from this Text, that it is one ſort of Faith, even ſaving, that muſt go before Baptiſm, the profeſſion whereof the Miniſter muſt expect. Of which ſee what is to this purpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited by <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Piſcator,</hi> which Words are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by him, <hi>p.</hi> 85. and are as follows, <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. ſaith, Therefore that Men may rightly offer themſelves to Baptiſm, Confeſſion of Sins is required, othewiſe the whole Action would be nothing elſe but Sport. And <hi>Piſcator</hi> upon <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. ſaith, It is called the Baptiſm of Repentance for Remiſſion of Sins, becauſe <hi>John</hi> preached the Remiſſion of Sins to the Penitent Believers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> further ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 149. If there can be no Example given in Scripture of any one, that was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized without the profeſſion of a ſaving Faith, nor any Precept for ſo doing, then muſt we not baptize any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it: But the Antecedent is true, therefore ſo is the Conſequence.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:11"/>
            <p>
               <q>To prove this Aſſertion, he produces the ſeveral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in Scripture, which (he ſaith) might afford us ſo many ſeveral Arguments, but I ſhall put them together.</q> 
               <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Firſt, John,</hi> as I have ſhewed you, required the proſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of true Repentance, and that his Baptiſm was for the Remiſſion of Sin.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> When Chriſt layeth down the Apoſtolical Commiſſion, the Nature and Order of the Apoſtles work is firſt to make them Diſciples, and then to baptize them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That it was ſaving Faith that was required of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and profeſſed by them (<hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.) is plain in the Text.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The <hi>Samaritans</hi> believed, and had great Joy, and were baptized into the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. whereby it appeareth, that the Underſtanding and Will were both changed. And they had the profeſſion of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith, yea, even <hi>Simon</hi> himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 37.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Condition upon which the Eunnch muſt be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed was, If he believed with all his Heart, which he profeſſed to do, and that was the Evidence <hi>Philip</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> was baptized after true Converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.18. The Holy Ghoſt fell on the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before they were baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Heart was opened before ſhe was baptized, and ſhe was one the Apoſtles judged faithful to the Lord, and offered to them the evidence of her Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Example alſo of the Jaylor, is very full to the reſolution of the Queſtion in hand: He firſt asketh, <hi>What he ſhall do to be ſaved?</hi> The Apoſtle anſwereth him, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaved and thy Houſe:</hi> So that it was a ſaving Faith that is here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: <hi>He rejoiced and believed with all his Houſe, and was baptized the ſame hour of the Night, or ſtraightway.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Criſpus the chief Ruler of the Synagogue believed on the Lord, with all his Houſe, and many of the Corinthians bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, believed and were baptized,</hi> Acts 18.8.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. is determining the Queſtion, and giveth this in as the deciſion, <hi>If thou believeſt with all thy heart, thou mayeſt.</hi> And to ſay, that this is but <hi>De
<pb facs="tcp:34587:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>bene eſſe,</hi> meaning that it includes not the Negative, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou may'ſt not, is to make <hi>Philip</hi> to have delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not decided or reſolved.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>In a word, I know not of one Word in Scripture, that giveth us the leaſt Intimation that ever Man was baptized without the Profeſſion of a ſaving Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He alſo affirms poſitively, That we muſt not baptize any <q>without the profeſſion of true Repentance, which he thus proves.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 1. If <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt required the profeſſion of true Repentance before he would baptize them, then ſo muſt we; but <hi>John</hi> did ſo, therefore the Conſequence is clear.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Antecedent I prove (ſaith he) from <hi>mark</hi> 1.3, 4. he preached the Baptiſm of Repentance unto remiſſion of Sins, and doubtleſs that Repentance which is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins is true, ſpecial Repentance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 2. If Jeſus Chriſt hath by Scripture Precept and Example, directed us to baptize thoſe that profeſs true Repentance, and no other, then we muſt baptize them and no other; but the Antecedent is true, ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the conſequent, which is fully made good from <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. when Chriſts himſelf did, and ſent forth his Diſciples alſo to preach Repentance, to prepare them for Baptiſm, which afterwards followed, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38, 41.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And in <hi>page</hi> 156. if according to the Inſtitution, the Anſwer of a good Conſcience muſt be joyned with Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, for the attaining of its end, then we muſt admit of none that profeſs not the anſwer of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But the former is certain from the Text, for Baptiſm is ſaid to ſave, that is its appointed uſe, yet not the external waſhing, but the anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth it; therefore this is of a neceſſary injunction, and without it Baptiſm cannot attain its End. But it is to be adminiſtred and received only in order to the Attainment of its end, and therefore never in a way by which the End is apparently not attainable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> calleth all the Baptized Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, none that profeſs not juſtifying Faith are called ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified; therefore none ſuch ſhould be baptized. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs (ſaith he) tis ſad, that good Men ſhould be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful
<pb facs="tcp:34587:12"/>to the Truth, which is ſo preclous, and is not their own, and which they ſhould do nothing againſt, but all they can for it.</q> Divers other Teſtimonies might be added, beſides theſe already recited, but theſe ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice at this time,</p>
            <p>And Sir, If theſe do not plainly prove our practice of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Perſons upon profeſſion of Faith; and alſo that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants cannot be the Subjects of Holy Baptiſm, as not being capable of performing the neceſſary pre-requiſites thereto, I have no Skill in Polemicks.</p>
            <p>I proceed therefore to what you ſay, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 44.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> The baptizing Perſons before they know, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions much groſs Ignorance. To which you anſwer,</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the Occaſion of the Ruine and Damnation of thouſands,</p>
            <p>I reply. Dear Sir, Altho' you make bold to abuſe the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and throw very Reproachful Scandals and Calumnies upon them, Methinks you might have ſpared their Lord and Maſter, and not have laid the Ruine and Damnation of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands at his Door, <hi>Who came not into the World to condemn the World, but that the World through him might be ſaved:</hi> But I need not wonder at this in you, when divers of your party have charged Chriſt with being the greateſt Sinner in the World, notwithſtanding he did no ſin, neither was Guile found in his Mouth. Sir, Theſe are unſavoury Expreſſions, unbecoming the Pen of one who would fain be eſteemed a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And now, Dear Sir, as a Cloſe, I have ſome few things to ſpeak to your ſelf by way of Caution and Advice, which I wiſh may be received by you, as candidly as they are imparted by me.</p>
            <p>In all your Diſcourſes about Polemical Divinity, that you would obſerve theſe few ſhort Rules, which may be of uſe to your ſelf and others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be careful to avoid all invective Calumnies, Wrath, Bitterneſs and Reviling, againſt the Party with whom you contend: For that is ſo far from being a means to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them, that it rather begets a Prejudice in them againſt what you ſhall ſay.</p>
            <p>I know, every Perſon is naturally a Friend to what he ſuppoſeth to be a Truth, and wiſheth that others were of his Mind, and it's both lawful and commendable to promote it, in a ſober and judicious way: But ſurely it is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb facs="tcp:34587:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to propagate Truth, (a thing divine) by the Methods of Hell; as Anger, Biterneſs, Fraud, Reviling Reproaches, and throwing out Scandalous and Vile Invectives againſt your Antagoniſts. Sir, You have more Reaſon to believe your Adverſaries are in the right, than your ſelf: For, that they have both Precept and Precedent for their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the Holy Scripture, but you have neither for your own. What need was there therefore of all thoſe bitter Revilings you have poured out againſt us? Sir, We could uſe the Liberty of <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> (if we were minded to recriminate) in ſuch inſtances againſt your Party, that would blacken you with a Witneſs; of which you could never acquit them by all the Artifices you could uſe: But we do not think it comports with Charity, to exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate your Enemies againſt you, and make you vile in their Eyes, notwithſtanding you have ſo unchriſtianly dealt by us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When any of your Chriſtian Neighbours labour to convince you of ſome Truth you are yet ignorant of, do not ſcorn their Advice, nor trample upon the Truth for their ſakes, becauſe they are but mean in the Worlds Eſteem; but remember that <hi>Apollo,</hi> altho' he was a Man mighty in the Scriptures, did not diſdain that <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcila,</hi> ſhould expound unto him the way of God more perfectly, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.26. A Cardinal could once ſay upon the Words of a Shepherd, Unlearned Men take Heaven by force, whilſt we with all our Learning are thruſt down to Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let me entreat you to ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee whether the things I have ſaid be ſo or no; give your ſelf to Faſting and Prayer, cry mightily to God to give you his Spirit, to open your Underſtanding, that you may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Give me leave to tell you, That it's not likely your People ſhould think you in earneſt, when in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit you Preſs them to Meekneſs and Charity, when they find ſo much Railing and Reviling in your Books.</p>
            <p>Truly Sir, If Miniſters Books of Diſputation were as full of Charity, as they require their People to be in their Sermons, our Diſputes and Writings would be Excellent Expedients of improving Knowledge, and diſcovering Truth. And not as now perpetuating Controverſies, and of wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and imbittering them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34587:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>No Debates (ſaith one) have been managed with that bitterneſs, no Queſtions debated with that virulence, as the Theological. When will Divlnes be aſhamed of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing of their Charity to their Paſſions; that is, to the ſenſual and brutal part of our Natures? The <hi>Tartars</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their Wars with leſs Cruelty than the Clergy: For (ſaith he) there is neither Meaſure nor End of our Reproaches and Infamations.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you Sir, conſider theſe things, and if you are not ſatisfied about the Controverſie depending, if you pleaſe to acquaint me with any particular doubt about it, ſo you do it in the ſpirit of Meekneſs, I ſhall endeavour to give you all reaſonable ſatisfaction. For, in ſhort, the beſt Expedient (I can think of) to promote Knowledge is, that we argue all our Religious Controverſies with that Spirit of Charity and Tenderneſs, and of deference towards our Oppoſites, which the Goſpel we preach to others more eſpecially obiiges us to: Then may we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a Bleſſing from the Lord, in ſuch Pious and Charl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Procedures. I ſhall add no more, but ſubſcribe my ſelf, as in Duty bound,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A Sincere Lover of your Soul,</hi> W. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34587:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE Baptized Churches.</head>
            <p>BEfore an Artificer can build a new Houſe, in the room of an old one that is fallen down, he muſt firſt clear away all the Rubbiſh, that he may lay a new Foundation: That Rubbiſh of <hi>Railery</hi> and <hi>Abuſive Language</hi> with which I perceive Mr. <hi>Michael Harriſon</hi> hath lined his <hi>Mouth</hi> in his <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and has ſtuffed his <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>print,</hi> (for he tells us in his Epiſtle to his firſt Book, that he was firſt put upon <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon that Subject, and afterwards conſented to the <hi>printing</hi> of it) I intend to <hi>remove,</hi> before I ſpeak any thing to his Book.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>IN the Epiſtle of his <hi>firſt</hi> Book he charges us with <hi>Erroneous</hi> Doctrines, that we are like <hi>pricking Briars</hi> and wounding <hi>Thorns.</hi> Thoſe <hi>wild</hi> and Erroneous Doctrines broached by the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34587:14"/>have been a perpetual Vexation and Trouble. The <hi>confident</hi> repeated Challenges, the <hi>reſtleſs</hi> Inſinuations of the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> Their various <hi>Attempts</hi> to enſnare and draw away <hi>my</hi> Hearers to their <hi>own</hi> way. They are a ſort of <hi>reſtleſs</hi> People, with <hi>great</hi> Indignation <hi>ſpurning</hi> at Infant-Baptiſm. They tempt you to be <hi>cruel</hi> to the Children of your <hi>own</hi> Bowels, ſetting them among <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> They are the <hi>Enemy</hi> of Infants. The Doctrine of the Anabaptiſts makes all Infants to be of the viſible Kingdom of <hi>Satan,</hi> and leaves us no well-grounded <hi>Hope</hi> of the Salvation of <hi>any</hi> dying in Infancy, and is therefore to be juſtly <hi>abhorred</hi> as falſe Doctrine. Then it ſeems by his Doctrine, that Baptiſm doth <hi>it ſelf</hi> regenerate Infants in <hi>his</hi> Underſtanding, and <hi>tranſlate</hi> them out of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the Devil, into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt. This is plain downright <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>abhorred</hi> by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as <hi>falſe</hi> Doctrine. (But he goes on with his Railery for want of Argument:) What <hi>barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> uſage is this to poor Infants, the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts <hi>perverſely</hi> thruſt them away from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and from <hi>his</hi> Church, <hi>ſet</hi> them among <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> who are of the viſible <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Devil.</hi> (But in the ſame page he tells us,) That the Anabaptiſts do <hi>not</hi> aſſert the damnation of <hi>all</hi> Infants dying in Infancy, but on the <hi>direct</hi> contrary; they aſſert the <hi>certain</hi> Salvation of <hi>all</hi> Infants. (Why then doth he charge it upon them?) Poor Man! I pity him for his <hi>Ignorance</hi> in <hi>Divinity.</hi> We have many <hi>Inferionr Mechanicks</hi> in <hi>our</hi> City of <hi>Londou,</hi> that (bleſſed be God) underſtand the <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> of the Spirit of God in the <hi>Holy</hi> Scriptures, <hi>better</hi> than <hi>he.</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34587:14"/>And there is another <hi>unhappineſs</hi> attends the poor man, he hath ſo lately <hi>changed</hi> his Religion from <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> that he is not <hi>well</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Doctrines, but <hi>began</hi> to write <hi>too ſoon,</hi> before he knew what <hi>they</hi> held, or what <hi>himſelf</hi> was talking of. I am aſhamed to think that a man ſhould <hi>print</hi> himſelf a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> of the Goſpel, and ſhould know <hi>ſo little</hi> of the Goſpel <hi>Church-ſtate,</hi> if <hi>all</hi> his Knowledge be <hi>ſuitable</hi> to what he <hi>writes</hi> in <hi>his</hi> two Books.</p>
               <p>But he proceeds, <hi>Erroneous</hi> Doctrine. <hi>Weak</hi> Anabaptiſts. Their <hi>Children</hi> are <hi>ignorantly</hi> and <hi>bruitiſhly</hi> brought up, live and dye <hi>Pagans.</hi> It's a <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> Doctrine. They <hi>wilfully</hi> ſhut their Eyes. They do it with much <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>contempt.</hi> They are <hi>guilty</hi> of a plain breach of the <hi>ſixth Commandment,</hi> Thou ſhalt not <hi>kill. Dipping</hi> Perſons in <hi>water</hi> is a moſt <hi>heinous Sin,</hi> is a plain <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>ſixth Commandment,</hi> Thou ſhalt not <hi>kill.</hi> (Obſerve what Tautologies the poor man is guilty of;) Dipping in <hi>cold</hi> water <hi>tends</hi> to the taking away of <hi>Life,</hi> many have <hi>contracted</hi> ſuch <hi>Diſtempers</hi> that have <hi>haſtened</hi> their <hi>Deaths</hi> thereby, therefore the <hi>ſo</hi> doing is a <hi>great</hi> ſin. But the <hi>contrary</hi> to this <hi>is true,</hi> that <hi>divers</hi> have <hi>recovered</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Diſeaſes <hi>upon</hi> their being <hi>baptized;</hi> Ergo. Mr. <hi>Michael Harriſon</hi>'s aſſertion is a <hi>great</hi> untruth, <hi>great</hi> malice, and a <hi>great</hi> ſin. And herein <hi>he</hi> imitates the Devil, who was a <hi>Lyar</hi> from the <hi>beginning,</hi> and is the <hi>falſe accuſer</hi> of the <hi>Brethren.</hi> If this Charge be <hi>true,</hi> that we are <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Murder,</hi> why hath not <hi>he</hi> or <hi>ſome</hi> of his horrid <hi>lying</hi> Authors accuſed <hi>us</hi> to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> that <hi>Juſtice</hi> might have been <hi>executed</hi> upon <hi>us</hi> as <hi>murderers.</hi> But I am confident he doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34587:15"/>not <hi>believe</hi> himſelf, but writes <hi>directly</hi> againſt <hi>his</hi> Knowledge and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> I never had to do with ſuch a <hi>ſcurrilous,</hi> foul <hi>mouthed</hi> Author in <hi>Divinity</hi> in all my life; and I am heartily ſorry he hath (ſo fooliſhly) offered me <hi>this</hi> occaſion, for it's very contrary to <hi>my Genius,</hi> to render <hi>railing</hi> for <hi>railing.</hi> All this <hi>Rubbiſh</hi> is in his <hi>firſt</hi> Book of a Groat price.</p>
               <p>But in his <hi>2d.</hi> Book, as he begins with a known <hi>untruth</hi> in the Frontiſpiece, <hi>Infant-Baptiſm God's Ordinance,</hi> when he knows it is not ſo much as <hi>mentioned</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the Holy Scripture, ſo he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds <hi>all</hi> bounds in his <hi>railing</hi> and <hi>abuſive</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in this <hi>2d.</hi> part; For in the <hi>Title Page</hi> you have theſe Words, Anabaptiſts <hi>plea</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> a meer <hi>untruth.</hi> A Rebuke of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Erroneous</hi> Opinions. An Anſwer to ſeveral Scandalous and Erroneous Papers put out by the Anabaptiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts have been <hi>exeeeding troubleſome</hi> to all our Reformers. <hi>Hardned</hi> the Churches <hi>Enemies,</hi> hindred the Reformation. <hi>Bitter</hi> Enemies to the Work of God. Have moſt <hi>maliciouſly</hi> charged me with preaching <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrine. <hi>Malicious</hi> Slander. Betrayed their <hi>Weakneſs</hi> and <hi>Ignorance.</hi> Are a People ſtrangely <hi>alienated</hi> from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Goſpel. They have an <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuition</hi> to all Chriſtian Churches, and look on <hi>all</hi> others to be <hi>Pagans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he falls upon abuſing Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> who hath (together with that <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>eminently</hi> learned <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Claridge</hi>) ſufficiently anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>firſt</hi> Book. Which Anſwer (he ſaith) is <hi>ſo</hi> weak, it ſcarcely deſerves <hi>any</hi> reply: And ſaith, He is a <hi>weak</hi> unthinking man; foul and unchriſtian
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34587:15"/>Carriage; and then he quotes one <hi>Mence</hi> for his Author, (who I perceive was another <hi>railing Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhekah</hi> like himſelf) in a Letter ſent to him; who ſpeaks <hi>thus</hi> of Mr. <hi>Collins;</hi> The <hi>proud</hi> Author who was ſo <hi>impudent,</hi> He is the <hi>proudeſt,</hi> the <hi>Ignoranteſt,</hi> and the moſt <hi>abuſive</hi> Perſon I ever met with. His pittiful Anſwer. A <hi>lying</hi> ſlanderous paper. His <hi>fooliſh</hi> anſwer to your Book. He hath an <hi>Ignorant,</hi> malicious and <hi>lying</hi> Crew that <hi>follow</hi> him. That all this was a <hi>Malicious</hi> ſlander. <hi>Malignant</hi> ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Nay, theſe Charges and ſlanders filled with a blind <hi>raging</hi> Zeal. Directly <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the Goſpel. <hi>Pricking</hi> Briars and <hi>wounding</hi> Thorns. Clamorous and unruly Carriage. Scandalous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. I tax their Errors. A numerous <hi>croud</hi> of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts. Mr. <hi>Claridge's</hi> Love is a <hi>ſect</hi> Love, ſuch as is found among <hi>Papiſts, Quakers,</hi> nay, <hi>Mahumc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</hi> His Underſtanding under a falſe Conduct. Fearing his Zeal for his <hi>new</hi> Religion had quite darkned the uſe of his Underſtanding. Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi>'s is a <hi>Heterodox</hi> Pamphlet, ſtuffed with <hi>Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites</hi> and Miſtakes He is a weak unthinking man. Stock of <hi>raſh</hi> Confidence. <hi>Cruel</hi> to poor Babes. <hi>Arminian</hi> Anabaptiſts. Erroneous Opinions. They deny <hi>Original</hi> ſin. Hold that Chriſt <hi>dyed</hi> for <hi>all, &amp;c.</hi> in common with <hi>Papiſts, Socinians, Pelagians, Arminians,</hi> (I thought he had called us <hi>Arminians</hi> but even now; where is the <hi>congruity</hi> of his words? I perceive <hi>Paſſion</hi> deſtroys the uſe of his <hi>Reaſon</hi>) and other condemned Hereticks. And ſpeaking to his <hi>own</hi> People, he ſaith, It's your duty to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect them, they are <hi>falſe</hi> and dangerous, it will be <hi>your</hi> duty to <hi>reject</hi> them. And ſpeaking to the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> he ſaith, You ignorantly oppoſe Chriſt, who will both oppoſe and expoſe your Errors. And
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34587:16"/>then to his own People he ſaith, We ſee our <hi>dear</hi> Babes thruſt <hi>out</hi> of the Church, and <hi>ſet</hi> amongſt <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> and the <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>our</hi> Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>torn</hi> in pieces, and ſet aſide, as an <hi>old</hi> uſeleſs antiquated <hi>Covenant.</hi> Anabaptiſm is a <hi>new</hi> thing. Their Erronerous Opinions. The Anabaptiſts <hi>Pretence</hi> to Antiquity <hi>meer</hi> Forgery. Falſe and dangerous Doctrine. The Anabaptiſts have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived ſeveral <hi>old</hi> condemned <hi>Hereſies.</hi> They <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy</hi> the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>Reader, take notice, I am but now come to the firſt page of his <hi>Second</hi> Book, which <hi>begins</hi> with as manifeſt an Untruth as it is poſſible for the <hi>verieſt miſcreant</hi> under Heaven to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he is like to <hi>account</hi> for, when I have <hi>removed</hi> the reſt of thoſe <hi>excrementiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and abuſive ſpeeches the man hath in his Book, which is a manifeſt Indication of that Corruption which is in his Heart.</p>
               <p>The <hi>first</hi> Anabaptiſt in the <hi>World</hi> (ſaith this <hi>ignorant</hi> Trifler) being one <hi>Nicholas Stock,</hi> or <hi>Stork</hi> (or he knows <hi>not</hi> who) but however being a <hi>bold</hi> man, he tells us at <hi>all</hi> adventure, he was a <hi>blaſphemous Heretick.</hi> And <hi>diſgorged</hi> his <hi>malice</hi> againſt the <hi>baptizing of Infants.</hi> Pretended to Dreams and Viſions, and alſo Converſe with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. And in the <hi>Carcaſs</hi> of this <hi>unclean Beast</hi> was <hi>bred</hi> a multitude of <hi>ſtinging Inſects.</hi> Who moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently uttered <hi>their</hi> heretical Blaſphemies. That they would <hi>play</hi> with <hi>Rattles, ride</hi> on <hi>Hobbihorſes,</hi> (or elſe a Hobbihorſe ſaith ſo) and <hi>wallow</hi> in their <hi>own Dung.</hi> Preaching up <hi>vile</hi> Doctrines. Thundring out <hi>fearful Curſes</hi> againſt all that would <hi>not</hi> obey. And in the ſpace of a <hi>few</hi> years <hi>Germany</hi> was <hi>filled</hi> with Anabaptiſts. (Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34587:16"/>they were <hi>all inchanted</hi> that followed them, if they were ſuch <hi>vile</hi> Miſcrcants as <hi>you</hi> repreſent them.) They <hi>thunder'd</hi> againſt <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> turned all into <hi>uproar</hi> and <hi>confuſion.</hi> Played <hi>ſtrange</hi> wicked <hi>Pranks.</hi> Exceedingly <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> the Papiſts, <hi>hindred</hi> the Reformation, and <hi>grieved</hi> the Reformers. Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> a <hi>confident</hi> man, guilty of <hi>notorious</hi> Forgery. And yet Mr. <hi>H. Collins</hi> confidently tranſcribes from <hi>him.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly falſe. The Anabaptiſts <hi>confidently</hi> cite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet the Anabaptiſts have the <hi>Impudence.</hi> Their Infatuation is <hi>very</hi> great. But it's altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe. Thus they have <hi>most wickedly</hi> ſlander'd the <hi>Fathers.</hi> Detected the <hi>Forgeries. Strange</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries. They thus <hi>ſlander</hi> and <hi>bely</hi> Antiquity. So confidently, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus Ignorance, Impudence, and a ſtock of <hi>vile</hi> Conſidence, makes men they neither care what they <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ſay.</hi> A falſe Witneſs. He confidently ſaith, They <hi>pervert</hi> the Sayings of learned godly men. Such <hi>ſtuff</hi> as this will ſerve to raiſe a <hi>dust,</hi> and <hi>hlind</hi> the eyes of an <hi>ignorant</hi> Reader. Notorious <hi>Forgeries</hi> and Slanders. The <hi>pitiful</hi> Condition of the ſeduced, thus <hi>deceived</hi> in the dark. Untruths in <hi>fact</hi> and <hi>hiſtory.</hi> So notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and <hi>ſhameleſs.</hi> Notorious Untruths. Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently tranſcribes and reports. Whether they be not of <hi>ſo</hi> ſtupendious a magnitude, as ſhould have <hi>frighted</hi> the Conſcience of a <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Pagan?</hi> So ſlandered by you. So many <hi>whole</hi> Books are <hi>falſified.</hi> Notorious Scandals. Can ſwallow ſuch <hi>Camels</hi> as theſe. Notorious <hi>Forgers</hi> and <hi>Slanderers.</hi> So deliberately <hi>forge</hi> and ſlander. Such <hi>unmanly</hi> Scandals. Is not <hi>this</hi> a Scandal. To be <hi>ſo</hi> polluted. Greater Scaudals, more ſcandalous members. Brags and Boaſts. Anabaptiſm is a <hi>meer</hi> Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34587:17"/>Its <hi>first</hi> Authors and Founders <hi>notorious</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Blaſphemers. An <hi>Impoſture</hi> of Satan, to vex and <hi>pollute</hi> the Church. Weak Cavils. Fiery Zeal. Bitterneſs, Scorn, and Reproach. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly or maliciouſly raiſes a <hi>dust</hi> to blind the <hi>Readers</hi> eyes. To this they confidently reply. Their <hi>Cavil</hi> is this. The Anabaptiſts have indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly thrown <hi>Snares</hi> and Stumbling-blocks in <hi>our</hi> way. It is <hi>notorious</hi> Wickedneſs. The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts weakly urge. Run into ſtrange Abſurdities (if Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> may but have the <hi>making</hi> of <hi>them.</hi>) The rotten Doctrine which the Anabaptiſts hold. Some of them have turned <hi>Ranters, Quakers,</hi> any <hi>thing,</hi> or rather <hi>nothing.</hi> The plain Truth is, the poor man has a <hi>weak</hi> Head. Extreamly <hi>ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi> In <hi>their</hi> ignorant Pride they <hi>fly</hi> in the <hi>face</hi> of the Spirit of God. An ignorant <hi>raſh</hi> man. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds</hi> the Anabaptiſts. Pervert thoſe Words. They have made a <hi>great</hi> noiſe, and raiſed a <hi>great</hi> Duſt, to blind and divert an <hi>unwary</hi> Reader. The <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of the Anabaptiſts. (They were <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>weak-headed</hi> but <hi>now,</hi> and what, are they turned <hi>Sophiſters</hi> already?) <hi>Falſe</hi> Doctrine: I ſay again it's <hi>falſe</hi> Doctrine. <hi>Falſe</hi> Doctrine. His Anſwer is nothing but a <hi>meer</hi> blind. The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts confidently affirm, the <hi>right</hi> manner is <hi>dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</hi> Is <hi>fetched</hi> from what <hi>they</hi> fancy. To follow the natural <hi>Fancy</hi> of the Anabaptiſts. They hypocritically practice. <hi>Dipping</hi> cannot be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred without <hi>just ſcandal.</hi> They <hi>proudly</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own <hi>Communion.</hi> Their <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is from a <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>blaſphemous</hi> men. The Anabaptiſts are <hi>notoriouſly</hi> unſound. Unſound <hi>heterodox</hi> Opinions. They have <hi>revived</hi> ſeveral <hi>old</hi> condemned Hereſies, and are extreamly <hi>rotten</hi> in ſome <hi>fundamental</hi> Truths.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34587:17"/>The Anabaptiſts have nouriſhed many <hi>prodigious</hi> Errors. They are very erroneous. The <hi>Socinians</hi> have taught the Anabaptiſts. That the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts hold <hi>more</hi> erroneouſly <hi>than</hi> the very Papiſts. Uſe ſlippery and equivocating Terms. This <hi>fancy</hi> of the Anabaptiſts. Now the Anabaptiſts are more erroneous <hi>than</hi> the Papiſts. Error the Anabaptiſts are guilty of. A falſe and <hi>dangerous</hi> Doctrine. This Doctrine is <hi>falſe.</hi> This is <hi>falſe</hi> Doctrine. Error of the Anabaptiſts. In this Doctrine, <hi>Papiſts, Socinians, Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> are <hi>all</hi> agreed. It's of miſchievous and <hi>malignant</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. We boldly deny this <hi>monſtrous</hi> and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous <hi>Aſſertion.</hi> This <hi>rotten</hi> pillar. This <hi>Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> Doctrine is but a <hi>lying</hi> Invention of their own, and is deteſted by <hi>all</hi> Proteſtant Churches. Error. <hi>Abominable</hi> Doctrine! <hi>Falſe, dangerous,</hi> and <hi>uncomfortable</hi> Doctrine. Error of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts. <hi>Arminian</hi> Anabaptiſts. The groſſneſs and foulneſs of it. <hi>Weak,</hi> ignorant Preachers, they have Pride and Confidence, and 'tis theſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant men that broach moſt of <hi>theſe</hi> Errors. I might tax the Anabaptiſts as guilty. Oppoſing their Errors. This <hi>ſtone</hi> is flung at the <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Anabaptiſts. Now which Party Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> is of, I know not; but (by what he ſaith) it <hi>ſeems</hi> to <hi>me</hi> not only rank Arminiamiſm, but a <hi>new</hi> way to Heaven, and <hi>Mountebank</hi> Divinity.</p>
               <p>Thus you may <hi>ſee</hi> what <hi>frame</hi> of Spirit <hi>this</hi> man is of; it's in Vain for him to <hi>think</hi> he is in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate for <hi>leaving Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>becoming</hi> a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter,</hi> whilſt ſuch <hi>corrupt</hi> Communications pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds out of his mouth: For as our <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh;</hi> it's an <hi>Indication</hi> therefore of a <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>unmorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34587:18"/>Heart; for which he ought to be <hi>deeply</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. 'Tis contrary to all thoſe <hi>Exhortations</hi> in the Goſpel, to Meekneſs, Kindneſs, Tenderneſs, and Gharity. Our Lord, who is the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> whoſe <hi>Goſpel</hi> is a <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>peace,</hi> whoſe <hi>People</hi> are <hi>peaceable, gentle,</hi> and <hi>eaſy</hi> to be entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hath himſelf <hi>ſet us</hi> a bleſſed Example, who when he was <hi>Reviled,</hi> Reviled <hi>not</hi> again; when he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, he threatned <hi>not,</hi> but commited himſelf to him that Judgeth Righteouſly: Let us therefore labour to follow <hi>his</hi> Example, and then we may expect a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> in <hi>our</hi> Deed. For <hi>the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> Jam. 1.20.</p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Reader</hi> take notice, I have collected <hi>theſe</hi> harſh expreſſions <hi>out of</hi> Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s Books, page by page, as <hi>he</hi> may <hi>ſee</hi> by examining the <hi>ſame;</hi> beginning with the <hi>firſt,</hi> and ending with the <hi>laſt,</hi> and have been <hi>very exact</hi> therein, becauſe I would not wrong him. My Reaſon was, <hi>partly,</hi> that you might ſee what Spirit he is of, and <hi>how</hi> unfairly he hath dealt by us; as alſo, to avoid being <hi>vex'd</hi> with them, in <hi>every</hi> paragraph where <hi>they</hi> occurr'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THE firſt thing he begins with, is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Circumciſion; which he ſuppoſes to be the Covenant of Grace; and quotes <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17.7. for proof thereof: and infers, That all <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Believers</hi> are in <hi>this</hi> Covenant, and therefore <hi>they</hi> have a <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſm. He ſpends the firſt <hi>eight</hi> Pages upon it, and ſeems to <hi>hug</hi> himſelf in the Thoughts of ſome <hi>great</hi> Succeſs among <hi>his</hi> Hearers upon <hi>this</hi> his Undertaking.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34587:18"/>
               <p>But if I ſhall be <hi>ſo</hi> happy as to <hi>take</hi> from <hi>him</hi> the Foundation upon which <hi>all</hi> his <hi>Fabrick</hi> is built, He may then think he hath labour'd in <hi>vain,</hi> and ſpent his time for <hi>nought.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> inſiſt upon, it being the <hi>main</hi> Pillar he <hi>reſts</hi> upon (in both his Tracts) to ſupport that <hi>humane Invention</hi> of <hi>Baby baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall <hi>firſt</hi> ſhew; That the Covenant mentioned in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>place</hi> cited by <hi>him,</hi> is not the Covenant of Grace, but the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Circumciſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>this</hi> Covenant was <hi>aboliſhed</hi> by the Death of the Meſſiah.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if <hi>that</hi> Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. had been (as he ſaith) the Covenant of Grace; yet it had not <hi>therefore</hi> given the Infants of believing Parents a <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſm, without an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> from God, requiring <hi>it</hi> to be done.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To prove therefore, That the Covenant mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion, we have nothing to do, but to <hi>read</hi> the Words <hi>as</hi> they are recorded. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their Generations, for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee. And I will give unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee, the land wherein thou art a ſtranger, all the land of Canaan, for an everlaſting poſſeſſion; and I will be their God. And God ſaid unto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou and thy ſeed after thee in their Generations. This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep between me and you and thy ſeed after thee: every man child among you ſhall he circumciſed. And ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your foreskin; and it ſhall be a token of the Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34587:19"/>me and you.</hi> And ver. 13. <hi>He that is born in thy houſe, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumciſed; and my Covenant ſhall be in your fleſh for an everlaſting Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the <hi>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>plainneſs</hi> of theſe Expreſſions, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is pleaſed to tell us, <hi>this</hi> Covenant is the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> as you may ſee in <hi>pag.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. Altho' I believe no man that is not prepoſſeſſed with Error, can ever find any thing like it, by the Words of God himſelf; for he ſaith poſitively, it is <hi>that</hi> of Circumciſion.</p>
               <p>I need not therefore inſiſt <hi>much</hi> upon his <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> when it is directly <hi>contrary</hi> to the Word of God. But to make the matter beyond any <hi>reaſonable</hi> Contradiction, I ſhall urge <hi>thoſe very</hi> Arguments Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> hath <hi>ſo well</hi> advanced upon <hi>this</hi> Subject, in his <hi>Sandy Foundation of Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſhaken;</hi> in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Mence</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> which do <hi>yet</hi> remain <hi>unanſwered,</hi> pag. 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Mr. <hi>H. Collins,</hi> to prove that <hi>that</hi> Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his natural Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> he urges <hi>theſe</hi> following Arguments.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. The Covenant of Grace extends unto all Nations, the Covenant of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was limited to one Nation; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Covenant of Circumciſion is not the Covenant of Grace: Both which he hath ſubſtantially proved, to which I refer you.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. That Covenant which obligeth to <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> Law, is <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace:</hi> But the Covenant of Circumciſion obligeth to <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> Law; <hi>Ergo;</hi> the Covenant of Circumciſion is <hi>not</hi> the Covenant
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34587:19"/>of <hi>Grace.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> he ſhews to be undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and the <hi>minor</hi> he proves from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4. <hi>For I teſtify to every man that is circumciſed, that he is a Debtor to do the whole Law, and that Chriſt ſhall profit him nothing,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. That Covenant which is <hi>abrogated</hi> and repeal'd, is <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace:</hi> But the Covenant of Circumciſion is <hi>abrogated</hi> and repealed; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Covenant of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>minor,</hi> there are few in the World, but ſuch as are <hi>Judaizing,</hi> will deny. And for the <hi>major,</hi> none do ſuppoſe the Covenant of <hi>Grace</hi> can be <hi>repealed, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore the <hi>conſcquence</hi> follows, that that Circumciſion was <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace.</hi> Now notwithſtanding all this, and much more, which Mr. <hi>H. Collins</hi> hath ſpoken upon <hi>this</hi> ſubject, and that indeed with <hi>ſuch</hi> clearneſs of Evidence, that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will <hi>never</hi> be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>yet</hi> in his ſecond Book he ruſs over his <hi>old</hi> Arguments again in the former Book, and inſtead of giving <hi>any</hi> new ſolid Arguments, to take off the force of what Mr. <hi>H. C.</hi> had ſaid, this is his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in Part 2. Page. 15. The plain truth is, the <hi>poor man</hi> hath ſuch a <hi>weak</hi> head, that he knows not what in the World to make of it. (He miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the man) It was himſelf, and not Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins,</hi> to whom <hi>theſe</hi> words ought to be applied: For it's manifeſt, that he knew <hi>not</hi> how to confute him, becauſe he repeats the <hi>old</hi> Arguments he had uſed in his <hi>firſt</hi> Part. But I would not have Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> think the worſe of himſelf for all his <hi>Railery</hi> againſt him, becauſe the poor man hath not yet learned the common Civility and <hi>curteous</hi> Behaviour which every <hi>ingenuous</hi> man will ſhew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34587:20"/>to <hi>any one</hi> that is a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> eſpecially if he put himſelf upon the <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>charge</hi> to ſerve him for the <hi>good</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Soul, as Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> hath done: But ſome mens <hi>evil</hi> Nature will <hi>never</hi> depart from them, nor be mortified <hi>by</hi> them, let <hi>us</hi> do what we can. There are ſeveral other Arguments Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> hath alſo added, by which he hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably evinced this Covenant in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c. not</hi> to be the Covenant of <hi>Grace;</hi> as having only <hi>temporal</hi> Bleſſings promiſed in it. And becauſe perſons might be ſaved out of this Covenant, and many were ſaved who were <hi>never</hi> circumciſed, nor <hi>in</hi> that Covenant. That <hi>many</hi> Abſurdities fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the holding <hi>ſuch</hi> an Opinion, and that it overthrows <hi>many</hi> fundamental Points of Religion, <hi>divers</hi> of which he there enumerates. Now I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>all</hi> ingenious men, whether it had not been Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s buſineſs to have given ſome ſolid Anſwers to theſe Particulars? and whether Mr. <hi>H. Collins</hi> deſerved <hi>ſuch</hi> a Treatment from a <hi>man</hi> who calls himſelf a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Goſpel. But to proceed,</p>
               <p n="2">2. I have undertaken to <hi>prove,</hi> That <hi>this</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Circumcifion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was <hi>aboliſhed</hi> by Chriſt. But upon Enquiry I find that Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> Part 1. pag. 6. doth confeſs that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is <hi>now</hi> aboliſhed: His Words are theſe, Circumciſion <hi>is now</hi> aboliſhed by Chriſt; and cites for <hi>Probation</hi> thereof <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Having aboliſhed in his Fleſh the Enmity, even the Law of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, contained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelf of twain one new man, ſo making Peace.</hi> To this he adds, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion is nothing, but the keeping the commandments of God.</hi> Now upon <hi>this</hi> Conceſſion I would willingly know of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> why he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34587:20"/>the Covenant of which he ſaith Circumciſion was a <hi>Seal,</hi> is <hi>ſtill</hi> remaining, when he <hi>confeſſes</hi> the <hi>Seal</hi> thereof is <hi>broken</hi> off, and taken <hi>away</hi> from it? If a <hi>Bond</hi> for the <hi>performance</hi> of a <hi>Covenant</hi> be <hi>once</hi> cancelled, the Covenant <hi>it ſelf</hi> ceaſes to be <hi>obligatory</hi> any <hi>longer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If <hi>that</hi> Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had been (as he ſaith) <hi>the</hi> Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> yet it had <hi>not</hi> therefore given the Infants of believing Parents a right to Baptiſm, <hi>without</hi> an Inſtitution from God, requiring it to be done.</p>
               <p>I prove it thus:</p>
               <p n="1">1. From Mr. <hi>H.</hi> own words, <hi>part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 6, 7. We do <hi>not</hi> baptize perſons <hi>as</hi> the Elect of God, or Infants <hi>as</hi> Infants of the <hi>Elect.</hi> And a little before ſpeaking of perſons being <hi>really</hi> in the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> as <hi>united</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>living</hi> Branches, <hi>knit</hi> to Chriſt by a <hi>vital</hi> union; he adds, and thus <hi>only</hi> the Elect are <hi>in</hi> Covenant. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>thus</hi> conſidered is <hi>not</hi> the ground of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; if we muſt baptize <hi>none</hi> but <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>vitally</hi> in Chriſt, then muſt <hi>we</hi> baptize <hi>none;</hi> and he gives this reaſon for it, becauſe tho' we ſee the <hi>outward</hi> profeſſion, we do <hi>not</hi> know <hi>who</hi> belong to the <hi>Election</hi> of Grace.</p>
               <p>From all which its plain Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth not think their being <hi>in</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace</hi> a ſufficient ground to baptize <hi>any</hi> perſon, becauſe he cannot poſſibly know that they <hi>are ſo.</hi> How <hi>then</hi> can he baptize <hi>any</hi> Infant upon the terms of <hi>that</hi> Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. if it were (as he ſaith) the Covenant of <hi>Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſaith he, thoſe that are <hi>externally</hi> and <hi>viſibly</hi> in Covenant, all that <hi>profeſs</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Tares</hi> and <hi>Wheat,</hi> wiſe Virgins and <hi>fooliſh: This</hi> (ſaith he) is the <hi>Ground</hi> of Baptiſm.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34587:21"/>
               <p>I anſwer, Had Mr. <hi>H.</hi> being ſpeaking of the Members of a Nation, and alſo of the Members of the viſible Church, and had diſtinguiſhed the latter into theſe two ſorts of Perſons, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch that were inviſible members, and ſuch that were only ſo by a bare profeſſion, reaſon would that I ſhould allow it: But when he is ſpeaking of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> to tell us of <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>carnal Profeſſors,</hi> who are <hi>devoid</hi> of true Grace, and that <hi>all ſuch</hi> are to be accounted <hi>Believers</hi> in <hi>Covenant,</hi> and that <hi>all</hi> Infants of <hi>ſuch</hi> believing Parents are <hi>in</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> (as you may ſee in the Page before-mentioned) this is one of the greateſt Paradoxes I ever met with. If the <hi>wicked,</hi> who are called Tares, are to be accounted <hi>Believers</hi> in Covenant, why ſhall they be caſt into <hi>Hell</hi>-fire? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.40, 41, 42. If the <hi>fooliſh</hi> Virgins in the Church are <hi>in</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> why muſt they be <hi>ſhut out</hi> of Heaven? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Now that it was <hi>without</hi> reaſon for him thus to argue, I prove from his own Words, Becauſe <hi>he</hi> doth aſſure us from the Teſtimony of Holy Scripture, that <hi>all</hi> Believers are <hi>in</hi> this <hi>Covenant.</hi> This (ſaith he in <hi>pag.</hi> 6.) is abundabtly evident from <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. the Covenant was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> as a Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and with all Believers as well as him. And that we may not <hi>miſtake</hi> his <hi>meaning,</hi> he often calls it <hi>the</hi> Covenant of <hi>Grace</hi> made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> &amp;c. Now that the Covenant in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is <hi>not</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> I have <hi>already</hi> ſhown: But that there was <hi>a</hi> Covenant of Grace, in which <hi>Abraham</hi> was inſtated, (being a Believer in Chriſt, and a ſpecial Friend and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34587:21"/>Favourite of God) as the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>faithful,</hi> wherein <hi>all</hi> true Believers have a <hi>right</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, as being <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, I readily allow: And moreover, That <hi>all</hi> true Believers <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' under the <hi>former</hi> diſpenſation, they <hi>could not</hi> be admitted to Baptiſm, becauſe it had been <hi>Will</hi>-Worſhip <hi>ſo</hi> to do, it <hi>not</hi> being <hi>then</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: Yet <hi>now</hi> they have a right to <hi>that</hi> Holy Ordinance, as the <hi>proper</hi> Subjects thereof; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt hath not <hi>only</hi> commanded <hi>it,</hi> but made a <hi>gracious</hi> promiſe to them <hi>upon</hi> their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing Mr. <hi>H.</hi> further ſaith, in <hi>page</hi> 7. That Perſons <hi>are</hi> to be baptized, as <hi>making</hi> a viſible and <hi>credible</hi> profeſſion of Religion, and that the Apoſtles did baptize <hi>ſuch</hi> as did profeſs <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</p>
               <p>I therefore <hi>infer</hi> upon him the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his <hi>former</hi> Aſſertion, That the Children of <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>only</hi> formal Hypocrites, are to be baptized, becauſe their Parents make an <hi>outward</hi> profeſſion of Chriſtianity; (for which he quotes <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20, 21. which I deſire may be read over; for I think he might have proved it as well from <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.) when according to his <hi>own</hi> Aſſertion <hi>all</hi> true Believers are in the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>ſo</hi> are the <hi>Elect</hi> of God in a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> ſence, and the <hi>fit</hi> ſubjects of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> And if he would himſelf (who is <hi>yet</hi> an <hi>unbaptized</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) truly believe, and be baptized, and by a <hi>Gift</hi> from Chriſt did once become a <hi>Teacher</hi> in the <hi>true</hi> viſible Church, he might <hi>then</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>penitent</hi> Believers, upon a foundation that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34587:22"/>
                  <hi>himſelf</hi> acknowledges to be <hi>good</hi> and warrantable, from the <hi>practice</hi> of the Apoſtles: But for his baptizing <hi>Infants,</hi> as he hath <hi>no</hi> authority for it from the Word of God, ſo by his <hi>own</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he hath no Foundation for it, as they are in Covenant, becauſe he doth <hi>not</hi> know they are <hi>ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>page</hi> 7. That <hi>all</hi> Infants of <hi>ſuch</hi> believing <hi>parents,</hi> (i. e. External and Viſible Profeſſors) are <hi>in</hi> the Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> and have <hi>as much</hi> a right to Baptiſm, the <hi>Now</hi> Seal of the Covenant, as the Infants of the Jews <hi>had</hi> to Circumciſion, the <hi>then</hi> Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: And ſaith, <hi>This</hi> is the principal thing deſigned from this Text, meaning <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Well, if it be ſo, it ſhall be conſidered; but I pray <hi>who</hi> told him theſe things he hath ſo <hi>boldly</hi> aſſerted? For in the firſt place, If <hi>all</hi> Infants are <hi>not</hi> within the Covenant of Grace, how comes it about that <hi>all</hi> the Infants of <hi>ſuch</hi> believing Parents, <hi>qua talis,</hi> are <hi>in</hi> that Covenant? Hath he not forgot what he wrote in the very Page before? That the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Grace is God's gracious <hi>Promiſe</hi> of delivering from a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> and bringing into a ſtate of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>all</hi> that by faith <hi>fly</hi> to, and <hi>lay hold</hi> on him; and could it <hi>enter</hi> into his imagination, that little Infants can by faith <hi>fly to,</hi> and <hi>lay hold</hi> on Chriſt? And if they cannot, then it's plain this Gentleman hath been guilty of a <hi>Self-contradiction,</hi> from which he can no ways extricate himſelf. Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> had given him ſufficient notice of it, by ſaying, ſurely the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath forgot himſelf, in the <hi>Definition</hi> of the Covenant of Grace; and hath ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34587:22"/>this Aſſertion; but I find it's (as yet) a Work he cares not to undertake, to <hi>recant</hi> his <hi>Errors,</hi> when he is <hi>detected</hi> for them.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2ly.</hi> How doth he know that Infants have as much a <hi>right</hi> to Baptiſm <hi>now,</hi> as the Infants of the <hi>Jews</hi> had to Circumciſion? He gives us nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Argument, <hi>nor</hi> Scripture, (in this place) to prove it; and therefore we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it our ſelves.</p>
               <p>All the Anſwer I think needful to give, is this: Infants were <hi>commanded</hi> by God to be circumciſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Every man-child among you ſhall be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</hi> Ver. 12. <hi>And he that is eight days old ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> And the particular Direction is given, <hi>Ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your foreskin.</hi> Here, you ſee, is the <hi>Command</hi> of God, both for the <hi>Work</hi> it ſelf, the Subject <hi>upon whom,</hi> and the <hi>time when</hi> it was to be performed: So that God's <hi>Command</hi> gave Infants <hi>then</hi> a <hi>right</hi> to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion.</p>
               <p>Now let but Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhew us any <hi>ſuch</hi> Command in <hi>all</hi> the Scriptures, for the baptizing of Infants, and we will thank him; for we never yet could find it in all the Book of God: And <hi>till</hi> he doth, we have <hi>no</hi> reaſon to believe what he ſo <hi>confidently</hi> aſſerts, to be true.</p>
               <p>But <hi>3ly.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> aſſerts, That Baptiſm is the <hi>now</hi> Seal of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> I know not how he will prove it; for I am ſure it's an <hi>unſcriptural</hi> Notion: For the Holy Scripture doth <hi>no where</hi> tell us, that Baptiſm is the <hi>ſeal</hi> of the Covenant, but hath plainly told us, that Chriſtians were <hi>ſealed</hi> with the <hi>holy Spirit;</hi> Epheſ. 1.13, 14. <hi>After that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of Promiſe which is the earneſt of our Inheritance:</hi> And I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34587:23"/>will <hi>rather</hi> believe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> than Mr. <hi>H.</hi> And this leads me to conſider what he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in his firſt <hi>Chapter, Part</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving in the <hi>former</hi> Chapter confuted thoſe Arguments he hath brought from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. to prove Infants Baptiſm, I come <hi>now</hi> to conſider his <hi>five</hi> introductory <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> which he ſaith are very needful, for the right underſtanding the <hi>Controverſy</hi> of Infant-baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſaith, That a Doctrine or Practice may be proved to be of God <hi>two</hi> ways.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of Scripture.</item>
                  <item>2. Or from <hi>evident</hi> Conſequences <hi>drawn</hi> from Scripture.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As to the <hi>firſt:</hi> It is a great <hi>Truth:</hi> And <hi>thus</hi> we can prove <hi>our</hi> Practice of <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> with all the Perſpicuity imaginable, as I ſhall make appear when I come to treat of <hi>that</hi> Subject: Therefore he muſt, from his <hi>own</hi> Rule, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that <hi>our</hi> Practice therein <hi>is</hi> of God. But I am ſure he is conſcious to himſelf, that the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Infant-baptiſm <hi>cannot</hi> be proved by the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of Scripture; becauſe he finds fault with <hi>us</hi> for urging them to it, in <hi>Page</hi> 10. where he brings us in, ſaying, bring us a <hi>plain</hi> Text, and we will <hi>believe</hi> it; and repreſents <hi>it</hi> as an <hi>un</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Demand.</p>
               <p>But if his <hi>Paſſion</hi> hath not ſo <hi>far</hi> tranſported him, as to make him forget what <hi>Subject-matter</hi> he is treating of, he might have forborn thoſe Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34587:23"/>againſt us: For I do affirm, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a part of <hi>Inſtituted Worſhip;</hi> and therefore whilſt he pretends to practice Infant-baptiſm, he is <hi>obliged</hi> to ſhew us, where it is expreſly commanded in the Word of God, or otherwiſe how does he know it is the Will of God that it ſhould be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed <hi>at all?</hi> For <hi>all</hi> Inſtituted Worſhip hath its Foundation <hi>only</hi> in the <hi>Will</hi> of the Law-giver, as he hath revealed it unto us; and unleſs he hath found out ſome <hi>other</hi> Rule of Faith and Practice <hi>beſides</hi> the Word of God, he is bound to ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Authority thereof, in the Determination of <hi>this</hi> Controverſy: <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; if they ſpeak not according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſa. 8.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He endeavours to perſwade us, That <hi>evident</hi> Conſequences, drawn from Scripture, are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>I might deny <hi>this</hi> in the Point under Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; becauſe <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a <hi>part of Inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> For altho' this may be true about <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Points in Divinity, it is no neceſſary Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it muſt be ſo in <hi>poſitive</hi> Duties. But I will not inſiſt upon it, but for Arguments ſake allow it to be true: And therefore let him proceed as ſoon as he pleaſes, to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of Infants an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, by <hi>evident</hi> Confequences, drawn from Scripture, and I will allow it.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>ſecond</hi> Obſervation, it is applicable to <hi>himſelf,</hi> and not to <hi>us,</hi> and therefore I ſhall leave it at his <hi>own</hi> door.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>Thoſe</hi> Doctrines which were <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> revealed, and <hi>fully</hi> conſirmed in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho' <hi>little</hi> or <hi>nothing</hi> be ſaid of them in the <hi>Now</hi> Teſtament, and were <hi>never</hi> repealed, are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34587:24"/>
                  <hi>yet</hi> to be owned, received, and believed, <hi>as</hi> if <hi>much</hi> had been ſaid of them in the <hi>New</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And preſently after he tells us, <hi>This</hi> is the <hi>caſe</hi> of Infant-baptiſm.</p>
               <p>Well Sir, If you will <hi>prove</hi> that Infant bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was <hi>clearly</hi> revealed, and <hi>fully</hi> confirmed to be an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, and <hi>our</hi> duty to practiſe it <hi>in</hi> Goſpel-days, by the Scriptures of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, I am contented. But pray be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſhew us <hi>that</hi> revelation and <hi>confirmation,</hi> that <hi>we</hi> may be ſatisfied <hi>it is</hi> ſo: For I <hi>never</hi> read of Infants-baptiſm as <hi>yet</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and I believe there is <hi>as little</hi> mention made of it <hi>in</hi> the <hi>New.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>4ly.</hi> You ſay, <hi>thoſe</hi> Doctrines which were once <hi>throughly</hi> ſettled in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, and <hi>never</hi> called in queſtion by any <hi>in</hi> the New, there was <hi>no</hi> occaſion given to ſpeak of them <hi>again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this be <hi>ad rem,</hi> there are then <hi>two</hi> things ſignified thereby:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That there was no occaſion given to ſpeak of Infant baptiſm <hi>in</hi> the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament: And I am certain if there were, it was <hi>wholly</hi> omitted; for there is no mention made of <hi>it</hi> in the leaſt.</item>
                  <item>2. That it was a Doctrine throughly ſettled in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament. If <hi>this</hi> be true, Why doth he not <hi>prove</hi> it, by ſhewing us where it is ſo writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? If he cannot, let him acknowledge <hi>his</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As for what he ſpeaks in his fifth <hi>conſideration,</hi> That Doctrine may be <hi>very</hi> clear, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> brought to prove, and the <hi>Argument</hi> thence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced clear and <hi>convincing;</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> it may remain <hi>dark</hi> to one that is <hi>uncapable</hi> of diſcerning it. This I allow to be <hi>true.</hi> And if there were no <hi>other</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34587:24"/>to be given of it beſides, Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> himſelf may be given <hi>in evidence:</hi> For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the expreſs Evidence from Scripture, that <hi>multitudes</hi> of Believers were baptiſed <hi>by dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> in the Apoſtles days, (as I ſhall prove in <hi>due</hi> place) yet by reaſon of thoſe <hi>Catarrachs</hi> of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that have blinded the Eyes of <hi>his</hi> Mind, he is <hi>uncapable</hi> of diſcerning <hi>it;</hi> for in <hi>Pag.</hi> 48. he ſaith, It was <hi>never yet</hi> proved, that perſons were <hi>then</hi> dipped. And on the <hi>contrary,</hi> a thing that is <hi>never</hi> mentioned <hi>at all</hi> in Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> Infant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm, That, he ſaith, is <hi>as</hi> clear to <hi>him</hi> as the Doctrines of the Trinity; the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt; Juſtification by imputed Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this gives occaſion to fear that he is yet but a <hi>natural man;</hi> becauſe <hi>ſuch</hi> a one perceiveth not the things of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, neither <hi>can</hi> he know them, becauſe they are <hi>ſpiritually</hi> diſcerned: And therefore <hi>He</hi> that is not <hi>as yet</hi> of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Illuminati;</hi> would do well to put himſelf into the number of the <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> that he might be inſtructed in the <hi>way</hi> of God <hi>more</hi> perfectly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34587:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Being an Anſwer to what Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> ſaith upon Acts <hi>2.39. For the Promiſe is to you, and to your Children,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>I Shall endeavour to give you the true <hi>Scope</hi> of the place, and then return an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Allegations.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> having convinced the <hi>Jews,</hi> That the ſame Jeſus whom they had crucified was both Lord and Chriſt, they being <hi>pricked</hi> in their Hearts, <hi>cryed</hi> out, <hi>Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do? Peter</hi>'s Anſwer is, <hi>Repent, and be Baptiſed every one of you, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, (This</hi> is the duty) <hi>for the remiſſion of Sins;</hi> (<hi>that</hi> was the <hi>end</hi> propoſed, and the <hi>thing</hi> they wanted): The <hi>promiſe</hi> follows in theſe words, <hi>And ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt: For the promiſe</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt) <hi>is to you, and to your Children, &amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Children here</hi> is meant <hi>their</hi> poſterity; who, if they did <hi>alſo</hi> perform <hi>thoſe</hi> conditions of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> Faith and Baptiſm, they <hi>alſo</hi> ſhould receive the <hi>gift</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Moreover, there being <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo his preſent Auditors, he adds, <hi>The promiſe is to all that are afar off,</hi> meaning the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:</hi> And to let them know he intended <hi>no other</hi> mathod for <hi>their</hi> children, than what he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>unto them,</hi> he <hi>reſtrains it</hi> to Believers <hi>only; Even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> If any ſhould <hi>fancy</hi> that Baptiſm is intended in the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and ſo apply it to <hi>little</hi> children, that <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34587:25"/>be; becauſe Baptiſm is <hi>not</hi> a Promiſe, but a <hi>Command;</hi> and <hi>ſo</hi> there can be <hi>no</hi> Pretence for Infant baptiſm from <hi>this</hi> Promiſe.</p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>H.</hi> being aware of <hi>that,</hi> he hath found out a <hi>New Invention,</hi> for he tells us, 'tis the promiſe of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. which <hi>therefore</hi> contains a <hi>plain</hi> precept for the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Infants.</p>
               <p>I was in hopes I might have <hi>finiſhed</hi> what was needful to be ſaid upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. before, but I ſee Mr. <hi>H.</hi> builds his <hi>whole Superſtructure</hi> upon <hi>it,</hi> and therefore I muſt ſay ſomething <hi>further</hi> to it: Notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>H. Collins</hi> hath <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently confuted</hi> what he ſaith, but it ſeems he hath not <hi>yet</hi> attained to <hi>that</hi> diſcretion, to know <hi>when</hi> he is <hi>fully</hi> anſwered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore I ſhall ſhew, that <hi>Canaan-Land,</hi> with thoſe <hi>External</hi> Bleſſings that accompanied <hi>them</hi> in the poſſeſſion thereof, is the <hi>great</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in <hi>that</hi> place by <hi>him</hi> cited, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I do <hi>affirm,</hi> and I think the <hi>proof</hi> I have given for it <hi>already</hi> may be <hi>ſufficient ſatisfaction</hi> to any <hi>reaſonable</hi> man, that the Covenant in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. is <hi>that</hi> of Circumciſion, and not the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and then his Interpretation of <hi>this</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. is <hi>wholly</hi> groundleſs.</p>
               <p>As touching the firſt, whoever will pleaſe to read <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. will find, <hi>beſide</hi> the Promiſe of a <hi>numerous</hi> Off-ſpring, that of <hi>Canaan</hi> particularly <hi>expreſt,</hi> ver. 8. <hi>And I will give unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee, the Land wherein thou art a ſtranger, all the Land of Canaan, for an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſſion, and I will be their God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will give you the Words of a late <hi>Learned</hi> Proteſtant upon the place; he tells us, <q>That
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34587:26"/>
                     <hi>this</hi> Covenant is ſaid to be an <hi>everlaſting</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in the ſame ſence as <hi>Canaan</hi> is ſaid to to be an <hi>everlaſting</hi> poſſeſſion; there is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no more reaſon to conclude from <hi>this</hi> term, that the Covenant of Circumciſion was directly and properly a covenant of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> bleſſings, <hi>than</hi> there is to affirm, that the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the good things thereof, were a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</q> And God's promiſing to be <hi>their</hi> God, denotes <hi>only</hi> his <hi>engaging</hi> himſelf to make good the promiſes contained in <hi>that</hi> Covenant.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>pretended</hi> Reaſons, they vaniſh of themſelves, becauſe they are built upon a <hi>falſe</hi> Notion, that the <hi>covenant</hi> of circumciſion is the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> which I have already diſproved: And he may as well affirm, that <hi>all</hi> Believers, and <hi>their</hi> Children, have a <hi>promiſe</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. to poſſeſs the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whether they be <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as to tell us, <hi>That</hi> promiſe the Apoſtle <hi>here</hi> ſpeaks of, muſt be <hi>that</hi> promiſe to which he ſaith, Circumciſion was the <hi>Seal</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>former</hi> diſpenſation. I am <hi>troubled</hi> to think, that Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> ſhould <hi>trifle</hi> thus about <hi>ſacred</hi> things, and endeavour to <hi>deceive</hi> his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by perſwading him, that the covenant of circumciſion is <hi>yet</hi> in being <hi>under</hi> the Goſpel; a thing ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>tenor</hi> of the Goſpel, and the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of Holy Scripture. The <hi>whole</hi> Fabrick of the <hi>Jewiſh Church-ſtate</hi> being <hi>pulled</hi> down, and a <hi>New Church-ſtate</hi> erected in the <hi>room</hi> thereof, it is not the Houſe of God, <hi>erected</hi> by the <hi>Moſaical Law,</hi> but the Houſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> erected by the Son himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. oppoſed <hi>to,</hi> and in contradiſtinction <hi>from</hi> that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34587:26"/>former <hi>one</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> which <hi>all</hi> that were circumciſed were <hi>obliged</hi> to obſerve: For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If any man he circumciſed, he is a debtor to the whole Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in his <hi>next</hi> Paragraph he entangles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a difficulty (I ſuppoſe) he will not be able to free himſelf from: For he ſaith, in <hi>page</hi> 21. <hi>This</hi> promiſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, was <hi>that</hi> promiſe or covenant of which Baptiſm was the <hi>Seal.</hi> And in the words following he tells us, that Circumciſion and Baptiſm are <hi>Seals</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> covenant. Now whereas I have <hi>already proved,</hi> that the <hi>covenant</hi> of Circumciſion was <hi>not</hi> the covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> I think I need <hi>not</hi> prove that Baptiſm is a <hi>duty</hi> belonging to the <hi>New</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; becauſe <hi>all</hi> acknowledge it <hi>ſo</hi> to be: And as certain I am, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the <hi>Law</hi> of Works to the <hi>Law</hi> of Faith, <hi>It is of Faith, that it might be of Grace;</hi> and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion <hi>obliging</hi> to keep the <hi>whole</hi> Law, <hi>which</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant being <hi>now</hi> aboliſhed, he ſaith, <hi>If ye be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> And he gives this reaſon for it, <hi>Whoſoever of you are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the law, ye are fallen from Grace:</hi> And that <hi>this</hi> reſpects the <hi>covenant</hi> of circumciſion, with <hi>its</hi> adjuncts, is plain from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. where the Apoſtle exhorts them <hi>To ſtand faſt in that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free, and not to be entangled again with the yoke of bondage;</hi> which he explains in the following verſes to be meant of the <hi>covenant</hi> of <hi>circumciſion:</hi> So that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> may ſee what a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> he is in, out of which I ſuppoſe it will not be eaſie for him to <hi>extricate</hi> himſelf.</p>
               <p>The late Learned Dr. <hi>Neh. Coxe,</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34587:27"/>
                  <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of the <hi>Covenants,</hi> hath given us the <hi>true ground</hi> of <hi>theſe perplexities</hi> that the <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> have fallen into, which I ſhall tranſcribe, for the ſake of thoſe who have not his Book to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, nor are likely to obtain, becauſe it's out of print.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 12. Now as it is evident from what hath been already ſaid, that <hi>all</hi> ſoederal tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of God with men, flow <hi>only</hi> from his good pleaſure, and the counſel of his Will, ſo upon that ground it is certainly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that our knowledge and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, muſt <hi>wholly</hi> depend upon <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation. None can pretend acquaintance with the <hi>ſecret</hi> of God, but as he hath pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reveal it in his Word; <hi>this light</hi> muſt guide <hi>all</hi> our inquiries after it, and our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of things of <hi>this</hi> nature muſt be ſtrictly governed by <hi>this</hi> Rule; ſeeing the nature of them is ſuch, as tranſcends the <hi>common</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of reaſon or <hi>natural</hi> Light, inaſmuch as they owe <hi>their original</hi> to the free acts of the <hi>Divine</hi> Will and Wiſdom, which are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable, 'till revealed by God himſelf; and therefore it becomes us to captivate all our thoughts of them to the <hi>obedience</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> as knowing that <hi>Learning</hi> and ſtrength of <hi>Parts</hi> (tho' of excellent uſe in their place) <hi>not</hi> guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Scripture light</hi> in theſe Inquiries, can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly form an <hi>Ingenious</hi> Error, and loſe a man in the <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> Imagination, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Gueſſes; ſeeing the <hi>ſingle</hi> advantage of thoſe aſſiſtances (in this caſe truſted to, and ſtretched beyond their line) can reach no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to enable him, <hi>cum ratione errare,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34587:27"/>and ſo to wander from truth in a path ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more <hi>ſmooth,</hi> tho' no leſs dangerous than others light upon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And therefore in theſe things lyes the <hi>ſpring</hi> of <hi>moſt miſtakes,</hi> and <hi>corruption</hi> of Doctrine and Practiſe in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> men do eaſily find out, and agree in the true Dictates of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> but in things pertaining to the <hi>covenants</hi> of God, how <hi>various</hi> are their Sentiments? Yea, many <hi>great,</hi> Learned and <hi>good</hi> men, have been <hi>divided</hi> in their Judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome things of <hi>great</hi> importance to the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> of the Church: And ſome <hi>one</hi> Error <hi>admitted</hi> about the nature of God's ſoederal tranſactions with men, doth ſtrangely <hi>perplex</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> Syſtem, or Body of Divinity, and entangle our Interpretation of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Texts of Scripture, and by this means Jars and Contentions have been perpetuated in the Church, to the great <hi>grief</hi> and hindrance of <hi>all,</hi> the offence of the <hi>weak,</hi> and greater ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the <hi>blind</hi> World; and all this hath been much occaſioned thro' the want of a due and humble attention to <hi>that</hi> Revelation of Truth which God hath given us <hi>in the</hi> Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and endeavouring to collect the mind of God from thence, <hi>without</hi> prepoſſeſſion of Judgment, (which is a greater occaſion of <hi>theſe</hi> miſtakes than men are generally aware of) and careful avoiding the <hi>undue</hi> mixture or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of things <hi>natural,</hi> with thoſe that are <hi>purely</hi> of a ſoederal nature.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would earneſtly beg of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> both for his <hi>own good,</hi> and the good of the <hi>people</hi> he ſtands <hi>related</hi> to, that he would be pleaſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34587:28"/>to conſider ſeriouſly what <hi>this</hi> Learned Man hath ſaid; and by laying aſide all <hi>pre-conceived</hi> Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices and <hi>pre-poſſeſſion</hi> of Judgment, would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to an <hi>humble</hi> inquiry after the mind of God, <hi>as</hi> revealed in his Word, and not truſt to his <hi>Learning,</hi> nor lean to his <hi>own</hi> underſtanding in the <hi>matters</hi> of Divine Truths, but labour to ſatisfie his conſcience from the <hi>Revelation</hi> of God in his Holy Word, that <hi>thus</hi> it is written, and <hi>therefore</hi> I believe.</p>
               <p>And to apply it to the <hi>preſent</hi> caſe, if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can ſhew us <hi>where</hi> is written, that Infants <hi>ought</hi> to be baptized by <hi>any</hi> appointment of God, or <hi>where</hi> its written that <hi>any one</hi> Infant was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; or <hi>where</hi> its charged <hi>as a ſin</hi> upon <hi>any one</hi> to <hi>neglect</hi> carrying them to be baptized; or <hi>where</hi> any <hi>Miniſter</hi> is blamed for <hi>not</hi> teaching them to bring <hi>their</hi> Children to Baptiſm, or for <hi>not</hi> baptizing them <hi>when</hi> they were <hi>brought;</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if there be <hi>any thing</hi> ſaid about it, directly or indirectly, to <hi>enjoyn</hi> the practiſe thereof, or <hi>any</hi> the <hi>leaſt</hi> mention made of <hi>it,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the Book of God, we will grant him the cauſe: But I perceive <hi>himſelf</hi> is ſatisfied there is <hi>no</hi> ſuch thing, and therefore he is pleaſed to <hi>ridicule us</hi> for demanding of him to ſhew us <hi>where</hi> it is <hi>commanded</hi> in the Scripture. But let him know, that all inſtituted Worſhip hath <hi>no</hi> foundation, but the <hi>Divine</hi> Will requiring it, and therefore his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to evade the Objection is <hi>vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But however, ſeeing he thinks he is ſo <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> at <hi>conſequences,</hi> and that he can do <hi>mighty</hi> things that way, let Mr. <hi>H.</hi> (if he can) prove by <hi>conſequence,</hi> or any <hi>other</hi> way, that Infant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm is God's Ordinance: But I perceive he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34587:28"/>cannot do it; for he hath written <hi>two</hi> Books al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and not <hi>one</hi> Argument in either of them that concludes the <hi>thing</hi> in Queſtion. And to tell you my Thoughts upon it, I am of Opinion, if he ſhould write a hundred Books, it will be ſtill the ſame; for he hath run over <hi>nine</hi> Arguments <hi>twice</hi> to <hi>no</hi> purpoſe: For there is nothing of the Point in queſtion inferr'd in any of them. And I know the Reaſon: It is not <hi>ſimply</hi> for want of <hi>Parts,</hi> and Learning, but for want of <hi>Matter;</hi> for that which <hi>is</hi> not, cannot be proved to <hi>be;</hi> but Infant-baptiſm is <hi>not</hi> an Ordinance of God, and therefore it cannot be proved <hi>ſo</hi> to be. And whereas he doth allow he cannot ſhew us a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> for it, by abuſing us for <hi>but</hi> demanding it of him; I am ſure his Attempt to prove that to be an Ordinance of God by Conſequence <hi>only,</hi> when he hath granted there is no <hi>expreſs</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, is too great a Task for him <hi>ever</hi> to perform: And if he would take my Advice, I would not have him ſo much as attempt it any more, becauſe it's <hi>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſſible</hi> to be done.</p>
               <p>But why doth Mr. <hi>H.</hi> tell us, Baptiſm is a <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>New Covenant?</hi> If it be, his Arguments are all out of doors; for a <hi>Seal</hi> is not to be <hi>ſet</hi> to a <hi>Blank,</hi> as it muſt be if applied to Infants. Beſides, he is miſtaken in the <hi>whole</hi> of his Poſition; for Circumciſion is only ſaid to be a <hi>ſeal</hi> of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Faith, to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>not</hi> to the <hi>reſt</hi> of his Poſterity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Faith is reckoned to Abraham for Righteouſneſs.</hi> And in the <hi>10th. Verſe</hi> he tells us, it was before he was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: But in <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. he received the ſign of Circumciſion, a <hi>ſeal</hi> of the Righteouſneſs of the Faith which he had, <hi>yet</hi> being <hi>uncircumciſed,</hi> that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34587:29"/>he might be the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>all</hi> them that believe, tho' they be <hi>not</hi> circumciſed, that Righteouſneſs might be imputed unto <hi>them</hi> alſo. This is the only Text that I find the Word is uſed in, as applied to Circumciſion; and here it is reſtrained to <hi>Abraham only,</hi> and not applied to <hi>any</hi> other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever. I do think therefore, it was an unwary Expreſſion of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to make Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a <hi>Seal</hi> of the Covenant of Grace under the Law, to <hi>all</hi> circumciſed Infants, when it's applied by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Abraham only,</hi> and not to <hi>any one</hi> of his Poſterity: Nor could it be, becauſe it was to him as a <hi>Seal</hi> of <hi>that</hi> Promiſe, that he ſhould be the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Believers; which could not be true of <hi>Individuals,</hi> nor of <hi>any other</hi> but himſelf, it being commanded to them for other Ends.</p>
               <p>As for his calling Baptiſm a <hi>Seal</hi> of the New Covenant, I muſt ſay the ſame of it <hi>as</hi> of the <hi>other:</hi> For, 1. It is <hi>no where</hi> called <hi>ſo</hi> in all the Holy Scripture, and therefore no metaphorical Uſe to be made of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Holy Scriptures do tell us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>other</hi> thing that is the <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>New</hi> and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant, wherewith Believers are <hi>ſealed</hi> under the Goſpel, and that is the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.21, 22. <hi>Now he which ſtabliſheth us with you in Chriſt, and hath anointed us, is God; who hath alſo ſealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.</hi> Epheſ. 1.13. <hi>After ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe:</hi> Epheſ. 4.30. <hi>And grieve not the holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are ſealed unto the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> The Learned Dr. <hi>Cox,</hi> upon theſe words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. ſaith, <q>It is <hi>Genitivus Speciei,</hi> as when we read the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34587:29"/>City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the like: For we read not, ſaith he, that any other Ordinance (No, not Baptiſm) is ſo called in Scripture; but in the New Teſtament, the ſealing of Believers is attributed to the Holy Ghoſt.—For it is not poſſible to conceive that Circumciſion ſhould be a <hi>Seal</hi> of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>one</hi> that <hi>never</hi> had Faith: And it is equally abſurd to ſay, that Circumciſion was a <hi>Seal</hi> unto <hi>all</hi> its Subjects of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Faith, which they had while uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, <hi>as</hi> to affirm, that it was the <hi>Seal</hi> of a <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> relation to <hi>all</hi> Believers, unto <hi>every one</hi> that received it.</q> And I hope this Gentleman will allow me to ſay, that it's <hi>more</hi> abſurd <hi>now</hi> under the Goſpel, wherein <hi>all</hi> the Children of the <hi>Covenant</hi> are to be <hi>taught</hi> of God, and <hi>all</hi> of them to know God, that any ſhould affirm, that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is a <hi>Seal</hi> to Infants who have <hi>no</hi> Faith at all, neither in <hi>Habit</hi> nor in <hi>Act;</hi> eſpeeially ſeeing it's <hi>no where</hi> called ſo in the Holy Scriptures. If men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ough the Lightneſs and Vanity of their Minds, muſt needs play with <hi>metaphorical</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Scripture, yet I know not how they ſhould have a liberty to <hi>impoſe</hi> words upon us, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth, which are not at <hi>any</hi> time, nor in <hi>any</hi> place, ſo much as mentioned. This is <hi>our</hi> Caſe; Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will have <hi>Baptiſm</hi> called the <hi>Seal</hi> of the Covenant, we will <hi>not</hi> allow it him, becauſe it's <hi>no where</hi> ſo called in Scripture. But ſuppoſe we ſhould, it would <hi>ruine</hi> his <hi>beloved</hi> Cauſe; for then it could be adminiſtred to <hi>none</hi> but <hi>ſuch</hi> who are <hi>true</hi> Believers.</p>
               <p>But before Mr. <hi>H.</hi> goes any further, he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes this Queſtion, Who we are to underſtand by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34587:30"/>the <hi>Children</hi> in the Text? <hi>viz.</hi> Acts. 2 39. His Anſwer is, No doubt but they are the <hi>very ſame</hi> which in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 are called <hi>Seed.</hi> The Reaſon he gives for it is, from the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> word there uſed: The Word (ſaith he) is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, uſed for <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes, Matt.</hi> 21.18. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p>How he came to give us <hi>this</hi> ſence of the Word, ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Scope</hi> of the place, I know not: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the ſingular, is rendred thus by a late famous Grecian, A <hi>Child,</hi> an <hi>Off-ſpring,</hi> and in the plural a <hi>numerous Off-ſpring.</hi> In the <hi>2d.</hi> Epiſtle of <hi>John, Ver.</hi> 1. he uſes the ſame Words, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The elder unto the elect Lady and her Children:</hi> Here it's rendred <hi>Children,</hi> as it is in <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.39. but not <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes:</hi> For you have their Character given in <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced greatly, that I found of thy Children walking in truth, as we have received a commandment from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> And he writes to <hi>her</hi> and <hi>them</hi> in the plural, to <hi>look</hi>-to <hi>themſelves,</hi> and to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> falſe Teachers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in the laſt Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith, The <hi>Children</hi> of thy Elect Siſter <hi>greet</hi> thee. Now theſe things can <hi>no ways</hi> agree with Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes:</hi> And he hath every whit as much Reaſon to give this ſence of the word here, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. it being the ſame Word. But let us examine his other two Texts.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.18. <hi>Now in the morning as he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the City, he hungred.</hi> This I am ſure hath <hi>neither</hi> the <hi>word</hi> nor <hi>thing</hi> he intends: But I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he intended the <hi>15th.</hi> Verſe; <hi>And when the chief Prieſts and Scribes ſaw the wonderful things that he did, and the Children crying in the Temple, and ſaying, Hoſanna to the ſon of David, they were ſore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34587:30"/>diſpleaſed:</hi> The word that is here tranſlated <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> is not the ſame word as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and if we may believe our Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cographers, they tell us, that in <hi>this very</hi> Text <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.15. it ſignifies a <hi>Boy,</hi> or young <hi>Maid;</hi> ſometimes a <hi>Son,</hi> and ſometimes a <hi>Servant:</hi> And we have an Inſtance in <hi>Mark</hi> 5.39, 40, 41, 42. of a young <hi>Maid</hi> of 12 years of Age, where the <hi>ſame</hi> word is rendred <hi>Damſel: And ſtraight-way the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel aroſe and walked, for ſhe was of the Age of twelve years:</hi> Now had not her Age been recorded, no doubt but Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would have inſiſted upon it, that ſhe was a <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Child,</hi> becauſe it's ſaid in <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>my little daughter.</hi> But to proceed, they alſo tell us it's taken for a <hi>Maid-ſervant,</hi> a <hi>Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is rendred <hi>Gal</hi> 4.22, 30. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Hagar,</hi> after the birth of <hi>Iſhmael; Cast out the Bond-woman and her ſon:</hi> Now in this place it's impoſſible to prove <hi>Hagar</hi> a little ſucking <hi>have,</hi> and therefore I ſuppoſe he will not attempt it. I hope the Reader will obſerve, how I came to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d to the <hi>uſe</hi> of this word by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> But the Reaſon why he quoted it, I know not; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he took it for granted, becauſe he found <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bible, it muſt needs be the ſame word in <hi>Greek;</hi> which he may now find to be a miſtake. But I ſhall proceed to conſider his other Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p>In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. the word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, your <hi>Children;</hi> nor will this Text do him any Service, to prove what he brings it for; becauſe it's often uſed for perſons of <hi>grown</hi> years; <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Sons</hi> of God: He cannot ſuppoſe theſe to be <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes,</hi> for that they had <hi>actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> received Chriſt, and believed on his Name.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34587:31"/>The learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> in his <hi>Critiea Sacra,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>liberi,</hi> often: And beſides what he ſaith upon <hi>John.</hi> 1.12. He cites the uſe of it in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: It is uſed there in the <hi>plural</hi> Number, ſuch as are begotten and born of them; and being of the Neuter Gender doth include <hi>both</hi> Sexes, Males and Females, Sons and Daughters, which agrees with thoſe words, <hi>Asts.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Your Sons and your Daughters ſhall propheſie:</hi> Coloſ. 3.20. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur ad Filios, &amp; Filias imò ad Nepotes:</hi> It is extended to their Sons and Daughters; yea, as One hath it, <hi>Nepotes vocant omnes poſteros,</hi> They call all their poſterity by that name. But not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to uſe <hi>polixity</hi> in the handling of it, take the plain words of my fore-named Author: It is a <hi>general</hi> word, which in Scripture and <hi>other</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is uſed to ſet forth <hi>all</hi> ſorts of <hi>Children,</hi> of what <hi>ſex,</hi> of what <hi>age,</hi> of what <hi>degree</hi> ſoever they be.</p>
               <p>To this I ſhall only add this <hi>brief</hi> Obſervation, That thoſe Exhortations ſpoken of in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. and <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.20. where it is written, <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ren obey your Parents in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be intended <hi>ſuch</hi> Children of <hi>grown</hi> years that were <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>viſible</hi> Church of Chriſt by <hi>Repentance,</hi> Faith, and Baptiſm; becauſe 'tis ſuch the Apoſtle directs his Epiſtles unto, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.1. <hi>To the ſaints which are at Epheſus, and to the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> And in <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. <hi>To the ſaints and faithful brethren in Chriſt, which are at Coloſs:</hi> Now theſe words cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be applied to <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes,</hi> unto whom Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would have the uſe of the Word <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay further, where the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> uſes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Filioli, <hi>little</hi> Children, (which is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34587:31"/>the Diminutive of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) no leſs than <hi>eight</hi> times in his <hi>firſt</hi> Epiſtle, as 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 12, 28. and 3.4, 7, 18. and 4.4. and 5.21. yet in none of thoſe places doth he intend <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Babes;</hi> for there are ſuch things required of them which <hi>ſuch</hi> Infants are <hi>not</hi> able to perform; for in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.1. They are exhorted <hi>not</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. They had <hi>heard</hi> that Antichriſt ſhould come: <hi>Ver.</hi> 28. They are exhorted to abide in Chriſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Little</hi> Children, let no man <hi>deceive</hi> you, <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. not to Love in <hi>word</hi> and tongue, but in deed and in <hi>truth, Ver.</hi> 4, and 5. he tells them they <hi>knew</hi> that Chriſt was manifeſted to take away their Sins. Ye have <hi>overcome, &amp;c.</hi> 5.21. <hi>little</hi> Children, <hi>keep</hi> your ſelves <hi>from</hi> Idols. Now it's evident to the <hi>meaneſt</hi> Capacity, that <hi>little</hi> ſucking <hi>Children</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do all theſe things here ſpoken of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are <hi>not</hi> at <hi>all</hi> intended in <hi>any</hi> of thoſe places. Now had Mr. <hi>H</hi> found the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Asts</hi> 2.39. as he did the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, how would he have <hi>ſwaggered</hi> with it? But the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> knew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>how</hi> to expreſs the Mind of God in <hi>that</hi> place than Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth to underſtand it, Prejudice hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blinded his Eyes.</p>
               <p>For his other Reaſon that he gives, that it is a Repetition of the grand Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. I have anſwered that already, and therefore I had thought to have ſaid no more to that; but finding him to return again to it in <hi>page</hi> 26. I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour fully to clear the Point before I leave it.</p>
               <p>His Words are theſe; Now to return to <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. The <hi>promiſe</hi> is to <hi>you,</hi> and to your <hi>Children.</hi> I will conclude (ſaith he) in the words of Holy Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> Break (ſaith he) the Text into an hundred pieces, and <hi>blood</hi> it as men pleaſe, this is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34587:32"/>the <hi>genuine</hi> Theſis, which cannot be neglected, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe to whom the <hi>promiſe</hi> of the Covenant belongs, <hi>thoſe</hi> ſhould be <hi>baptiſed:</hi> But the <hi>promiſe</hi> of the Covenant is to you, and to your Children; therefore <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Children <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth not inſiſt upon it; however I ſhall give this Anſwer thereunto.</p>
               <p>If Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> intended ſuch of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that were the called of God by <hi>Repentance,</hi> Faith, and <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> then the gift of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit belonged to them as well as to their Parents: But if he doth <hi>not,</hi> it is a <hi>heap</hi> of words without Reaſon or Truth, or any <hi>proper</hi> Signification: For here is (by him) neither <hi>Promiſe,</hi> nor Covenant, nor any thing plainly expreſt: For the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Berith,</hi> is thus rendred, <hi>a Covenant, or mutual Paction;</hi> ſo called from the Choice made of the Perſons and Conditions in a Covenant. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertſon's ſecond Gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as the learned <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica ſacra</hi> ſaith, <hi>Berith</hi> is <hi>Fadus pactum,</hi> and quotes <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and <hi>Buxtorf</hi> for his Authority; <hi>Quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt, ut Aben Ezra ſcribit, mutuus conſenſus duorum ſuper aliquare:</hi> That a Covenant, as <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> writes, is a mutual Conſent of two upon any matter. And he further ſaith, it ſignifieth both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Compact or Covenant made between parties, as <hi>Aquila</hi> tranſlateth it, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Teſtiment or diſpoſition of ones laſt Will, as the word is uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. And the learned Dr. <hi>Coxe,</hi> in his diſcourſe of the Covenants, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. ſaith, Covenant relation to God, and intereſt in him, doth not immediately reſult from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of a Covenant, and terms of Covenant rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to man, but it is by reſtipulation that he actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34587:32"/>enters into Covenant with God, and becomes an interreſſed party in the Covenant, it is a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Conſent of the parties in Covenant, that ſtates and compleats a Covenant-relation; and this is called an avouching of the Lord to be their God, by conſent to the terms of a Covenant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to them: It includes mutual ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But what <hi>Rutherford</hi> ſaith, is not at all agreeable to the nature of Man's entring into Covenant with God under the Goſpel, becauſe the Subjects he ſpeaks of, <hi>viz.</hi> Little Infants, are not capable of underſtanding, much leſs of giving themſelves up to God in baptiſm, in the way of a Covenant Engagement: And I remember a ſaying of Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter,</hi> in a Sermon I heard him preach ſome years agoe, which is as follows; <q>It was the practice of the Church generally for the firſt five hundred years not to admit any to Baptiſm, but ſuch that did firſt make a publick profeſſion of their Faith before the Church: But for as much as the Church hath alter'd the time of Baptiſm, and doth adminiſter it to ſuch that are not capable to make ſuch a profeſſion of their Faith, were I a Paſtor of a particular Congregation, I would admit none to the Lord's Supper, but ſuch who ſhould firſt make a publick profeſſion of their Faith before the Church; for we ought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch the Lord to be our God.</q> Now by what Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> ſaith in his Book concerning Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> I take him to be of that ſort of Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians which are called <hi>Baxterians:</hi> And if he will abide by the ſentence of his Maſter, then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants can make no reſtipulation, and ſo not be actually in the Covenant: For they cannot avouch
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34587:33"/>the Lord to be their God, and conſequently can have no right to Baptiſm by vertue of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, if they are not actually in it.</p>
               <p>But further, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſaith, If this diſpleaſe, we will ſtand by Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> his Syllogiſtical Frame upon the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> That they who have a right to be baptized by the word of Promiſe, they alſo have a right to be baptized by the word of Command: But the Infants of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parents have a right to be baptized by the word of promiſe, therefore they have a right by the word of Command.</p>
               <p>Who this Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> is, I neither know, nor care; but this I know, that his Argument is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe he brings it for.</p>
               <p>For, 1. He doth not toll us what this word of promiſe is. Nor, 2. Where it is written. And therefore we are at as great a loſs as before. But if there be any conſiſtence betwixt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and him, it is in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. and if he reads the Text but once more without Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> his Spectacles, he will not find any promiſe there, that Infants ſhall be baptized.</p>
               <p>I may with far better Authority argue thus,</p>
               <p>If there be no Command in all the Scripture, that Infants ſhould be baptized, nor any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of any bleſſing to them in being baptized, then they have no right to be baptized: But there is no Command in all the Scripture that Infants ſhould be baptized, nor any Promiſe of any bleſſing to them in being baptized: <hi>Ergo,</hi> They have no right to be baptized. The <hi>major</hi> is undeniable, the <hi>minor</hi> is proved from that univerſal ſilence throughout the whole Book of God, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot being the leaſt word ſpoken
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34587:33"/>concerning it, either directly or indirectly of any ſuch command or promiſe. And yet for all this, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> according to his uſual way of <hi>ludere ſacra,</hi> trifling and fooling with Holy Things, ſaith, He hath now anſwered our deſire, here is both a word of Command and a word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; But it is in his Friend <hi>Stephens</hi> his Argument, and not in the Holy Scripture. But ſeeing, he hath promiſed he will ſtand by Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> his Syllogiſtical Frame, we have reaſon to conclude he values it above any thing that can be ſaid to the contrary, tho' never ſo plain evidence be given him from the Holy Scriptures. But if it were not the gain of filthy lucre that incited him thereto, perhaps he might as well change his mind about that, as he hath done about ſome other things, when he left a ſmall Benefice under Epiſcopacy, to get a better Livelyhood under the form of Presbytery.</p>
               <p>I have ſaid enough to this of the Covenant to ſatisfie any man that is willing to receive ſatisfaction, either from Scripture or the reaſon of the thing: But if neither of thoſe will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, we muſt leave ſuch to ſtand and fall to their own Maſters. For all the benefit we can expect from the beſt of means where it is will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rejected, is, that they will ſtill perſevere in their old practiſes, contradicting and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming the way of the Goſpel, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did in oppoſition to the Apoſtles Doctrine, to their own Deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34587:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Shewing that the right manner how Baptiſm ought to be adminiſtred, is by Dipping, Plunging, or Overwhelming the whole Body of the Perſon baptized under Water: And that it is not by ſprinkling, or otherwiſe applying Water to the Perſon baptized, as Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> ſaith.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>H.</hi> tells us, The Anabaptiſts confidently affirm, the right manner is dipping the whole body under water, and (ſay they) if not ſo performed, is no baptiſm at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are many who do thus affirm, and that truly; but that the Anabaptiſts do ſo, I know not, for I do not know of any Anabaptiſt in the World. If he means thoſe that do baptize believers upon profeſſion of Faith, they cannot be called Anabaptiſts, becauſe they do not baptize any who were before baptized; and I hope he is ſo good a Maſter of the Word himſelf uſes, as to know the Etymology thereof: For the word <hi>Ana</hi> ſignifies again, and we do not baptize any that were baptized before. And indeed it's neither like a Man, much leſs a Scholar, to beg the Queſtion, but to prove it. Beſides, he knows we deny ſprinkling to be Baptiſm, and till he hath proved himſelf, or any of thoſe he ſprinkles to be baptized, he hath no reaſon to call us Anabaptiſts.</p>
               <p>Now for dipping in Baptiſm (ſaith he) they plead.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34587:34"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the <hi>Greek</hi> Word ſignifies to Dip.</item>
                  <item>2. The manner of baptizing in the primitive times was by dipping.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>John</hi>'s baptizing at <hi>Aenon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. The word Burial, being buried in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> A man would ſuppoſe that this plea were good, but it ſeems not pleaſing to Mr. <hi>Harriſon.</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſaith, we ſay the word baptizing in <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifies to be Dipped: They ſay, to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize in <hi>Engliſh</hi> is to dip: And what doth he ſay to that? And ſo there is the Engliſh of Engliſh. This is a meer Quibble, for baptize is from <hi>baptizo,</hi> and is not originally an Engliſh Word, and by his good favour there is (if he will have it ſo) other Engliſh for it, <hi>viz.</hi> to dip or plunge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whether he will or no, we believe that to be the ſignification of the word, and doubt not to make it appear.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Well, (ſaith he) but let us enquire what theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifie in the Original Language: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> comes indeed from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to dip or plunge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I wiſh Mr. <hi>H.</hi> would do by himſelf in this, as he ſaith he will do by Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> his Syllogiſtical Frame, ſtand by it: For if the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies to dip or plunge, how comes its derivatives to ſignifie otherwiſe? <hi>Bapto</hi> is the Theme or Root from whence all the other are derived, and the Branches certainly are of the ſame nature with the Root. What wiſe man expects Apples to grow upon an Oak, or Grapes from Thorns, or Figs from Thiſtles? And it's as ſtrange to think, that the genuine and proper
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34587:35"/>derivatives of <hi>Bapto,</hi> to dip or plunge, ſhould ſignifie to ſprinkle or ſcatter.</p>
               <p>But in the very next words he ſaith, But it is ſeldom or never uſed for dipping in the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's a wonder that the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, who were divinely inſpired, ſhould feldom or never uſe a word in its right ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Pray let Mr. <hi>H.</hi> either retract this unwary aſſertion, or elſe acquit himſelf from blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt, if he knows how. It's a dangerous thing to charge the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pen-men at this rate: But ſeeing he ſaith, it's ſeldom or never ſo uſed in the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it implies that it's ſo uſed by other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; Why doth he not tell us who they are? that we may apply to them for the right uſe of words, and not any longer be deceived by the Pen-men of the Scripture. Doth he not ſee what a Trifler he is about divine things, and what horrid conſequences do attend ſuch a frothy way of arguing? Can he believe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? I do not think it poſſible.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, though it be derived of a word that ſignifies to dip, it does not follow it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptizo,</hi> is the word he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, or nothing; for himſelf puts that down, and that muſt be the it he means; and tells us, it's never rendred to dip in all the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Nay, further, (he ſaith) it's not yet proved that it ever ſignifies dipping in all the New Teſtament. Now ſeeing he hath mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> in his <hi>Critica Sacra,</hi> and prefaced it with theſe words, <hi>Inſtar omnia,</hi> in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34587:35"/>the ſtead of all, I will examine his Author; Theſe are his Words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptizo,</hi> the word Baptize, (notwithſtanding what he cites out of Dr. <hi>Featly</hi>) he declares to be derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Bapto, Tingo,</hi> to dip or plunge into the Water, and ſignifieth primarily ſuch a kind of waſhing as is uſed in <hi>Bucks,</hi> where Linnen is plunged and dipt. Now if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> doth not know how they uſe to order their Linnen when they waſh Bucks, let him ask the good women in the Countrey, and they will inform him, that they do not ſprinkle a little water only upon their Cloaths, but cover them all over with it. And again, ſaith the Learned <hi>Leigh,</hi> the native and proper ſignification of it is, to dip into Water, or to plunge under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and quotes ſeveral Places in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament where it's ſo uſed; as <hi>John</hi> 3.22, 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. Again, for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptiſma,</hi> he ſaith it is dipping into Water, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptiſmos, Merſionem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat in aquam:</hi> It ſignifies to be drowned, or overwhelmed in the Water. He further ſaith, That it appeareth from the Notation and Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology of the word it ſelf, what was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of adminiſtring Baptiſm in the beginning, whereas we now have rather Rantiſm (that is, Sprinkling) in the ſtead of Baptiſm: Wherefore he further tells us, that we might not be deceived by a fallacious uſe of ſome latter Authors, as if leſs than dipping the whole Body under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were intended, when they uſe the word waſh, or waſhing, in the ſtead of baptizing; <hi>Neque vero</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſignificat lavare, niſi à conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenti: Nam propriè declarat tingendi cauſâ im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergere:</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34587:36"/>Neither indeed doth the word <hi>Baptizein</hi> ſignifie to waſh, except only by conſequence.</p>
               <p>For it properly declares they are to be plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under water, as things are that they may be dyed. Again, <hi>Siquidem proprie baptiſmos eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſio, intinctio; Baptiſmos</hi> is properly a dipping, a dying. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Intin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor,</hi> Dipt; For which he quotes <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. He hath his <hi>Veſture dipt in blood:</hi> And concludes thus, it is taken from the Dyers Vatt, and is a dying, or giving a freſh colour, and not a bare waſhing only, whence cometh Baptiſm. So that you may ſee how fairly he is confuted out of his own Author.</p>
               <p>We will now examine another of his Authors, <hi>Schrevelius,</hi> as publiſhed with many additions by the Famous Linguiſt Mr. <hi>William Robertſon,</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Cornelij Schrevelij, Lexicon manuale Graco-Latinum, copioſiſſime Adauctum.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Bapto, Intingo, Mergo, Lavo, hine</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptizo, idem Baptiſmos &amp; Baptiſma,</hi> &amp;c. all which ſignifie to dye, to dip or plunge, but not one word of ſprinkling ſo much as mentioned: And there was was a very good reaſon fet it, becauſe he tells us there is another word in the <hi>Greek</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that by; I ſhall give it you from the ſame Author, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rantizo, Aſpergo,</hi> to ſprinkle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rantiſmos, Aſperſio,</hi> Sprinkling; and <hi>Rantiſma</hi> the ſame. So that you may ſee the words are as different in the <hi>Greek</hi> as they are in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Languages, and are as diſcernable as they are in Engliſh: And every Engliſh Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der knows there is a vaſt difference in the Action ſignified by dipping, and that ſignified by ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Sprinkling is not Dipping, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34587:36"/>is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and ſeeing the Spirit of God uſes two Words to ſignifie two different actions, it would be great preſumption in us to confound them. <hi>Alſtedius</hi> in his <hi>Lexicon Theologicum,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>tantum ſignificat immergere, non lavare, niſi ex conſequenti;</hi> that <hi>Baptizein</hi> ſignifies on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to dip, plunge, or drown, and not to waſh, except by conſequence. Beſides, as I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my Epiſtle concerning Baptiſm, that this ſence is ſo well underſtood, however it comes about that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is ſo great a ſtranger to it, that every School-boy in the Greek Grammar can tell you, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is there rendred <hi>mergo, immergo,</hi> to dip, to plunge or overwhelm, and that all its Derivatives are uſed in the ſame ſence.</p>
               <p>I could give you multitudes of Inſtances to prove, that the right way of baptizing is by dipping. Mr. <hi>John Goſnold</hi> in his excellent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, ſaith, The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baptizo,</hi> in its proper and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſignification is to dip: This (ſaith he) the Learned in all Ages, and all Lexicous or Dictionaries do acknowledge; nor can we find by the moſt diligent ſearch, that 'tis otherwiſe accepted by any Author whatſoever, excepting ſome very few of late.</p>
               <p>He hath there given us divers Inſtances from men of good Authority for Learning (as he ſaith) in all Nations, ſome of them I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> as Learned a man as any our latter Age hath afforded, ſaith, the word ſignifies to dip under water. Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his Body of Divinity, ſaith the ſame: As alſo Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:34587:37"/>in his Marrow of Divinity, <hi>Book</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 40. As alſo Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ball</hi>'s Catechiſm hath it, waſhed by dipping. Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Critica ſacra</hi> on the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, the laſt and beſt of this kind, ſaith, The native and proper ſignification of the Verb is to dip into water, or to plunge under Water, and of the ſubſtantive dipping into Water: So alſo <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s Dictionary. The Dutch Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to their Language, reads for <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>John</hi> the Dipper, and for he bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized them, he dipped them: And the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book preſcribes Dipping as the beſt way for the manner of the performance of this Ordinance, and always places it firſt, The Prieſt ſhall dip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So likewiſe <hi>Daniel Rogers,</hi> a famous Engliſh Writer, in his Treatiſe of the two Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c. Part</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. hath theſe Words, It ought to be the Churches part to cleave to the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which is dipping; eſpecially it not being left arbitrary by our Church, to the diſcretion of the Miniſter, but required to dip, or dive: That he betrays the Church, whoſe Officer he is, to a diſorder'd Error, if he cleave not to the Inſtitution, which is to dip.</p>
               <p>And this (ſaith he) I ſo aver, as thinking it exceeding material to the Ordinance, and no ſlight thing; yea, which Antiquity conſtantly, and without exceeption of Countries, hot or cold, witneſſes unto; and eſpecially the conſtant word of the Holy Ghoſt, firſt and laſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, as a Learned <hi>Critick</hi> upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. hath noted, to wit <hi>Cauſabon.</hi> And he further ſaith, I doubt not but contrary to our Churches inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34587:37"/>this Error having once crept in, is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſtill by the carnal eaſe of ſuch, as looking more at themſelves than at God, ſtretch the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Church in this caſe deeper and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than either the Church her ſelf would, or the ſolemneſs of this Sacrament may well and ſafely admit. I ſpeak this, (ſaith he) as deſiring ſuch as it concerns, in their places, to look to their Duty in this behalf. Afterward he further ſaith, I confeſs my ſelf unconvinced by Demonſtration of Scripture, for Infants ſprinkling. Thus you ſee here is a Cloud of Witneſſes to prove that baptizing was, and ought to be, by dipping or plunging the whole Body under Water. And I am perſwaded, there was not one of theſe but underſtood the Etymology of the Greek word <hi>Baptizo,</hi> as well as Mr. <hi>Harriſon;</hi> and yet they all agree, that Dipping is the right manner of baptizing.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is pleaſed to tell us, as tho' our Tranſlators had never rendred the Word to <hi>dip,</hi> or that it ſignified <hi>dipping</hi> in all the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>pag.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I will prove, that in divers places, where there was nothing of the ſtreſs of the Controverſy depending, they have ſo rendred it, as I have given a plain and full Account in my Epiſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Baptiſm, to which I refer you; as <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24. <hi>John</hi> 13.26. it's tranſlated <hi>dipt, dippeth, dip, dipped,</hi> as you will ſee by reading the places cited.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing he alſo tells us, to <hi>ſprinkle,</hi> is a certain known ſenſe of the Word, and that it ſignifies to baptize by ſprinkling, <hi>page</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, in the words of the learned Mr. <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:34587:38"/>the Tranſlators themſelves never once in all the New Teſtament renderd it by <hi>ſprinkling:</hi> There is another word for that, which they conſtantly tranſlate to <hi>ſprinkle,</hi> to wit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rantizo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Tranſlators do in effect render the word <hi>Baptizo</hi> as we do; for they tranſlate it <hi>waſhing, Mark</hi> 7.4, 8. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.38. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. <hi>waſhed;</hi> which all know cannot be done by ſprinkling, but muſt be by dipping or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, ſo much of it as is waſhed, into the Water: And where it is ſpoken of Perſons, it can ſignify no leſs than the whole body being dipt thereir. And that this was the Practice in the firſt times of the Goſpel, I will alledge two or three Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and ſo paſs on.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.6. <hi>were baptized in Jordan:</hi> The Aſſemblies Annotations read it, <hi>dipping in Jordan:</hi> And <hi>Diodate</hi> ſaith, <hi>they were plunged in water.</hi> In <hi>Ver.</hi> 16. <hi>And Jeſus when he was baptized,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cajetan</hi> ſaith, Chriſt was baptized not by ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but by dipping into the Water: And <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas Brugenſis</hi> upon the ſame place ſaith, The Party baptized went into the Water, as deep as his Thighs or Navel, the reſt of his Body was dipt, not ſprinkled.</p>
               <p>Upon <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38, 39. <hi>And he baptized him,</hi> &amp;c. The Aſſemblies Annotations ſaith, They were wont to dip the whole body: And <hi>Piſcator</hi> on the place ſaith, The ancient manner of Baptiſm was, that the whole Body was dipt into the Water.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> a great Antiquary, in his <hi>Diatribae,</hi> on <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. ſaith, That there was no ſuch thing as ſprinkling uſed in Baptiſm, in the Apoſtles time, nor many Ages after them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo upon <hi>John</hi> 3.22, 23. ſaith, From
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34587:38"/>this place you may gather, that <hi>John</hi> and Chriſt adminiſtred Baptiſm by plunging the whole Body into the Water; and confeſſes, That the Church hath aſſumed this Liberty to her ſelf of ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>I might add many other Teſtimonies to prove this Truth, but I am tired with writing; and theſe I have already alledged are more than ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>Now a man would think it were highly reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſhould give us ſome plain Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for his Rantiſm, or Sprinkling, to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when I have given my ſelf ſo much Trouble to ſatisfy his Curioſity: But he puts us off with a ſham Pretence, without any Scripture Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, either from the Engliſh Tranſlation, or from the Greek.</p>
               <p>His Pretence is this, That in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. it ſignifies to baptize by ſprinkling; for all the World knows a Cloud doth but ſprinkle.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, I pray, how this Man deals with us: Doth the Text by him quoted, ſay, They were baptized by ſprinling? Surely, No: There is not one word of ſprinkling ſo much as mentioned.</p>
               <p>In the next Page he abuſes his Reader more, for there he tells him, that the Word <hi>Baptizo</hi> doth ſignify <hi>ſprinkling;</hi> but then his Heart failing him in the Proof, he adds, or to baptize by ſprinkling, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. <hi>They were all</hi> (Inſants as well as grown Perſons) <hi>baptized by the Cloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two great Abuſes he puts upon his unwary Reader: 1. He falſifies the Text; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being baptized unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea, he ſaith, by the Cloud. Doth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34587:39"/>he think the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, did not know how to uſe an apt word to expreſs his meaning by, but he muſt be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch a one as he to mend it for him? Had Mr. <hi>H.</hi> the like Advantage againſt us, we might have expected to have been ſufficiently abuſed by his virulent Pen; but he ſhall ſee (by the Grace of God) that we have other wiſe learned Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly.</hi> He tells us, They were all (Infants as well as grown Perſons) baptized.</p>
               <p>Who told him ſo? He is a bold Man, to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon adding to the Word of God. Let us read the words, and then you will ſee there is not the leaſt mention of Infants in the Text: But his Deſign was, to prove Infants the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as well as <hi>ſprinkling</hi> the manner of Baptiſm. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Moreover, Brethren, I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant, how that all our</hi> Fathers <hi>were under the Cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea; and were all baptized unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea; and did all eat the ſame ſpiritual meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpiritual drink; for they drank of that ſpiritual Rock that followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt: But with many of them God was not well pleaſed, for they were overthrown in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let us ſee if we can (by Gods Aſſiſtance) find out the Mind of the Spirit in theſe words:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Subjects are deſcribed, to wit, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>All our Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are ſaid to eat ſpiritual Meat, and drink ſpiritual Drink, to drink of Chirſt, the Rock of Ages.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34587:39"/>
               <p n="3">3. That from hence it will manifeſtly appear, That all the Perſons ſaid to be Baptiſed unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> &amp;c. were true Beleivers; becauſe none can eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, but ſuch that are united to him by Faith; <hi>John</hi> 6.32, 33, 34, 35, 36. I ſhall only recite part of the words, you may read the reſt at your leiſure; <hi>And Jeſus ſaid unto them, I am the bread of Life; he that cometh to me ſhall never hunger, and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on me ſhall never thirſt,</hi> &amp;c. See alſo from <hi>Ver.</hi> 47. to <hi>Ver.</hi> 59. So that it appears from hence, That it was only the Believers in Chriſt, among that mixt multitude, that were the Perſons intended.</p>
               <p>But <hi>4ly. With many of them God was not well pleaſed, for they were overthrown in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> Now let us examine who thoſe were whoſe Carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſs: In <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Becauſe all thoſe Men which have ſeen my glory, and my Miracles which I did in Egypt, and in the Wilderneſs, and have tempted me now theſe ten times, and have not hearkned to my voice, ſurely they ſhall not ſee the land,</hi> &amp;c. V. 29. <hi>Your Carkaſſes ſhall fall in this Wilderneſs, and all that were numbered of you, according to your whole number, from twenty years old and upward,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſave Caleb the ſon of Jephunneh, and Joſhua the ſon of Nun:</hi> Here you ſee who they were whoſe Carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſs, who are called Fathers, <hi>viz.</hi> The men among them from Twenty years old and upward; they ſinned, they murmered, they tempted Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and their Carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſs: From whence the Apoſtle cautions theſe Saints at <hi>Corinth</hi> to be warned by their Example, <hi>V.</hi> 12. <hi>Wherefore let him that thinketh he ſtands, take heed leaſt he fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34587:40"/>
               <p>But, ſaith Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Infants as well as grown Perſons.</p>
               <p>I pray therefore ſee what is written from the mouth of God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.31, 32. <hi>But your little ones, which ye ſaid ſhould be a prey, them will I bring in, and they ſhall know the land which ye have deſpiſed: But as for you, your Carkaſſes they ſhall fall in this Wilderneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence I infer, That if Baptiſm were here caken for an Ordinance adminiſtred by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Subjects of it, as expreſſed by the Apoſtle, were Fathers; and from that of <hi>Numbers,</hi> where we are told what they were, They are called men, and ſaid to be twenty years old and upward. So that you may ſee Mr. <hi>H.</hi> makes ſtrange work in his Interpretation of Scripture, for he turns Men into Infants.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2ly.</hi> If it muſt be ſo taken as an Ordinance, then Believers in Chriſt are the only Subjects of it: For they drank of that Spiritual Rock that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them, and that Rock was Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith Mr. <hi>H.</hi> They were Baptiſed by ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for they were all Baptiſed by the Cloud; and a Cloud doth but ſprinkle, or pour out water, not Dip.</p>
               <p>What he means by a Cloud dipping, I know not; but when he hath falſified the Text, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>by,</hi> in the room of <hi>in,</hi> he had a mind to accommodate it to his own Fancy.</p>
               <p>But why Mr. <hi>H.</hi> fancies that they were ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Cloud, I cannot tell, except it be that he prefers his own Imaginations before the written Word. I would ask this Gentleman a few Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34587:40"/>
               <p n="1">1. How he knows there was Water in this Cloud?</p>
               <p>If he ſhall ſay, that all Clouds have Water in them, that I muſt deny: Beſides other Reaſons that might perhaps be aſſigned, I ſhall offer this in Evidence, That in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 12. we read of Clouds without Water, and how doth he know but this might be ſuch a Cloud?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> If this Cloud had Water in it, How will he be able to prove, that it dropped upon the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whilſt they were paſſing through the Sea? For I am ſure the Scripture ſaith not one word of it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> If he will but conſider the account that is given of this Cloud in <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21.22. whether he will not find that this which is called the Pillar of a Cloud, was not the Token of God's Preſence, as a Guide to them by day, as the Pillar of Fire was by night? And whether this was not a miraculous manifeſtation of God's Favour to them, and not a common natural cloud? ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.21, 29. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.9. Now theſe places aſſure us they went thro' the midſt of the Sea, as on dry Land, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were a Wall unto them, on the right hand and on the left: Pray how had it been dry Land, if it had rained upon them all the time they paſſed thro'? Compare but this with <hi>Pſalm</hi> 105.39. <hi>He ſpread a Cloud for a Covering,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4ly.</hi> Seeing the word in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whether it being here uſed in the paſſive form, it may not properly be read thus, They were all overwhelmed unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea, as they muſt needs be when the Cloud covered them, and the Waters were a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34587:41"/>Wall unto them, on the right hand and on the left: So that the main deſign of the Apoſtle, among other Mercies of God beſtowed upon that People, is to commemorate that great and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful deliverance at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and then to ſhew us what an ungrateful People they were, thus to ſin againſt him, and to cauſe him for their ſins to deſtroy them in the Wilderneſs. And if this be the Scope of the place, (as I believe it is) that ſo we might be warned by their fall, to avoid falling into Apoſtacy againſt God, as they did; and had our tranſlators ſo rendred the word, as it imports in our Engliſh Tongue, no Man would ever have dreamt of an Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm from this Text.</p>
               <p>If notwithſtanding all that I have ſaid upon the Text, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will ſtill inſiſt upon it, that it was a Baptiſm, and that by ſprinkling, I ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereto the <hi>Dutch</hi> Tranſlators, to ſhew him their Opinion to the contrary; who being <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> their words may poſſibly have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er force upon his Underſtanding: They read it thus, <hi>Ende alle in Moſen gedoopt Zin,</hi> And they were all dipt unto <hi>Moſes:</hi> So that you may ſee the Learned Men in <hi>Holland,</hi> of his own perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, do directly contradict what he ſaith.</p>
               <p>I will only offer one Conſideration more, and ſo paſs it, <hi>viz.</hi> That by the ſame Argument that in the word <hi>all</hi> their Infants were included, their Cattle were included alſo; for they all paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Cloud, and thro' the Sea, as well as their Little Ones; for it is written <hi>Exod,</hi> 10.26. <hi>Our Cattle alſo ſhall go with us, there ſhall not a hoof be leſt behind:</hi> And altho' the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are for bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Bells, I hope Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will not be alſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34587:41"/>for baptizing of Cattle, even the Beaſts of the field: But let him avoid the conſequence if he can, in caſe it be not reſtrained to the Fathers, as in the Text.</p>
               <p>The next thing Mr. <hi>H.</hi> inſiſts upon, is, That there are three ſorts of Baptiſm, that of Water, that of the Spirit, and that of Afflictions; to which I concede: And whereas he ſaith, it's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by one <hi>Greek</hi> Word, I do alſo agree; but that thoſe three (as he ſaith) are but one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, that I deny: He is the firſt that I ever knew affirm it.</p>
               <p>But pray Sir conſider what you ſay; Is Water the Spirit and Fire. Is Affliction the Spirit, or Water Affliction, or Fire Water? Take it which way you will, I believe you will find it attended with difficulties. Indeed Sir it's one of the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate Metaphors that you have yet ſported your ſelf with in your whole Book; and if you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it no better than I do, you might have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore to acquaint the World with the conceited fineneſs of the thought.</p>
               <p>But, Sir, I ſuppoſe I may have the ſame liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give you my thoughts, as you had to impart yours.</p>
               <p>The Text you have brought to prove that theſe three Baptiſms are but one, and expreſt by one word, is <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm:</hi> How this proves that thoſe three Baptiſms are but one Baptiſm, I ſee not. Sir, you are very unhappy in one thing, to lay down Aſſertions, and when you come to prove it, you urge ſuch Texts that do not conclude the thing in Queſtion; but altho' this doth not prove three to be one, and ſo afford us a new ſort of Trinity,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34587:42"/>I will not be ſo ungentile as not to give you my thoughts upon the Text, before I paſs it.</p>
               <p>There is a threefold Baptiſm ſpoken of in the New Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> That of Water, that of Affliction, and that of the Spirit; and yet the Apoſtle here ſpeaks after this manner, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as there is one Lord, one God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now my thoughts are theſe, That it is Water-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm only that is here intended. And my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is this, becauſe, to ſpeak properly, there is no other real baptiſm; for the other two are figurative and metaphorical.</p>
               <p>But beſides, The Apoſtle is there ſpeaking of thoſe Believers as incorporated into one body, and as having been called into one hope of their calling, having Chriſt for their one Lord, and one Faith to unite them to this one Lord, and one Baptiſm to make them viſible Members of this one body, the Church, which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> owns to be an initiating Ordinance; and God as their one common Father, to ſupply all their wants; and that theſe Perſons that were members of this Church, were baptized with water upon believing, you may ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 19. beginning. And this ſeems to me the moſt probable ſenſe of thoſe words, <hi>One Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that it is a real Baptiſm, is evident: For as the word ſignifies to dip, plunge, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them in the water, and as it ſignifies the Burial and Reſurrection of Chriſt, ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the thing done it's a real act; for that every perſon, who is truly baptized, (as I have ſhewed above) is plunged into the water, and alſo raiſed up again out of the water, the thing is really performed: But that of Affliction is only
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34587:42"/>metaphorical, alluding to this of water, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo that of the Spirit and of Fire.</p>
               <p>But perhaps Mr. <hi>H.</hi> may imagine that to be the Baptiſm of Affliction which is not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us hear what he ſaith about it. As to the Baptiſm of Affliction, ſaith he, ſome ſoffer more, ſome leſs; ſome ſuffer lighter croſſes, as Mocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome loſs of goods and liberty, others Death; when he hath ſaid this, he then delivers his Opinion about it in theſe words: Now he that ſuffers leaſt for Chriſt in a Chriſtian man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, doth as truly partake of the Baptiſm of Afflictions as he that ſuffers moſt. Now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I deny this, (as I muſt) how doth he prove it? why he quotes no Text here, but in the foregoing page, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.39. <hi>Ye ſhall indeed drink of the cup that I drink of, and with the baptiſm that I am baptized withall ſhall ye be baptized.</hi> That this is the Baptiſm of Affliction I own.</p>
               <p>We muſt now enquire what this hath a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal reſpect unto, for there is ſomething more than common intended in theſe words: In <hi>Luke</hi> 12.50. our Saviour ſaith, <hi>I have a Baptiſm to be baptized withall, and how am I ſtrained till it be accompliſhed?</hi> Now this can be no other than that Death and bitter Agony he was to undergo for our ſins, that he might bring us to Glory: And by his prediction to his Diſciples in <hi>Mark</hi> 10.39. he foretold their deaths alſo for his ſake: Now as a Perſon that is baptized in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is overwhelmed therewith, even ſo that bitter Agony our Lord endured in the Garden, and upon the Croſs, when his Soul was exceeding ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, even unto death, before wicked men had ſo much as laid their hands upon him, it pleaſed the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34587:43"/>Lord ſo to bruiſe him, and put him to grief, that his ſweat was as it were drops, or clotters of blood falling down to the ground. And when he was upon the Croſs, how did he cry out by reaſon of that ſorrow that overwhelm'd his Soul, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me!</hi> And what great torture ſome of the bleſſed Martyrs have endured is not unknown. This therefore I take to be meaning of thoſe words.</p>
               <p>I will cloſe this in the words of a Learned Proteſtant Writer, <hi>J. G.</hi> I ſhall (ſaith he) ſay no more of this Baptiſm, but only leave this Note, That every ſuffering is not the Baptiſm of ſuffering, but only great and deep ſufferings unto blood and death. Hence the Ancients call it the Baptiſm of Blood, in oppoſition to a leſſer degree or meaſure of ſuffering, being dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and plunged into afflictions: So <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s Dictionary. And ſtill this carries the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Word with it.</p>
               <p>Some conceive this phraſe to be borrowed from ſuch places in the Old Teſtament as theſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.7. <hi>Deep calleth unto deep at the noiſe of thy water ſpouts, all thy waves and thy billows are gone over me:</hi> Pſal. 69.1, 2. <hi>Save me, O God, for the waters are come in unto my Soul! I ſink in deep mire, where there is no ſtanding, I am come into deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where the floods overflow me:</hi> Pſal. 88.7. <hi>Thy wrath lyeth hard upon me, and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy waves, Selah:</hi> Ezekiel 26.19. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord God, when I ſhall make thee a deſolate City, like the Cities that are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited; when I ſhall bring up the deep upon thee, and great waters ſhall cover thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place Mr. <hi>H.</hi> proceeds to ſpeak
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34587:43"/>of the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt, and of Fire, for which he cites <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I perceive Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is as much miſtaken in the true Notion about this Baptiſm as he is in the other two; and indeed 'tis common for one Error to follow another at the heels. What need therefore have Chriſtians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and more eſpecially thoſe that are Miniſters, who are Guides to others, to be very cautious of admitting any thing for truth, but what they have good Authority for from the Word of God. The Lord pour out of his Spirit, to give us more light, and to make us all ſincere.</p>
               <p>I find by his citing theſe Texts in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. that it is his Opinon, That Regeneration wrought in the Soul by the Spirit, is the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt and of Fire: For, (ſaith he) the giving of the Spirit is expreſſed by ſprinkling.</p>
               <p>Now for my part, I am quite of another mind; for as I do not believe that any were baptized with that Baptiſm from the beginning of the World to the coming of the Meſſiah, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think that any have been baptized with it, ſince the miraculous Gifts of the Spirit did ceaſe after the Apoſtle's days.</p>
               <p>And to make it appear, that it's more than only the ſanctifying Graces of the Spirit, I might recite the Opinions of divers learned Men, I ſhall content my ſelf with what is already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to my Hand by a Learned Pen, whoſe Words are theſe, That this Phraſe hath a further meaning in it; ſee <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s Dictionary: Alſo the Learned <hi>Cameron</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> on this place,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34587:44"/>
                  <hi>viz. Mat.</hi> 3.11. who both refer, and that rightly, this for the further opening of it, unto <hi>Acts</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>There appeared unto them cloven Tongues, like as of fire, and it ſat upon each of them, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and began to ſpeak with other Tongues, as the Spirit gave them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance:</hi> So that this Baptiſm of Fire hath clearly reference unto, and was fulfilled in this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary appearance of the Spirit like as of fire. That this was the Baptiſm of the Spirit promiſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. and <hi>Luke</hi> 3. appears further by <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>The Apoſtles being aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Chriſt commanded them that they ſhould not depart from Hieruſalem, but wait for the promiſe of the Father, which (ſaith he) ye have heard of me: For John truly baptized with water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the Holy Spirit not many days hence:</hi> Which was accordingly fulfilled, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 11.15, 16. the Caſe of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> as reported by <hi>Peter; As I began to ſpeak, the Holy Spirit fell on them, as on us at the beginning:</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. before-mentioned) <hi>Then remembred I the Word of the Lord, how that he ſaid, John in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed baptized with water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the Holy Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Baptiſm of the Holy Spirit and Fire, is firſt called a pouring out of the Spirit in the Old, as in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. and the Baptiſm thereof in the New Teſtament, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. as borrowing its phraſe from the Baptiſm of Water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. ſtill carrying the ſignification of the word with it; both terms, to wit, a pouring forth of the Spirit and Baptiſm, in oppoſition to a ſprinkling or dropping of the Spirit, in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meaſures thereof.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:34587:44"/>
               <p>Moreover, The account we have of it <hi>Acts</hi> 2.2. proves it, <hi>And ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven as of à ruſhing mighty wind, and it filled all the houſe where they were ſitting: And there appeared unto them cloven tongues, like as of fire, and it ſat upon each of them, and they were all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>From whence I obſerve the reſemblance it had to the Baptiſm of Water: For, 1. They were filled with it. 2. It ſat upon each of them. 3. The Houſe was filled therewith: So that it was not only about them, but it covered or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd them, even as the water doth in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. 4. All that were baptized with this Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm had the Gift of Tongues. 5. It is to be obſerved, that the Spirit was not thus given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: <hi>For they were all amazed at it, and ſaid one to another, what meaneth this?</hi> Ver. 12. and this did agree with that promiſe of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>John</hi> 7.37, &amp;c. <hi>This ſpake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him ſhould receive, for the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence I infer, It could not be the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts of the Spirit, with the ſanctifying Graces thereof, for this the Apoſtle had before his death; but ſuch an eminent pouring forth, which is called the Baptiſm of the Spirit, by which they received the Gift of Tongues and Propheſie; by which they were endued with power from on high, to execute their Maſters Commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. &amp; <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>To go into all the World, and preach the Goſpel to every Creature:</hi> This they did not receive till that wonderful pouring of it out upon the day
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34587:45"/>of Pentecoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. it was a Gift reſerved till that time, to put a Glory upon the Meſſiah, in the preſence of thoſe who had been his Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers.</p>
               <p>By this time I hope Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is ſatisfied of his Ignorance about points of ſuch Importance as theſe are: I wiſh with all my Soul that he were a Man of that meekneſs of Spirit which he ought to be, ſo as to be willing to learn the truth as it is in Jeſus; but I very much doubt it, becauſe he hath took no more notice of what Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> had told him, but to perſiſt in his Errors after he was detected ſo manifeſtly, both by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſtrength of ſolid arguing: And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in the caſe of <hi>John</hi>'s baptizing at <hi>Aenon,</hi> near to <hi>Salem,</hi> becauſe there was much water. And notwithſtanding he was ſo ſharply rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for contradicting the Spirit of God, yet he goes on with a confidence not befitting a ſincere Chriſtian, much leſs one that takes upon him to be a Guide to others. I ſhall not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore trouble the Reader with his fooliſh Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, having given a ſufficient Anſwer to all that he hath ſaid, or can ſay about it, but ſhall now take him to task for his abuſive Language and ſcurrilous Reflections upon thoſe who are better than himſelf. And altho' he ſeems to glory in that which ſhould have been his ſhame, (and will be, if ever God pleaſe to open the Eyes of his Underſtanding, ſo as to bring him to the knowledge of the truth) by putting of it in the front of his Book, yet I have choſen that laſt, as being to me an unpleaſant and ſtrange Work.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34587:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Being an Account of what is contained in his firſt Chapter, <hi>pag. 11.</hi> concerning his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies againſt the <hi>Baptiſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIs firſt Chapter is a piece of ſhameful, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Railery, not fit to be committed to the Preſs; but remembring the Saying of the wiſe Man, <hi>Anſwer a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit,</hi> I have thought fit to give ſome Anſwer, altho' I expect nothing but unſuitable returns from Mr. <hi>H.</hi> for my kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but it may thro' the bleſſing of God be of uſe to others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> (ſaith he) is but of yeſterday, and all the Antiquity it can lay claim to is not two hundred years; the firſt Anabaptiſt in the World being one <hi>Nicholas Stock,</hi> or <hi>Stork,</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> and a blaſphemous Heretick, who about the Year 1521. or 1522. began to diſgorge his malice againſt the baptizing of Infants, and that dipping was the only way of baptizing.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe this ſhould not be true, how finely were the World fitted with ſuch an Author? That it is not true, I thus prove:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there were Perſons in the World of our Perſwaſion more than 1600 Years agoe, I have already proved: <hi>John,</hi> who dipped our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and many others; that this Holy Prophet was a blaſphemous Heretick, will be hard
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34587:46"/>for him to prove. Chriſt himſelf commanded Believers to be baptized, and his Apoſtles pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it in Obedience thereunto: I hope theſe were not alſo blaſphemous Hereticks.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I can prove, and that by an Imperial Edict that was iſſued forth againſt them by that name, That in the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> Anno 413. they were in that called Anabaptiſts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending thereby ſuch who maintained the ſame Opinions with the Baptiſts in this Age, and this is above 1200 years agoe. See the <hi>Bloody Theater,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author gives an account of divers of them, that in every Age have been in the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Baptiſm as we are, and who have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for that cauſe in every Century, from the time of Chriſt until now.</p>
               <p>That you may have a ſmall Taſt of their cruel uſage, I will give you the words of one Edict againſt them in the Reign of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, <hi>Anno</hi> 1535. <q>That all thoſe who had been baptized in their Infancy, if they ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be baptized again upon their profeſſion of Repentance and Faith, that you puniſh them with cruel deaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> I hope this is enough to ſtop this clamour againſt us.</p>
               <p>But if I were minded to give him <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> I might tell him that Presbytery hath no more ancient date than about the time he mentions, for I take <hi>Calvin</hi> to be the firſt Founder of their Sect. He ought therefore to blot out <hi>Stock,</hi> (if there ever was ſuch a Man) and put in <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> that bloody Perſecutor, who burnt <hi>Serve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> alive, meerly for ſome difference in Opinion about matters of Religion; and yet this is the Man you reverence and adore.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:34587:46"/>
               <p>But he hath not done with him yet; for, ſaith he, in the Carkaſs of this unclean Beaſt was bred a multitude of ſtinging Inſects, ſuch as <hi>Muncer, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias, Kniperdoling, John</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Michael Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus, John Hut, David George, Socinus,</hi> &amp;c. I may very fairly deny ſome of theſe Men to be admitted; for (among others) I never yet knew <hi>Socinus</hi> to be reckoned an Anabaptiſt, (as he calls them.)</p>
               <p>Now becauſe <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> is the man that at every turn our Enemies take occaſion to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid us with, I ſhall take this occaſion to give you the true Hiſtory of that Action, as I find it recorded in that famous Hiſtory, written by <hi>Tileman Jan Van Braght,</hi> Printed at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> Anno 1685. Entituled, <hi>The Bloody Theatre,</hi> or <hi>The Martyrs Mirrour of the Baptiſts Perſwaſion,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein is contained an Hiſtorical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription (collected out of divers Authentick Chronicles, Memoirs and Teſtimonies) of thoſe Holy Martyrs of the Baptiſts Perſwaſion, that have ſuffered for the Cauſe of Baptiſm in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, or for the Teſtimony of Chriſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, in every <hi>Century,</hi> from the time of Chriſt until now: As alſo, concerning Holy Baptiſm it ſelf; with an account of thoſe that have been found in the Faith and Practice thereof, from the beginning of the Goſpel unto this Age. So that here is a conſtant Succeſſion of thoſe of our Perſwaſion proved from Authentick Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which no other Proteſtants can produce for themſelves, and the practice of their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, wherein they differ from us. And for Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, themſelves know it is but of yeſterday,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34587:47"/>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> being the firſt Founder of it, who lived but in the laſt Century.</p>
               <p>He reports the matter thus, That thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and wicked practices that were acted at <hi>Munſter,</hi> about the Year 1534. cannot (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to truth) be charged upon the Baptiſts, becauſe they themſelves were innocent, and thro' fear did fly from thoſe ravenous birds of Prey, leaving their Goods behind them, and hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Rocks and Hollow Trees, and were neceſſitated to keep themſelves conceal'd in Holes and private Places during that time: But it muſt be charged upon the Score of ſome <hi>Lutheran</hi> Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth therefore of the matter, as we find it in the Writings of divers credible Authors, ſtands thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1532. One <hi>Bernard Rotman,</hi> a Lutheran Preacher at <hi>Munſter,</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Maurice,</hi> began to preach againſt the Popiſh Doctrines; which the Papiſts being informed of, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him for a Summ of Money to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</p>
               <p>But having repented himſelf thereof, after ſome Months he returned again, and having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Notice before-hand to divers principal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the City of <hi>Munſter,</hi> he had a Pulpit erected for him in the Portal of the Church, and fought alſo to have the Church opened for the greater promoting of his Doctrine; and withal told them, if it were not granted, he would procure it to be done by force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> had no hand at all in any of theſe Diſturbances, neither as the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner nor Promoter thereof; for as yet he had not been at <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:34587:47"/>
               <p>But upon the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> 1533. (which was the year following) <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> came thither, a ſtrange, ſelfiſh and opinionative Man; who altho' he might ſtand up for Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, this we are ſure of, he differ'd in almoſt all other points with thoſe of the Baptiſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion: And after ſeveral Diſputations he tells us, that among other things <hi>Bernard Rotman</hi> taught <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> this Opinion, That it is lawful for Men not only to defend, but alſo to propagate their Religion by Force and Arms. In the end, the fore-named Perſons with other Lutherans, (ſome of which agreed with <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> in the point of Baptiſm) plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together to make a full Reformation in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by force, and to make their beginning in <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when he hath told us of their oppoſition they made againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and the Papiſts with him, and how they were ſubdu'd by the <hi>Munſterians,</hi> he concludes thus;</p>
               <p>This is indeed that Tragedy which was acted at <hi>Munſter,</hi> which was not contrived and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by thoſe called Anabaptiſts; but the firſt riſe of it muſt be charged upon the Lutherans, and in particular <hi>Bernard Rotman</hi> and his Allies.</p>
               <p>But had the Lutherans ſucceeded in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned Reformation, they would not have been aſhamed thereof, but would have much gloried in the Action, and not have given the Honour of it to the Anabaptiſts; whereupon was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made this following Verſe in <hi>Dutch,</hi> which I have rendred into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:34587:48"/>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If that a Reformation had</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Succeeded by this Fact,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No Anabaptiſt ſhould have had</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Honour of this Act:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But</hi> Luther, <hi>or ſome other Man,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom</hi> Rotman <hi>had ador'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Muſt then have been advanc'd on high,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And crowned as a Lord.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>The like Account may be ſeen in a Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>The profundity of Innocence;</hi> Printed at <hi>Haerlem,</hi> Anno 1631. Alſo in the annexed Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Martyrs, before the Introduction, with the divers Atteſtations of <hi>Bernard Rotman, Godfrey Stralenſis, Rullius,</hi> and others, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of Lutheraniſm at <hi>Munſter;</hi> which being found written under their own hands, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after this Action, were printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could ſay more about it, but this may ſuffice, to convince Mr. <hi>H.</hi> how ſhamefully he hath abuſed us in this matter; and therefore I may ſpare my pains to return anſwers to all his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar abuſive Reflections.</p>
               <p>Having done with the Story of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> I come now to conſider what he ſaith of the reſt of them, whoſe Names he hath affixt; They (ſaith he) fancying themſelves inſpired from above, moſt confidently uttered their He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical blaſphemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; which were,
<list>
                     <item>1. That no Infant ought to be baptized.</item>
                     <item>2. None were rightly baptized but ſuch as were dipped.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two plain and undeniable Truths this
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34587:48"/>Man hath the confidence to call Heretical Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: You may gueſs by this, what a lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he allows himſelf in the exerciſe of <hi>Billingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> Rhetorick.</p>
               <p>Pray Sir conſider; Suppoſe theſe two were Errors, yet they could not be Hereſies, nor Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: For if they are ſo, you have declared your ſelf for Communion with Hereticks and Blaſphemers: For in <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>page</hi> 50. ſpeaking of the particular Baptiſts, you ſay, you can bear with them, (in theſe two points) and give them the right hand of Fellowſhip, as Brethren, if they have no other Errors: Let them but be like-minded to me, and the Peace and Quiet of the Church will never be interrupted by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us. Now the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>Him that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject: For he that is ſuch, is ſubverted, and ſinneth, being condemned in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And of Hymeneus and Alexander,</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.20. But if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> be contrary to himſelf, it's no wonder to find him ſo to the bleſſed Apoſtle.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſaith, That Magiſtrates were not to be ſuffered in the Church; No Chriſtian ought be a Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know not what he means by Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the Church, nor himſelf neither; there is no ſuch thing in <hi>Rerum Natura:</hi> But ſuppoſe ſome Chriſtians have ſcrupled the lawfulneſs thereof, and were willing to deny themſelves therein, is this Hereſie and Blaſphemy?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4ly.</hi> That it was Unlawful to take an Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe it were ſo, that ſome of them
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34587:49"/>did ſcruple it, he doth not ſhew his Loyalty to King <hi>Willam,</hi> by charging it as a blaſphemous Hereſie; for by Act of Parliament it's made law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> to give their Teſtimony without an Oath.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That there ought to be no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Clergy and Laity; that every one that hath Gifts might preach, and adminiſter the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I fancy this Gentleman doth not know whence the word <hi>Clergy</hi> is derived; if he doth, he hath ſhewed his profound ignorance in this Aſſertion: I ſhall therefore inform him in what ſence it's uſed in the New Teſtament, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is rendred by our Tranſlators He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage; and that we may underſtand the true intent and meaning of the Apoſtle therein, read but the 1, 2, and 3. <hi>verſes</hi> together, and you will find that he is ſpeaking to the Elders or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and that he is ſpeaking of the Flock of God, over which he had made them Overſeers; and that he applies the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Clergy, or Heritage, to the People diſtinct from their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond, That every one that hath Gifts may preach: I anſwer, If he means every one that hath received Gifts from God, to fit him for that work, it's certainly true: And if he or any other take upon them to preach without a Gift from God to qualifie them for that work, they certainly run before they are ſent: For all Humane Authority, without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ability, can never qualifie any for that Undertaking. But is this a blaſphemous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie?</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34587:49"/>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6ly.</hi> That there is no Original Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there be any ſin in the World, it muſt have a beginning: If there be a ſecond, there muſt be a firſt. Either he knows not what he talks of, or elſe I affirm there were no ſuch Men in the World, neither of our perſwaſion or any other.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That Man hath Free-Will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Poſition was never denyed by any Mortal, either Heathen, Jew or Chriſtian, that I know of: All Men agree, that Wicked Mens Wills are free to do evil, and the Wills of thoſe who are regenerated and ſanctified by the Holy Spirit, are free to do good: <hi>To will is preſent with me,</hi> Rom. 7.18.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8ly.</hi> That the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are not three diſtinct Perſons, and in Nature and Eſſence one God: They made every Saint equal with Chriſt: That Chriſt is not God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I believe this to be a falſe Accuſation, and ſhall return it to the Father of Lyes, from whence it came.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9ly.</hi> They denyed that the Souls of the Godly or Wicked went to Heaven or Hell 'till the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there were any ſuch, it ſhewed them to be Men of Weak Judgment, but not to be blaſphemous Hereticks.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10ly.</hi> That the viſible Church conſiſts of thoſe which are perfect, and of them only.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He would have done well to have proved his Aſſertion; and 'till he doth, I muſt return it upon him as a falſe accuſation, pick'd up from ſome of our Lying Adverſaries.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:34587:50"/>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11ly.</hi> That Univerſities, Schools, and Humane Arts, ought not to be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As he hath worded it, I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it to be true: For how they would have got a Livelyhood without being Tradeſmen, and exerciſed in Humane Arts, I know not. And the former I believe to be as true as the latter, for 'tis the abuſe of things, and not the uſe of them, that are to be complained of.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12ly.</hi> The Anabaptiſts, called <hi>Liberi Fratres,</hi> denyed the Scriptures to be the Word of God, and Singing of Pſalms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is certainly a falſe accuſation; for our Brethren have in all Ages made that the ground of their Separation from the falſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that they did not walk according to the Will of God, preſcribed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but ſet up the Inventions of Men in the room thereof. As for that of Singing of Pſalms, they never denyed the practice of it, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God, but they did, and ſtill do deny the uſe of ſinging in Rhime, by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinted limited form, of all the people together, Saints and Sinners, becauſe they have no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for it from the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13ly.</hi> That a Man was not tyed to one Wife, therefore their Fairy King, <hi>John Becold,</hi> had fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let this go as a falſe Accuſation from whence it came; for by <hi>John Becold,</hi> he ſaith in the next page, was meant <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and I am as well aſſured as I can be of a thing of this nature, that it's utterly falſe.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14ly.</hi> That none were to be owned as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or Churches of Chriſt, but themſelves only,</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34587:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by Chriſtians he means nominally ſo, they always allowed all to be ſuch that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Chriſtian Name; but if he means real Chriſtians, they never owned any to be ſuch, but what were ſo truly in the Judgment of Charity: And if by Churches he means, true conſtituted Churches, according to Chriſt's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, then they could not believe any to be ſo beſides themſelves, unleſs they had at the ſame time believed themſelves not to be ſo. But notwithſtanding this, they have and do believe, that many perſons are in the Love and Favour of God, and in a State of Salvation, whilſt they hold the Head Chriſt Jeſus, altho' they differ from them in ſome of the external parts of Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That we muſt become as little Children, in Childiſh Actions; therefore they would play with Rattles, ride on Hobby-horſes, and wallow in their own dung, in imitation of Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Can any ſerious Chriſtian believe ſuch an ill told Story as this? or can they think that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> believes himſelf? Certainly his Hearers muſt bluſh at ſuch Folly as this in their Teacher, to utter ſuch Nonſenſical, unheard of Untruths, unleſs they have wholly given up their Reaſon to the conduct of a blind Guide, and pin their Faith (as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> do) upon their Prieſts Sleeve. I hope the people of <hi>Potters Pury</hi> have more wit, than to give credit to ſuch fooliſh and improbable ſtories as theſe are. But to deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you, I believe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> had got a Rattle in his Head, which hath made him ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome among his Neighbours: And perhaps his playing with Rattles when he was young, hath hindred him from a ſerious Application of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34587:51"/>to any thing but ratling and confuſed Noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ever ſince, and from thence concludes others to be like himſelf.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>2dly.</hi> (ſaith he) They rid on Hobby-Horſes: I know not but he might ride on a Hobby-Horſe from his late Parochial Church to <hi>Potters-Pury,</hi> which might occaſion him to think of a Hobby-Horſe ever ſince. But to be ſerious, I rather take him by a figure in Rhetorick, to be a Hobby-Horſe himſelf, than a ſolid grave Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, (not to ſay a Miniſter) that he ſhould talk at this Hobby-Horſe rate; if I may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to uſe ſuch a figure in ſpeaking, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Example.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>3dly.</hi> (he ſaith.) They did wallow in their own Dung, in imitation of Children: It would tempt a Man to think, that either his Mother or Nurſe were but ordinary Houſe-wives, to ſuffer him ſo to wallow in his own Excrements, that all the Water in their Countrey could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver waſh it off; but that it ſhould penetrate thro' the pores of his Skin, and get ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the ſecret receſſes of his Heart and interior parts, and remain there till he wrote theſe two Treatiſes againſt the Baptiſts, and then vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it forth againſt them in ſuch a violent and unpreſidented manner, as to infect all the people that come near him with the ſtence thereof; and then to charge his innocent Neighbours for having ſtinking breaths, when it's only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the ambient air, occaſioned by the breaking of his own Gall, and vomiting it forth againſt the Baptiſts. And for his Story, I muſt do by that as by the reſt of his Lyes and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt us, return them upon himſelf and his Lying Authors.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:34587:51"/>
               <p n="16">16. That <hi>Luther,</hi> and the Proteſtant Miniſters, were worſe than the Pope, Carnal Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with much more of the like kind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He would have done well to have told us where theſe People lived, in what Book and page we might have found it: But to take all he ſaith upon his own <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> is more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit than I will give to any Prieſt upon Earth, without other Evidence. I will ſooner believe a Gentleman that writes about Divinity, than a Parſon; becauſe our Law hath provided, that no Man ſhall be a Witneſs in a cauſe wherein himſelf hath either profit or loſs; and I doubt Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s Sallary tempts him to prevaricate at this egregious rate, either to gain or keep Proſelites. But I need not wonder at this, for we read of ſuch in the Scripture, of whom it's ſaid, <hi>Their God is their Belly, their Glory is in their ſhame, they mind earthly things:</hi> And we find by woful Experience, too much of this verified in ſome of the Prieſts of our day.</p>
               <p>But, (ſaith he) I would not have all theſe things charged upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anabaptiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have no cauſe to thank him for that, becauſe he knows that all their Neighbours among whom they live could eaſily confute him. But if he could do it, it's evident he would not ſpare us, after he hath poured out all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that Earth and Hell could furniſh him with againſt us.</p>
               <p>He further tells us, That in the Space of a few years <hi>Germany</hi> was filled with Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am ſure, if they were ſuch an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Wicked People as he pretends then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34587:52"/>to be, they muſt be under the greateſt Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ever Mortals were, for ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes to follow them as he ſpeaks of: For none but ſuch who had firſt abandoned Scripture and Reaſon, with all the Notions that ſerious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ever had about Religion, could ever fall in with ſuch Notorious and Nonſenſical Practices as he talks of.</p>
               <p>To conclude, (ſaith he) What ſhall we ſay to the Anabaptiſts, that dip and re-baptize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? The firſt Anabaptiſt in <hi>Germany</hi> did ſo, and one <hi>Smith</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, that was a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi>'s Congregation did ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had none to do it for them, there being no Anabaptiſts before them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If his Story about Fact be no truer than his reaſon he gives for it, I am ſure 'tis all falſe, and a meer ſlander: But let us conſider the matter diſtinctly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Who baptized <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who was the firſt Baptizer? Did he baptize himſelf? or was he baptized by another? If he was not baptized at all, then an unbaptized Perſon, did in the beginning of this Ordinance baptize multitudes: If he was baptized, it muſt be by himſelf, or ſome unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Perſon; ſo that if ſuch a thing were done, it were not ſuch a grievous Crime as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, If this be true, that there were none in <hi>England</hi> before <hi>Smith,</hi> what was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> ſhould tells us a ſtory ſo contradictory to this, in <hi>page</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> of his <hi>2d.</hi> part, That two Ships laden with Anabaptiſts eſcaped to <hi>England,</hi> where they have neſted ever ſince, endeavouring to propagate Anabaptiſm.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:34587:52"/>
               <p>Now obſerve, This ſtory is told by him as acted preſently upon the buſineſs of <hi>Munſter,</hi> &amp;c. Now if this Man was in <hi>Holland</hi> in Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi>'s time, I am ſure there was many Churches of Baptiſts in that Countrey, and that they had been before they were a ſtate, as the Lords of <hi>Holland</hi> have teſtified in their Approbation of that famous Book, Entituled, <hi>The Bloody Theater,</hi> and in their Lordſhips Letter therein to the Lords of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> &amp;c. And if <hi>Smith</hi> lived in <hi>England,</hi> then certainly ſome one of thoſe two Ship Loads of Anabaptiſts he talks of, or their Succeſſors, were in being; ſo that he needed not to have baptized himſelf for want of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator: I muſt therefore return him this for anſwer, that ſuch an improbable ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting Story is not to be credited.</p>
               <p>As to what he ſaith againſt the Honourable Collonel <hi>Danvers,</hi> I do affirm that neither Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> whoſe hand was not only againſt every Man that ſtood in his way, (altho' never ſo worthy) of whom the Learned and Judicious Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> (whoſe Books Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was not worthy to carry after him) who had been Vice-Chancellor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and lived and dyed a Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Honeſt <hi>Independant,</hi> yet this moſt Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and Civil Gentleman could not eſcape the virulency of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Pen, as you may ſee in <hi>Vindiciae Anti-Baxterianae,</hi> lately publiſhed, with divers others whom he hath alſo abuſed: But, (as hath long been obſerved of that Man) there was in his writings no conſiſtence, but <hi>Baxter</hi> wrote againſt <hi>Richard,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> againſt <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and therefore what he hath ſaid againſt Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Danvers,</hi> is not to be valued of a Ruſh;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34587:53"/>for thoſe Teſtimonies he hath given, will ſtand good to the ſhame and reproach of all the <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> in the World. But I will not trouble my ſelf to anſwer a Man that will never be anſwered, but refer him to the Collonel's own anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> at the end of his Hiſtory of Chriſtianity, where he hath fully confuted all Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s ridiculous and caufeleſs Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Being an Anſwer to thoſe Errors which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſaith we are guilty of.</head>
               <p>THere are ſix things which Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> charges upon us, as condemned Hereſies and Errors; which are as follows;
<list>
                     <item>1. The Anabaptiſts are very Erroneous in the Doctrine of Original Sin.</item>
                     <item>2. That Chriſt dyed alike for all Men, and that all Perſons in the World are by the death of Chriſt put into a capacity of Salvation.</item>
                     <item>3. That God affords all Men univerſal and ſufficient Grace, and conſequently a power of Free-Will, to be ſaved if they will.</item>
                     <item>4. That a Perſon truly juſtified and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo a Branch in Chriſt, united to him, may yet fall away and be eternally damned.</item>
                     <item>5. They diſown all Miniſters, Chriſtians, and Churches of Chriſt, to be any Miniſters, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or Chriſtians at all, but only ſuch as are gathered in their way, that is, by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</item>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:34587:53"/>
                     <item>6. Their employing many weak, ignorant Men, to preach, that have Pride and Confidence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to think themſelves fit to teach others, who have yet more need to be taught themſelves the very firſt Principles of Religion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As to his firſt Charge, That we are very Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous in the Doctrine of Original Sin, and that we plainly deny Original Sin; and for evidence quotes the Confeſſion of Faith publiſhed almoſt forty years ago, and reprinted <hi>Anno</hi> 1691. and refers us to <hi>Articles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> and <hi>10th.</hi> I ſhall ſet down the whole Articles, that the Reader may ſee we do own Original Sin, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Clamour to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Article 2d.</hi> That God in the beginning made Man upright, and put him into a ſtate and condition of Glory, without the leaſt mixture of miſery, from which he by tranſgreſſion fell, and ſo came into a miſerable and mortal Eſtate, ſubject unto the firſt Death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. and 3.17, 18, 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Article 10th.</hi> That all Children dying in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, having not actually tranſgreſſed againſt the Law of God in their Perſons, are only ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the firſt death, which comes upon them by the ſin of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and not that any one of them (dying in that eſtate) ſhall ſuffer for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin eternal puniſhment in Hell, (which is the ſecond death) for to ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs the Kingdom of Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. Not daring to conclude with that uncharitable Opinion of others, who tho' they plead much for the bringing of Children into the Viſible Church here on Earth by Baptiſm, yet nevertheleſs by their Doctrine, that Chriſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34587:54"/>dyed but for ſome, ſhut a great part of them out of the Kingdom of Heaven for ever.</p>
               <p>The great Quarrel he hath againſt this, is, becauſe we will not allow their ſcriptureleſs and uncharitable Notion, that Infants of a ſpan long are yelling in Hell, and that God made poor little innocent Babes on purpoſe to damn them; as ſome of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> affirm.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon why we reject this Doctrine, is, becauſe it's no where ſo written in the Holy Scriptures: But we own Original Sin, as truly and fully as any <hi>Calviniſt</hi> whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But we muſt be falſly accuſed, only becauſe we reject his blind and ignorant Notion about it, and will not ſend little ſucking Babes to Hell by whole-ſale, as he doth. The good Women that are his Hearers, can't chooſe but be mightily comforted with this News, (from the Pulpit and Preſs) and think it worth all the Money they or their Husbands give him for preaching, to hear him tell them, Beloved, If your Children dye in their Infancy, unleſs they are elected, I can aſſure you they ſhall go to Hell, and be puniſhed there to all Eternity, for that they could never help: God hath ſo ordered it by his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Decree, unknown to me and all the World. Do you think God ever ſent him of this Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage? Eſpecially when he tells you in his Book, he knows not who belongs to the Election of Grace.</p>
               <p>Now Mr. <hi>H.</hi> might have been truly inform'd of this matter, if he had minded what Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> told him in <hi>page</hi> 35. of his Book, in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Mence</hi> and him, That one of the firſt Arguments of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for Infant-Baptiſm,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34587:54"/>is, which (I ſuppoſe) is Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s alſo, (if he knows what he is talking of) that it waſhes away Original Sin: We can, ſaith Mr. <hi>H. Collins,</hi> tell you of a better way of waſhing away Original Sin, namely, by the imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to Infants dying in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy. Add to this what Mr. <hi>Claridge</hi> ſaith, in his Epiſtle to the ſame Book; And here I would inform all the Readers of Mr. <hi>Mence</hi>'s Book, that whereas he charges Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Infant-damning Doctrine, it is altogether a miſtake; for Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> is rather inclined to think, That all dying Infants are ſaved by the imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, and much more that hath been ſaid before upon this Subject, he ſtill goes on in his confident way of writing, and ſaith, he will prove, That all by Birth or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are by the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> liable to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of Hell by plain Scripture.</p>
               <p>He is a bold man at aſſerting, but he common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fails in his Proof. Let us now examine thoſe Scriptures he alledges for probation of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident aſſertion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> Now this was the threatning, but in <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. we have the Sentence denounced againſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by God himſelf, which ſerves to explain the former threatning to be only the firſt Death, with its Concomitants; <hi>Curſed is the ground for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the days of thy Life: Thorns alſo and Thiſtles ſhall it bring forth to thee, and thou ſhalt eat the Herb of the field: In the ſweat of thy Face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground, for out of it waſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34587:55"/>thou taken; for duſt thou art, and unto duſt ſhalt thou return:</hi> Here you ſee, that what is called Death in the threatning, is called returning to the Ground, and unto Duſt, in the Sentence, but not one word of puniſhment in Hell ſo much as intimated therein. As for the other Texts he mentions, they are no proofs of what he brings them for, and therefore I ſhall paſs them, and proceed to his three Arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 1. If Children need Regeneration and a Second Birth, before they can go to Heaven, then they are liable to Eternal as well as Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Death: But Children do need Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> John 3.3, 5. <hi>Except a man be born again,</hi> &amp;c. Now it's plain <hi>Nicodemus</hi> underſtood our Saviour in this ſence, by his anſwer; <hi>viz.</hi> not of Children newly born, but of adult Perſons; for he ſaith, <hi>How can a man be born when he is old?</hi> But to anſwer directly to his Argument, I deny his <hi>Minor,</hi> and ſay, they do not need Regeneration and a ſecond Birth, in the Sence there intended, before they can go to Heaven; and if they did, they were in a bad Caſe indeed, for they are not capable either of Repentance or Faith, both which are comprehended in thoſe words, <hi>Except a Man be born again.</hi> Thus you ſee, when he ſhould have brought a Text to have proved Infants muſt be born again, this only proves that a Perſon of grown years, a Man, muſt be born again.</p>
               <p>Let him not imagine that I feign an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of my own, for Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> a great Pedo-baptiſt, ſaith, They muſt be regenerate, they muſt have Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34587:55"/>have Faith and Repentance; all ſaved Infants are regenerated, therefore they have Faith and Repentance; they muſt be born of Water and of the Spirit, according to <hi>John</hi> 3.6. elſe there is no Heaven for them.</p>
               <p>Now that God does cleanſe dying Infants from all Impurity, and fits them for Heaven, I readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant: But this Regeneration they talk of from this Text, and apply to Infants, I poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively deny: And certain I am, if he had read thoſe Quotations upon that Argument given by Mr. <hi>Claridge,</hi> he might have been ſenſible of this his Error before he had wrote this his <hi>2d.</hi> part. Whether Infants have Faith or no, is a Queſtion (ſaith Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>) to be diſputed by Perſons that care not how much they ſay, and how little they prove; (which is the very caſe of Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>) when he hath denyed them to have either perſonal and actual, or habitual Faith; he concludes thus, This ſtrange Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is abſolutely without Art, without Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon or Authority; but the men are to be excuſed, unleſs there were a better. And again, we deſire (ſaith he) no more advantage in the World, (againſt ſuch men) than that they are conſtrained to anſwer without Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, againſt Reaſon, Common-ſence, and all the Experience in the World: Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Liberty of Prophecy,</hi> page 240, 242.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H's 2d. Argum.</hi> is this, If Infants are not liable to the damnation of Hell for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, then they may be ſaved without Chriſt, by vertue of the Covenant of Works: But, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is a ſtrange Aſſertion: What, can Infants be ſaved by Works, that are wholly uncapable to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34587:56"/>Perform any? this is meer trifling. But I ſhall deny the Conſequence of his <hi>Major:</hi> For, If Infants by virtue of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin muſt return to the duſt, and cannot raiſe themſelves to life again, but muſt have remained in that ſtate for ever, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Chriſt had come in the fleſh, dyed and roſe again, and by vertue of his Reſurrection raiſed them again by his mighty Power, then it had been impoſſible for them to have been ſaved: So that it's a <hi>Non-ſequitor;</hi> for altho' they are not condemned to eternal Puniſhment in Hell, yet there is a neceſſity for them to be ſaved by Chriſt, if ever they get to Heaven. But beſides this, they ſtand in need of Chriſt to purifie their Natures from Original Corruption, as I have ſhewed above.</p>
               <p>His <hi>3d. Argu.</hi> is this, Such as are by Nature Children of Wrath, are liable to the Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Hell; but all are ſo, therefore Infants; <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this he hath dealt very unfairly, and neither like a Gentleman, nor a Scholar, for his Argument is not in due form.</p>
               <p>For, 1. Infants are no where expreſſed but in the Concluſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He hath put the word <hi>all</hi> into the <hi>Minor,</hi> tho' he hath not told us what <hi>all</hi> he means: And in the <hi>major</hi> it's only ſuch as are, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe he would have framed a Categori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Syilogiſm, if he had known how, and then it ſhould have run thus,</p>
               <p>All ſuch as are by Nature Children of Wrath, are liable to the Condemnation of Hell.</p>
               <p>All Infants are by Nature Children of Wrath, <hi>Ergo,</hi> All Infants are liable to the Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34587:56"/>of Hell; which is the thing I ſuppoſe he meant: And then I deny his <hi>minor</hi> Propoſition, and let him prove it if he can.</p>
               <p>As for his Text he brings for probation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I deny that Infants are either expreſſed or intended therein: For the deſign of the Apoſtle in that place, is to ſet before them what a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition they had been in before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, by their own perſonal tranſgreſſions, <hi>viz. Dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, who in times paſt walked according to the courſe of this world, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the prince of the power of the Air, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that now worketh in the Children of Diſobedience: Among whom alſo we all had our Converſation in times paſt, in the luſts of our fleſh, fulfiling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by nature,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> by the corrupt and fleſhly Inclinations that were within us) <hi>Children of wrath even as others:</hi> Meaning thereby other <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were ſtill in an unregenerate Eſtate, wallowing in their Iniquities.</p>
               <p>So that as Infants are not here expreſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they be intended, as being free from all perſonal tranſgreſſions, and not capable to tranſact thoſe Evils there ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now offer ſome Reaſons, why I do not believe that any Infants dying in their Infancy ſhall be tormented for ever in Hell-fire.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe there is no ſuch thing expreſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Threatning or Sentence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. as I have already ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe God himſelf hath diſclaimed ſuch an Opinion as Erroneous, and declared the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.2, 3, 4, 20.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hear what the firſt Founder of your Sect,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34587:57"/>from whence you have your denomination, <hi>viz. John Calvin</hi> ſaith upon this Subject, ſpeaking of all others beſides the Elect; ſo many Nations of Men, together with their Infants, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved without remedy in eternal puniſhment, by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> for no imaginable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that ſo it ſeemed good in the ſight of God; <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Inſtit.</hi> l. 3. cap. 23. Sect. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hear what God ſaith in the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned place, <hi>The ſoul that ſinneth ſhall dye; the Son ſhall not bear the iniquity of the Father;</hi> this muſt intend eternal puniſhment, for as to temporal puniſhment Children do often ſuffer for their Fathers faults, and we all ſuffer for the fault of <hi>Adam,</hi> both temporal Miſeries and Death it ſelf. But whereas theſe People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſuch a blind Notion as that of Mr. <hi>H. That the Fathers had eaten ſowre grapes, and the Childrens Teeth were ſet on edge;</hi> God tells them, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, ye ſhall not have occaſion any more to uſe this Proverb in Iſrael, for the Son ſhall not bear the Fathers iniquity; the ſoul that ſinneth, it ſhall dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Lord (who beſt knew) hath declared, that Infants belong to the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I will add to theſe the Opinion of the Learned <hi>Poole,</hi> that he would rather believe that all Infants dying in their Infancy were elected, than conclude that any of them were damned; and his reaſon was, becauſe as no man knew the contrary, ſo they ought not to affirm what they did not know. But I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Poole</hi> muſt be a blaſphemous Heretick in Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Opinion, as well as the poor Anabaptiſts: But it's our
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34587:57"/>mercy he is not to be our Judge in the Great Day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>2d.</hi> Hereſie, or Error, this man of might charges us with, is,</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Chriſt dyed alike for all men, and that all Perſons in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This doth neceſſarily divide it ſelf into two General Parts:
<list>
                     <item>1. That Chriſt dyed alike for all men.</item>
                     <item>2. That all Perſons in the World are by the Death of Chriſt put into a Capacity of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall anſwer to both of them diſtinctly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Chriſt dyed for all men: I do (with the Pen-men of the Holy Scripture) affirm, and that it's a great and fundamental Truth, this appears from theſe following poſitive aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He gave himſelf a ranſom for all:</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14, 15. <hi>He dyed for all:</hi> Heb. 2.9. <hi>He taſted death for every man:</hi> 1 Tim. 4.10. <hi>Who is the Saviour of all men:</hi> 1 John 2.2. <hi>He is a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world:</hi> So that to deny this, is to deny the very expreſs words of Scripture. And therefore Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> being aware of this, hath owned it to be true in ſome ſence; but not content with this, he puts in the word (alike,) thinking to puzzle us with that, and lays down ſome Arguments to prove he did not dye for all (alike,) and thinks we are obliged to prove it.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, It's an Unſcriptural term, a man of Straw of his own ſetting up; for in all our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith that I remember to have been publiſhed, there is not the word (alike) to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34587:58"/>found in any of them. As for that laſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to, printed 1691. the words are theſe, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> 3. That Chriſt freely gave himſelf a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for all, taſting death for every man, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſins; and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole World. So that the word (alike) is not by them inſerted: And it being a term of Art of his own Coyning, I return it to the mint from whence it came.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion therefore betwixt us is this, not whether Chriſt dyed for all men, for that he owns, but, whether all perſons in the World are by the death of Chriſt put into a capacity of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? This he denyes, and we affirm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 4. Of the aforeſaid Confeſſion of the Baptiſts, they have theſe expreſs words, No man ſhall eternally ſuffer in Hell, (that is, the ſecond death) for want of Chriſt that dyed for them, but as the Scripture ſaith, for denying the Lord that bought them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. or becauſe they believe not in the Name of the only begotten Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. Unbelief therefore being the cauſe why the juſt and righteous God will condemn the Children of Men, it follows againſt all contradiction, that all men at one time or other are put into ſuch a capacity, as that (through the Grace of God) they may be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scriptures of Truth do affirm this, in as plain words as a matter of this kind can well be expreſt, <hi>John</hi> 3.14, 15, 16, 17. here is ſet down the deſign of God in the Gift of Chriſt for the World: 1. Negatively, that they ſhould not periſh, that God ſent not his Son to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the World. 2. Affirmatively; That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34587:58"/>believeth in him, ſhould have eternal life, and everlaſting life, and that the World through him might be ſaved: And in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God our Saviour, he ſaith, who will have all men to be ſaved; and in <hi>ver.</hi> 6. how God hath demonſtrated this good will of his to all men, by aſſerting that Chriſt gave himſelf a ranſom for all; and in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.10. who is the Saviour of all men. Now this muſt be underſtood of his putting men into a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of Salvation by the death of his Son, as having afforded all men thereby a Sufficiency of means to obtain it, otherwiſe it is not true; for it's manifeſt, that eventially all men are not ſaved, which (by the way) proves that God did not abſolutely, but conditionally will their Salvation, by putting them into a capacity to obtain it through Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I know that all this ſtir about, and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Death of Chriſt being ſufficient for all and every man, is founded upon that falſe Notion which ſome have of late licked up from the Stoicks Doctrine of Fate, That God hath ſo determined the Actions of all men, by an abſolute Decree, that there can nothing come to paſs in the world without it; and that he hath made the greateſt number of Men on purpoſe to damn them; and that their ſins foreſeen were not the cauſe of his Decree, but his Decree the cauſe both of their Sin and Puniſhment: And that God did not intend any of theſe ſhould enjoy any ſaving benefit by the death of his Son; and from thence it is they have formed this fancy in their own Imaginations, <hi>Chriſtum mortuum pro ſolis electis,</hi> that Chriſt dyed only for the Elect.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:34587:59"/>
               <p>Now this Opinion of theirs hath been Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themized above 1200 years ago, as I find it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by a very Learned Author, in theſe words-<hi>Synodus Arelatenſis habita circa annum</hi> 490. <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema illi qui dixerit quod Christus non pro omnibus mortuus ſit, nec omnes homines ſalvos eſſe velit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> hath qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf by Law for a Presbyterian Teacher, and then he hath ſubſcribed to the 39 Articles of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> The <hi>31ſt.</hi> Article there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, The offering of Chriſt once made is a perfect Redemption, Propitiation and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for all the ſins of the whole World, both ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and actual.</p>
               <p>And agreeable to this, Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſaith, We may ſafely conclude, that the Lamb of God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering himſelf a Sacrifice for the ſins of the whole World, intended by giving ſufficient ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God's Juſtice, to make the Nature of man which he aſſumed a ſit Object for mercy, and to prepare a Medicine for the ſins of the whole World, which ſhould be denyed to none that intended to take the benefit of it. And he alſo aſſigns the reaſon, why all are not ſaved, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this purchaſe, in theſe Words; But all do not obtain actual remiſſion, becauſe moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders do not take out and plead their pardon as they ought to do. Why doth not Mr. <hi>H.</hi> quarrel with, and rail at the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Doctors and Biſhops, have not they given him as much cauſe as the Baptiſts? But alas! he knows full well, they eſteem ſuch a one as he below their Anger.</p>
               <p>All the Arguments he brings to prove his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, being founded upon that word (alike,)
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34587:59"/>they all vaniſh like ſmoak before the Wind: For ſuppoſe that were granted which he labours ſo much to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt did not (in ſome ſence) dye alike for all: I do not ſee how that would in the leaſt hurt the cauſe we contend for, <hi>i. e.</hi> That he dyed with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to ſave all, if they repent and believe; and that he hath afforded a ſufficiency of means to all: Let them allow this, and I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third Error of the Anabaptiſts, ſaith he, (and why not of ſome of the moſt Learned and Eminent Doctors of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) is this, That God affords all men univerſal and ſufficient Grace, and conſequently a power of Free-will, to be ſaved if they will.</p>
               <p>The former part of this Charge I own, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>4th.</hi> Article of our Confeſſion, in the Words by him cited: All Men are at one time or other put into ſuch a capacity, as that (through the Grace of God) they may be eternally ſaved. And he rails bitterly at us, for ſaying, that if any periſh, it is not for want of the means of Grace, but for the non-improvement of the Grace of God freely offered through Chriſt. And in this Doctrine, ſaith he, <hi>Papiſts, Socinians, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are all agreed. Is it not as true in this Doctrine alſo, that there is but one only true God, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in which <hi>Papiſts, Socinians, Arminians, Baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are all agreed? Doth their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment make it a falſe Doctrine? Surely no.</p>
               <p>As for his two Reaſons, I ſhall ſpeak to them in their order:</p>
               <p n="1">1. For his inſtance of the Pagan Heathen
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34587:60"/>World, he ſaith, many of them have never heard of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore concludes, they have no ſufficient Grace, nor means of Salvation: Now (ſaith he) of theſe we boldly deny this Monſtrous and Erroneous Aſſertion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But as monſtrous as it is in his Eyes, what if I ſorce him to acknowledge his reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from it to be wholly groundleſs, from his own Principle, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſome perſons may be ſaved by Chriſt, without a particular knowledge of him, or an explicite Faith in him; then ſome of theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens may be ſaved by Chriſt, and may have a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of means for their Salvation, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his contrary Aſſertion. That he holds ſuch an Opinion, I prove thus, becauſe he aſſerts, That all Elect Infants dying in Infancy are ſaved: Now this muſt be by Chriſt, altho' they are no more capable to know him, and believe in him, than thoſe Heathens he ſpeaks of. What he ſays about their incapacity, becauſe they have no Preachers to inſtruct them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thoſe ſayings relates to ſuch as have the Goſpel among them, upon whom thoſe Duties are enforced, and do not relate to Heathens that lye under an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Ignorance, no more than they do to little Infants: For, as Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin</hi> ſaith, in his Aggravations of Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Poſitive Laws come to be in force only where they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated. God doth not exact impoſſible things from his Creatures, and then puniſh them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not obey him therein, for it is an act of high Injuſtice; ſhall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</p>
               <p>Let Mr. <hi>H.</hi> take care to enſure his own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and not trouble himſelf with thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34587:60"/>which belong only to God: Who made him (I pray) a Judge of Heathens, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes to ſentence them thus by whole-ſale to the torments of Hell fire? <hi>For the Lord our God is good to all, and his tender mercies are over all his Works: He is the God of the Spirits of all fleſh:</hi> And he hath ſent his Son to dye for them all, which beſpeaks his great Love towards them; from whence we have reaſon to hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, than that he made ſo many thouſand millions of Souls on purpoſe to damn them, as the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ſay. And this leads me to the Second Reaſon, for he triumphs over us in this ſaying, Thus this rotten Pillar of univerſal Grace is overthrown.</p>
               <p>His <hi>2d.</hi> is this, He denyes that God hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded every perſon in the Viſible Church ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Grace for their Converſion. To make it out, he inſiſts upon three things neceſſary, in order to Converſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a Perſon ſit under the Miniſtry of the Word faithfully preached: Multitudes (ſaith he) in the viſible Church do not enjoy a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſtry, ſome none at all; others, only ſuch as are ſent in Judgment, that dawb with untempered Mortar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What viſible Church muſt this be that he ſpeaks of? What, a Church and have no Preacher, and others Churches that have Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſent to them in Judgment only? This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Church of Chriſt, but the Synagogue of Satan: For, Chriſt hath promiſed to be with his Church (by his Spirit) alway, even to the end of the World. But will he charge all this upon God? I know that when ſome Perſons
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34587:61"/>have ſinned away all their Mercies, and the Grace offer'd them, then he doth ſometimes give them up to ſtrong Deluſions, to believe Lyes, as is the caſe of the Papiſts and others; but he charges the fault upon themſelves, becauſe they did not receive the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved, but took pleaſure in Unrighteouſneſs: It would therefore be horrid wickedneſs for any that profeſſes Chriſtianity, to charge God with being the cauſe of this, when he hath declared their Deſtruction is of themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ſaith, They cannot be converted, except their Conſciences be awakened, and ſtirr'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Miniſtry of the Word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Perſons may ſit under the beſt Miniſtry, and yet never be thus convinced. Now that we may know where he hath a Mind to lay the blame, he inſinuates it in ſaying, this Conviction is only from the Holy Spirit, who bloweth where he liſteth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ho' I acknowledge that no Man is converted without the Operation of the Holy Spirit, yet I am far from thinking, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they are not converted, is becauſe the Holy Spirit doth not operate with the Word; but it is becauſe they reſiſt the motions and ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thereof. God's Spirit did ſtrive with the Old World, but they reſiſted it, and periſhed by the Flood: And as <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 51. <hi>Ye do always reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did, ſo do ye:</hi> Now <hi>Stephen</hi> was better skilled in theſe matters than Mr. <hi>H.</hi> for he juſtifies God, and charges it upon them, as being a ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked and obſtinate People, uncircumciſed in Heart and Ears.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>3ly.</hi> ſaith he, There muſt be a divine
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34587:61"/>powerful drawing of the Soul to Chriſt by the Spirit, which he calls an irreſiſtible power; which he alſo ſaith, is not afforded to all that ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel-Miniſtry, and they cannot come to Chriſt without it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the Divine Power is in it ſelf ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable, I grant, but that is not here the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But whether that power be exerted in an irreſiſtable way? which was the thing he ſhould have proved, if he had ſpoken <hi>ad rem,</hi> but that he ſeldom does: And I have already proved, that the Spirit, in its Operations upon the Souls of Men, hath often been reſiſted. However, the Man crys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictory; and ſaith, This Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctrine of Univerſal Grace, is but a lying Invention of their own, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which I will put up among the reſt of his Railery, for it deſerves no better Treatment.</p>
               <p>As for what he ſays, that Free-will is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of our Opinion; I may truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, by a figure in Rhetorick, that he is a profound man for drawing of Conſequences. But to the point in Hand:</p>
               <p>The Words in the <hi>4th.</hi> Article of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which he refers to, are theſe; <q>Unbelief therefore being the cauſe, why the juſt and righteous God will condemn the Children of Men, it follows againſt all contradiction, that all Men, at one time or other, are put into ſuch a capacity, as that (through the Grace of God) they may be eternally ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 10, 18, 19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. <hi>John</hi> 3.17.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now there is not one word of Free-will in thoſe words, as quoted by himſelf, nor yet in the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34587:62"/>whole Articles in that Confeſſion, ſo that he quarrels with his own ſhaddow, and not with us; for we ſay, through the Grace of God.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe we had let fall ſuch Words as his Friend Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath uſed about Free-will, in his <hi>Call to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted:</hi> Oh! what a noiſe would he have made about our Ears. His Words are theſe: 1. In his Preſace, <q>And for the point of Free-will, which you harp ſo long upon, Divines are not ſo much diſagreed about it as you imagine, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> as well as <hi>Pelagius, Calvin</hi> as well as <hi>Arminius,</hi> the <hi>Dominicans</hi> as well as the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> all do generally maintain that Man hath Free-will.</q> No man of Brains denyeth that a Man hath a Will that is naturally free; it's free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m Violence, and it's a Self-determining principle: <q>In <hi>page</hi> 31. We are commanded to tell you, what thoughts of Kindneſs God hath towards you, and how happy, how certainly and unſpeakably happy you may be, if you will, <hi>page</hi> 32. I do here in the Name of the Lord of Life, proclaim to you all that hear me this day, to the worſt of you, to the greateſt, to the oldeſt Sinner, that you may have Mercy and Salvation, if you will but turn; there is Mercy in God, there is ſufficiency in the Satisfaction of Chriſt, the promiſe is free, and full, and univerſal; you may have Life, if you will but turn; <hi>page</hi> 90. If nothing will ſerve turn, but Men will yet refuſe to turn, we are next to conſider who it's long of, if they be damned: And this brings me to the laſt Doctrine; which is, That if after all this Men will not turn, it is not long of God that they are condemned, but of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, even of their own Wilfulneſs: They
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34587:62"/>dye, becauſe they will dye; that is, becauſe they will not turn; if you will go to Hell, what Remedy? God here acquits himſelf of your Blood, it ſhall not lye on him if you be loſt; <hi>pag.</hi> 102. But you ſeem to intimate all this while, that Man hath Free-will; his Anſwer is, The Diſpute about Free-will is beyond your Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſhall therefore now trouble you with no more than this about it; your Will is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a free, that is, a ſelf-determining Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but it is vitiouſly inclined, and backward to do good; but that is the wickedneſs of it, which deſerveth the puniſhment; your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability is your very unwillingneſs it ſelf, which excuſeth not your ſin, but maketh it the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; <hi>page</hi> 44. And think not to exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ate I by ſaying, that it was only for his Elect, for it was thy ſin, and the ſin of all the World that lay upon our Redeemer; and his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Satisfaction is ſufficient for all, and the fruits of it are offered to one as well as another: But it is true, that it was never the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Mind to pardon and ſave any, that would not by Faith and Repentance be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. And in the next page he ſaith, If there be any man that cannot reconcile this truth with the Doctrine of Predeſtination, or the actual damnation of the Wicked, that's his own Ignorance, he hath no pretence left to deny or queſtion therefore the truth of the point in hand, for this is confirmed by the Oath of God, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11.) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt not be diſtorted, to reduce it to other points, but doubtful points muſt rather be reduced to it, and certain Truths muſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34587:63"/>be believed to agree with it, tho' our ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Brains do hardly diſcern the Agreement.</q> Thus far Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and now let him rail at him if he pieaſes, for we have given him no occaſion; but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath aſſigned the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> to be the cauſe.</p>
               <p>But, (ſaith Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) The <hi>Fourth</hi> Error the Anabaptiſts hold, is, That a Perſon truly juſtified and ſanctified, and ſo a branch in Chriſt, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, may yet fall away, and be eternally damned, and cites part of the <hi>18th.</hi> Artitle of the fore-mentioned Confeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I will therefore deal impartially, and recite the whole Article, with the Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                     <desc>•••••…</desc>
                  </gap> at large, and then the World will ſee, that his peevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hneſs againſt us is without any juſt cauſe: Article <hi>18th.</hi> That ſuch who are true Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, even Branches in Chriſt the Vine, (and that in his Account, whom he exhorts to abide in him, <hi>John</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>I am the true vine, and my Father is the Husbandman, every branch in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh away; and every branch that beareth fruit, be purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit: Now ye are clean, through the word which I have ſpoken unto you, abide in me, and I in you; as the branch cannot bear fruit of it ſelf, except it abide in the vine, no more can ye, except ye abide in me: I am the vine, ye are the branches, he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit, for without me ye can do nothing;</hi>) or ſuch who have Charity out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Now the end of the Commandment is Charity, out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned;</hi> may nevertheleſs for want of Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34587:63"/>ſwerve and turn aſide from the ſame, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>From which ſome having ſwerved, have turned aſide unto vain jangling, deſiring to be Teachers of the Law, underſtanding neither what they ſay, nor what they affirm;</hi> and become as withered branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, caſt into the fire and burned, <hi>John</hi> 15. <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch, and is withered, and men gather them, and caſt them into the fire, and they are burned: But ſuch who add unto their faith virtue, and to virtue knowledge, and to knowledge temperance,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. <hi>Such ſhall never fall:</hi> Ver. 8, 9, 10. <hi>For if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be barren, nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: But he that lacketh theſe things, is blind, and cannot ſee afar off; and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old ſins: Wherefore the rather Brethren, give diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure; for if ye do thoſe things, ye ſhall never fall. 'Tis impoſſible for all the falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets that are, and are to come, to deceive ſuch, for they are kept by the power of God, through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5.</p>
               <p>I have often wiſhed, that all Creeds had been delivered only in the Words of Holy Scripture, that it might have prevented thoſe vain Janglings which the World hath been filled with about them; and herein I have my Hearts deſire in this Article: For the Reader may obſerve, that it is delivered in the plain, poſitive and expreſs words of Scripture: And yet, Behold! the fury of this Man's unbridled paſſion: For, he hath no ſooner recited the Words of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, but he crys out, <hi>Abominable Doctrine!</hi> falſe, dangerous, and uncomfortable Doctrine! doth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34587:64"/>this man pretend to be a Goſpel-miniſter, and yet dare thus let fly his Rage and Malice againſt Chriſt himſelf, and his Bleſſed Apoſtles? Oh! what a paſs is this World come to?</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſay no more to ſuch horrid Trifling as this, for all he ſays againſt us, is a ſtone flung at the head, (not of the general Anabaptiſts, as he ſaith) but at the head of Chriſt, and his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours: I pray God give him Repentance for it, that he may recover himſelf out of the ſnare of the Devil, who leads him captive at his Will.</p>
               <p>He proceeds in his falſe Accuſations againſt us, and ſaith, that the fifth Error of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts is, They diſown all Miniſters, Chriſtians, and Churches of Chriſt, to be any Miniſters, Churches or Chriſtians at all, but only ſuch as are gathered in their way, that is, by dipping: And for this he quotes part of the <hi>11th.</hi> Article, which is miſprinted in his Book the <hi>14th.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
               <p>I muſt be forced to recite the whole Article, becauſe of his falſe Repreſentation of it; but that is a ſmall thing in his Eyes, to belye the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, and abuſe them, for his Book is full of ſuch Railery.</p>
               <p>Article <hi>11th.</hi> of our Confeſſion of Faith, <q>That the right and only way of gathering Churches, (according to Chriſt's appointment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 23.) is firſt to teach, or preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel (<hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16.) to the Sons and Daughters of Men, and then to baptize (that is, to dip) in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, or in the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, ſuch only of them as profeſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34587:64"/>towards God, and Faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8. And as for all ſuch who preach not this Doctrine, but inſtead thereof, that Scriptureleſs thing of Sprinkling of Infants, (falſly called Baptiſm) whereby the pure Word of God is made of noue effect, and the New-Teſtament way of bringing in Members into the Church, by Regeneration, caſt out, when as the Bond-woman and her Son, that is to ſay, the Old Teſtament-way of bringing in Children into the Church by Generation, is caſt out, as ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24, 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8, 9. All ſuch we utterly deny, foraſmuch as we are commanded to have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but rather to reprove them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</q> This is the Article he quarrels with, and by the Grace of God we will abide by it, as the true Way and Order of planting a right Goſpel-Church.</p>
               <p>Now pray Obſerve, how this Man doth abuſe us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that here is nothing ſpoken of in this Article, but the right way of gathering Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, according to Chriſt's appointment, and we only deny them to be a true Viſible Church, who do not thus admit Members by Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but by Generation only; and we have great reaſon ſo to do, becauſe they have only Humane Invention for their Foundation, and not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God's Word; as I have already ſhewed in this Treatiſe, to which I refer you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He tells his People, that we are you ſee no Churches, no Miniſters, no Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:34587:65"/>whereas there is nothing of Miniſters intended in this Article, as all may ſee that read it; but that of Miniſters, under the Name of Elders, or Paſtors, is contained in the <hi>15th.</hi> Article: But he that writes in haſte, may repent at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſaith, We do by that make them no Chriſtians: I muſt confeſs I know not what his People are, but I hope they are men of greater Charity and Moderation than their Prieſt, or elſe I am ſure they are not well qualified Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. But how can he think ſo from that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle? when the deſign thereof is, to ſhew who are orderly Members of a true viſible Church, and do therein declare, that every one before they are admitted to baptiſm, are to be true penitent Believers; and he knows 'tis our avowed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple not to admit any other, but ſuch only that (in the judgment of Charity) are ſo. What ſorts of Perſons he accounts Chriſtians, I know not; but I do account ſuch to be ſo, that are true penitent Believers, and I hope there are many ſuch in the World, altho' they do not agree with us about ſome of the external modes of Worſhip; but this ſeems to be done on purpoſe, to exaſperate the Spirits of his People againſt us, but I hope they will not be ſo unwiſe, as to mind what ſuch a Clamorous Pen ſaith againſt us, without better evidence.</p>
               <p>Having cleared our ſelves from this Abuſe, I think it highly reaſonable, to know who it is he owns for Churches and Miniſters; for thoſe that are rightly conſtituted according to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Pattern he is againſt; ſo that it muſt be ſome others.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34587:65"/>
               <p>Now in <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 6. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſaith, Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will be a Member of the Chriſtian Church, muſt be baptized.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He tells us, That Perſons being knit to Chriſt, by a vital union, as they are living branches in him, and the Elect of God, is not a ground for Baptiſm, and yet he confeſſes that thus only the Elect are in Covenant.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When he comes to give us an account, who are in the viſible Covenant, (which in his Language is viſible Church-members) he ſaith, <hi>page</hi> 7. Thus all who profeſs Chriſt, Tares and Wheat, Wiſe Virgins and Fooliſh, this is the ground of Baptiſm. He is much miſtaken about the Parable of the Tares, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. to apply it to Viſible Church-members; for our Lord doth not ſay, the Field is the Church, but the field is the World: The good Seed are the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Kingdom, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Church) and the Tares are the Children of the Wicked One, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Devil); the Harveſt is the end of this World, and the Reapers are the Angels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now had I been to plead againſt ſome of the curſed perſecuting Tyrants of the World, or againſt thoſe bloody perſecuting Principles and Practices of your Old Friend, <hi>John Calvin,</hi> I would have uſed this Text for an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as genuine and proper, but it hath no relation to the viſible Church; for the Tares are the Rabble of the wicked, out of the viſible Church, and ſuch who ſhall be damned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternally, for the Angels ſhall caſt them into a Furnace of fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But however, it ſeems they will ſerve Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to make Church-members of; for he ſaith in the words following, They are to be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34587:66"/>accounted Believers in Covenant, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be baptized, and that all Infants of ſuch believing Parents are in the Covenant of Grace, and yet in the ſame page he ſaith, We do not baptize perſons as the Elect of God, or Infants, as the Infants of the Elect, for we do not know who belong to the Election of Grace: But ſelf-contradictions are common with him.</p>
               <p>I ſhall make ſome few Remarks upon it, and ſo proceed to what I intend.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That if all the unconverted Hypocrites, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all that profeſs the Chriſtian Name, be but baptized, they are Believers in the Covenant of Grace; then by his own Principle they muſt all be ſaved, for they can never fall totally and finally.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That if all the Infants of ſuch are in the Covenant of Grace, then they alſo muſt needs be ſaved by his Doctrine. It's an eaſie way to bring Perſons into the Covenant of Grace, if ſprinkling a little cold Water on their Faces will do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That notwithſtanding all this, (it ſeems) he doth not know that any one, either of his Church-members, or their Infants, are in the Covenant of Grace, neither doth he baptize them as ſuch; for he plainly confeſſes, he doth not know who belongs to the Election of Grace: Then it's as plain, that he is not ſure, that any of his Members, or their Infants, ſhall be ſaved, and then they are at charge to maintan him to very little purpoſe. Nay further, he doth not know, (by this confuſed way of arguing) that any of thoſe Churches, Miniſters, or Chriſtians, that belong to thoſe viſible Churches he talks of, are in any more hopes of Salvation, than
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34587:66"/>thoſe Heathens he ſpeaks of in another place, whom he (with <hi>Calvin</hi> of old) condemns to the pit of Hell, for no other imaginable Reaſon than the Decree of God, built only upon this Suppoſition, becauſe God will have it ſo: But God will not entruſt theſe raſn Men to be Judges of the World, <hi>For he hath committed all Judgment to the Son;</hi> otherwiſe the poor Anabaptiſts would be under bad Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>I now proceed to proſecute my Deſign, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover who it is that he intends by Miniſters. By Miniſters he muſt needs intend thoſe that were before deſcribed to be Members, <hi>viz.</hi> Either his carnal Profeſſors, or Infants born of them: Infants he cannot mean, becauſe they are not capable. If you would therefore be ſatisfied, he hath told you, it is all the Miniſters that profeſs Chriſt, beſides thoſe of our way: For there lyes the Antitheſis: For he ſaith, we diſown them all ſo to be, but our ſelves, and he owns them, or elſe he hath no reaſon to be angry with us. I hope we are not to underſtand, that he is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with us for diſowning them whom he diſowns.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, The Memberſhip and Miniſtry of the Presbyterians, Epiſcopal and Romiſh Church, are all built upon the ſame foundation, which will appear if you ask but a few Queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Que.</hi> Whether the Presbyterians do not own the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a true Church? Their Anſwer muſt be, Yes, becauſe we received our Baptiſm from them, and never repeated it, and therefore they muſt be a true Church, or elſe our Baptiſm is no true Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Que.</hi> Whether the Presbyterians do not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34587:67"/>own the Biſhops, and their Clergy, to be true Miniſters? They muſt tell you, Yes; becauſe we received our Ordination from the Biſhops, and therefore if they are not true Miniſters, we have no pretence ſo to be, for we never repeated our Ordination, which I ſuppoſe (among others) is alſo the caſe of Mr. <hi>Harriſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Que.</hi> When the Epiſcopal Miniſters have been asked, Whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be a true Church? They have often given this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Yes: For if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be not a true Church, we can't (ſay they) be true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; for we received our Baptiſm from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and never repeated it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be a true Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Que.</hi> If you ask them alſo this Queſtion, Whether the Prelates of the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> be true Miniſters? They anſwer, Yes: For we received our Ordination from them, and never repeated it; therefore they muſt be true Miniſters.</p>
               <p>Beſides, If any Man that is a Prieſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> become a Proſelite to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon recanting of his Popiſh Errors he is admitted to the Miniſtry, without re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</p>
               <p>Moreover, They have all three profeſſed the ſame Principles and Spirit of Perſecution, againſt thoſe that differ from them in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as is manifeſt to all the World.</p>
               <p>Thus I think I have made good my Poſition; and alſo ſhewn, That the Mother of Harlots, and her two Daughters, ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> are built upon the ſame Foundation, as to their Memberſhip and Miniſtry, and are acted by the ſame Spirit of Perſecution. Theſe are the marks
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34587:67"/>of falſe Churches, and not of the true Spouſe and Wife of Chriſt; and this hath exactly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled that prediction, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.19. as to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of it; <hi>The great City was divided into three parts;</hi> and I hope the latter is beginning to be fullfilled; <hi>and the Cities of the Nations</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional-Churches) <hi>fell, and great Babylon</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Rome) <hi>came in remembrance before God:</hi> For thanks be to God, the Earth hath holpen the Woman, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the true Church) and we have now by the Favour of our Rulers, the Liberty of our Religion given us by Law.</p>
               <p>The ſixth Error he charges us with, is employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many weak, ignorant Men, to preach, that have Pride and Confidence enough to think themſelves fit to teach others, who have yet more need to be taught themſelves the very firſt Principles of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is not five whole Lines, and yet all this opprobrious Language, weak, ignorant, proud and confident: But why did not this Man of profound Learning and Parts, (in his own Conceit) tell us of ſome of thoſe many that he mentions, who have need to be taught the very firſt Principles of Religion; and tell us how they may attain to greater perfection in Knowledge. I dare ſay, they muſt not come to learn of him; for I hope we have no Teacher of our way, but underſtands the ſix Principles of Chriſt's Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. better than he doth, or elſe they are very ignorant. It's our care to inſtruct e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, before they are baptized, into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe things, and by theſe two Treatiſes it's manifeſt, that Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> is more ignorant about the true Baptiſm, and the gathering of a true
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34587:68"/>Goſpel-Church than any of our Teachers can poſſibly be, for they own and contend for both; but he ſets himſelf to oppoſe both Chriſt and his Apoſtles therein. But, ſaith he, it's theſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Men, that manage two Callings, the Miniſtry and a private Trade, that broach moſt of theſe Errors.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Did not the Apoſtles follow their Callings, after they were ordained? divers of them were Fiſher-men, and followed that employment, after they were Apoſtles: And the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> wrought at the Trade of a Tent-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, that he might make the Goſpel without charge: And in <hi>Acts</hi> 20.34, &amp;c. he makes this ſolemn Appeal to an Aſſembly of Miniſters; <hi>Yea, you your ſelves know, that theſe hands have miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my neceſſities, and to them that were with me: I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labouring ye ought to ſupport the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jeſus, how he ſaid, it is more bleſſed to give than to receive:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> you know was brought up a Scholar, and was certainly a more Learned and Excellent Man than Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> and yet he did not diſdain to join labour with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. And it's certainly moſt commendable, for any Miniſter of Chriſt that hath ability of Body, to labour with his hands in an honeſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, according to the Apoſtle's Example; but if he be uncapable, the Church ought to maintain him; for the Labourer is worthy of his Hire, and the Work-man of his Meat: But ſuch that are Loiterers, and not Labourers, who ſeek the Fleece more than the Flock, if they have any thing, it's more than they deſerve.</p>
               <p>As for what he ſaith about ability for the Work
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34587:68"/>of the Miniſtry, had he but conſidered who he had been writing to, he might have ſav'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the labour, he knowing what is ſaid upon that Subject in the <hi>15th.</hi> and <hi>16th.</hi> Articles of our Confeſſion of Faith, which I am certain he knows not how to mend, nor well to imitate; and if I thought I could prevail with him, I would (as a Friend) deſire him to read our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, <hi>iterum atque iterum,</hi> and compare it with the Holy Scriptures, and he would learn more true Divinity from it, then he ever did in the Univerſity, if ever he was of any.</p>
               <p>As for his Negation about a Miniſters Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, I do not concede thereto; for he ſaith, Parts and Gifts do not make a Man a Miniſter. Now let us hear what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8. <hi>He gave gifts unto men,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>And he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts and ſome Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 6, 7, 8. <hi>Having then gifts differing,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 12.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>But the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal: For to one is given by the Spirit the word of Wiſdom, to another</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But all theſe worketh that one and the ſelf-ſame Spirit, dividing to every man ſeverally as he will:</hi> But what are theſe Gifts given for? the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> reſolves the Queſtion, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>As every man hath received the Gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold Grace of God: If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God; if any man miniſter, let him do it as of the ability that God giveth, that God in all things may be glorified through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe and dominion for ever and ever, Amen.</hi> From theſe and divers other places of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34587:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>Holy Scripture, it doth appear that the Spirit is able to fit men for the Work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, without Humane Learning; but all the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning in the World will not fit any man for that Work, without the Gifts of the Spirit: For we have always ſound, that the moſt Learned Men in Arts and Sciences, have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly introduced the greateſt Errors into the Church.</p>
               <p>As for what you ſay about Ordination, it reſpects ſettled Miniſters, as Paſtors of Churches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But it's as true, from the very Qualifications laid down in <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> concerning Elders or Paſtors, that it's both lawful, and a Duty, for unordained men to preach, if they are fitted for that work: For how elſe ſhould the Churches know, when they chooſe them to that Office, that they are fit to teach, and able by ſound Doctrine to exhort and convince Gain-ſayers, if they had never been exerciſed before in that Work? Thus I have anſwered all that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be ſpoken to in Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s two Treatiſes, and that it may be bleſſed to all thoſe good Ends and Purpoſes for which it is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is the Hearty Prayer of him, who ſubſcribes himſelf</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>A ſincere Lover of your Souls,</hi> W. R.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:34587:69"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
